<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Zayde a Spanish history, being a pleasant and witty novel : in two parts, compleat / originally written in French by Monsieur Segray ; done into English by P. Porter, Esq.</title>
            <title>Zaïde. English</title>
            <author>La Fayette, Madame de (Marie-Madeleine Pioche de La Vergne), 1634-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 253 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L173A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12090444</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12090444</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53855</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53855)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 74:5 or 638:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Zayde a Spanish history, being a pleasant and witty novel : in two parts, compleat / originally written in French by Monsieur Segray ; done into English by P. Porter, Esq.</title>
                  <title>Zaïde. English</title>
                  <author>La Fayette, Madame de (Marie-Madeleine Pioche de La Vergne), 1634-1693.</author>
                  <author>Segrais, Jean Regnauld de, 1624-1701.</author>
                  <author>Porter, P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 175, [3]; 192 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Milbourn for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Zaïde.</note>
                  <note>Written by Madame de La Fayette with the assistance of Segrais. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>In 2 parts; pt. 2 (Wing L173A, found at reel 638:5) has special t.p.: Zayde ... the second and last part ... London : Printed by T.M. for William Cademan, 1678, and separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end of pt. 1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library and Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53855:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53855:1"/>
            <p>ZAYDE, A Spaniſh Hiſtory. Being a Pleaſant and Witty NOVEL. The Second and Laſt Part. Originally Written in <hi>French,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Monſieur <hi>SEGRAY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Done into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>P. PORTER,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the <hi>Pope</hi>'s-<hi>Head</hi> in the Lower-Walk of the <hi>New-Exchange,</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53855:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53855:2"/>
            <head>ZAYDE, A Spaniſh Hiſtory. A NOVEL. THE SECOND PART.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> found himſelf in the Court of <hi>Leon;</hi> the ſight of a Place where he had been ſo Happy, renewed in him the Remembrance of his paſs'd Fortune, and awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened his Hatred againſt Don <hi>Garcia:</hi> The Regret of having loſt <hi>Zayde,</hi> gave place (for ſome Moments) to the Impetuoſity of his Rage: All his Thoughts were fill'd with a Deſire to let that Prince know, how little he valued all the bad Uſage he might receive from him.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:53855:3"/>
            <p>While his Mind was buſied about theſe Thoughts, he ſaw <hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Room, followed by the Prince of <hi>Leon;</hi> The ſight of both theſe preſent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in ſo private a Place, and at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, did ſo ſurprize him, that he was not able to conceal it: He went back ſome Steps; and his Aſtoniſhment did ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, that his Countenance betray'd the variety of Thoughts that crowded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Imagination: In-ſo-much, that Don <hi>Garcias,</hi> breaking Silence, told him; I am miſtaken, my dear <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> if you are not yet ignorant of all the Alterations that happened in this Court: Do you doubt my being Lawful Poſſeſſor of <hi>Hermeneſilde?</hi> I am truly, added he; and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting to compleat my Happineſs, but your Conſent, and your being a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it: With that, he Embraced him; <hi>Hermeneſilde</hi> did the like; and both the one, and the other, pray'd him to forgive them the Misfortunes which they had cauſed him. Sir, ſaid <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> (throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf at the Prince's Feet) I rather ought to beg Pardon of you, for thoſe bad Suſpicions I had of you; though, at the ſame time, I muſt confeſs, I could not have any other of your Courtſhip to my Siſter; but, I hope, you will be pleas'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53855:3"/>to grant it to the firſt Impulſe of ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary a Surprize, and to the little Appearance I ſaw of the Favour you have done to my Siſter. You might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect better things from her Beauty, and my Love (Replyed Don <hi>Garcias</hi>): I Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure you, to pardon what ſhe has done without your Conſent, for a Prince whoſe Heart ſhe knew ſo well. Sir, anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> Succeſs has ſo well juſtified her Conduct, that ſhe has cauſe to blame me, for endeavouring to oppoſe her Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. After this, Don <hi>Garcias</hi> told <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneſilde,</hi> that, being it was late, ſhe would (perhaps) be glad to retire; and, that he would be glad alſo, to ſtay ſome Moments with <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> alone.</p>
            <p>When they were by themſelves, he Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> with great Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Friendſhip. <hi>I</hi> dare not hope (ſaid he) you can forget what is paſſed: <hi>I</hi> only intreat you to remember the Friendſhip that was betwixt us; and to think, that if <hi>I</hi> have been wanting to what I ow'd you, it was by the Faſcination of a Paſſion, that bereaves a Man of his Reaſon. <hi>I</hi> am ſo full of Surprize, Sir, (ſaid <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) that <hi>I</hi> can make you no Anſwer: <hi>I</hi> ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect my own Eyes; and cannot believe my ſelf ſo Happy, as to find again that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53855:4"/>ſame Goodneſs, which <hi>I</hi> have heretofore experimented in you: But, my Lord, give me leave to ask you, who it is, to whom <hi>I</hi> owe this happy Return? You ask too many Queſtions at once (Replyed the Prince; yet, though <hi>I</hi> need a longer time to ſatisfy your Curioſity, <hi>I</hi> will tell you, in few Words; for, <hi>I</hi> will not put off, for the leaſt time, what may juſtify my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings towards you.</p>
            <p>Then he went about to tell him the beginning of his Paſſion for <hi>Hermeneſilde,</hi> and the ſhare Don <hi>Ramires</hi> had in it: But <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to ſave him that Labour, told him, That he had learnt all that had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Day of his parting from <hi>Leon;</hi> and, that he was only ignorant of what had happened ſince that time.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The HISTORY of Don <hi>Garcia</hi> &amp; <hi>Hermeneſilde.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DOubtleſs, the Information you received of my Weakneſs, in conſenting to your Baniſhment from Court, made you go away as you did: After your finding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53855:4"/>out, by <hi>Nugna Bella</hi>'s Miſtake offending you the Letter ſhe writ to Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> what we, with ſo much Induſtry, endeavoured to keep from your knowledge: Don <hi>Ramires</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Letter which was directed to you; and ſoon perceived the Miſtake; for which, he was extreamly perplexed; <hi>I</hi> was no leſs troubled; we were equally Guilty, too in a different manner. But the News of your Departure, gave him no ſmall Joy; nor was <hi>I,</hi> then, ſorry for it: But, when <hi>I</hi> reflected upon your Condition, and that I was the Cauſe of your Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; <hi>I</hi> was infinitly troubled at it; <hi>I</hi> ſaw, <hi>I</hi> was much in the wrong, to have ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly conceal'd from you the Paſſion <hi>I</hi> had for <hi>Hermeneſilde.</hi> My Opinion was then, That the Nature of my Inclination for her, was not to be blam'd or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd: It came into my Thoughts ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, to ſend after you; and <hi>I</hi> had certainly done it, if <hi>I</hi> had been the only Perſon in Fault; But the Intereſt of <hi>Nug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Bella,</hi> and Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> were invincible Obſtacles to your Return. <hi>I</hi> concealed my Thoughts from them, and made uſe of all wayes poſſible, to make me forget you: Your Departure made a great Noiſe; and it was variouſly talked of, according to Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Inclinations. When <hi>I</hi> found my ſelf
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53855:5"/>looſe from the ſtay of your Counſels, and gave my ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>f over to Don <hi>Ramires</hi> his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who thought it his Intreſt to ſee me more Abſolute; I fell at open Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the King: who then found, he was miſtaken in the opinion he had, that it was you that put me upon doing thoſe things, which had been ſo diſpleaſing to him; our Miſ-underſtandings grew Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; the Queen's Endeavours proved fruitleſs; and Things were come to that paſs, that all believed I meant in good Earneſt, to form a Party. Nevertheleſs, <hi>I</hi> believe, <hi>I</hi> ſhould not have taken that Reſolution, were it not for your Father, who (by the means of ſome People that he had placed about your Siſter, underſtood the Love <hi>I</hi> had for her) ſent me word, that, if <hi>I</hi> would Marry her, he would Raiſe me a conſiderable Army, and furniſh me with what Mony and ſtrong Places, that might be neceſſary to compel the King (my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to give me a ſhare in the Soveraigne Government: You know, what Influence my Paſſions have upon me; and what Power Love, and Ambition, have over my Heart: Both the one, and the other, were anſwered by the Offers that were made me; and my Vertue was too feeble, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt their Temptations, being no longer ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53855:5"/>by the Strength of your Advice. <hi>I</hi> accepted, with Joy, his Offers; but, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>I</hi> would fully reſolve to engage my ſelf, <hi>I</hi> deſired to know, who were to be of the Party <hi>I</hi> intended to Head? <hi>I</hi> was told, there were many Perſons of great Quality; amongſt others, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> one of the Counts of <hi>Caſtile: I</hi> found alſo, that <hi>Nugnes Fernan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> and he, required <hi>I</hi> ſhould own them as Soveraign Princes: This Propoſition ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd me; and <hi>I</hi> was aſhamed, to conſent, to an Act ſo prejudicial to the State, out of an over eagerneſs to Reigne: But Don <hi>Ramires</hi> his Intereſt made me paſs over all: He aſſured thoſe that treated for the Counts of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> they ſhould prevail with me, to do what they deſired, upon condition, that he might be ſecured to have <hi>Nugna Bella.</hi> He brought me to demand her for him; <hi>I</hi> did it with Joy, and it was granted me; ſo that, our Treaty was concluded in few Dayes. <hi>I</hi> could not reſolve to put off my enjoying <hi>Hermeneſilde,</hi> untill the end of the War; and therefore, <hi>I</hi> ſent word to <hi>Nugnes Fernando,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> would carry her away with me, at my going from Court; He conſented to it: Now, all my care was only, how <hi>I</hi> ſhould bring it about; Don <hi>Ramires</hi> was as much concern'd as <hi>I;</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:53855:6"/>becauſe Don <hi>Diego Porcellos</hi> thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed away at the ſame time. We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved (when the Queen ſhould go out of the Town to take the Aire) to make the Coach-man that was to drive <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> and <hi>Hermeneſilde,</hi> to leave that Road the Queen ſhould take, and to drive di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to <hi>Palence,</hi> a Town that was in my power, and where I was to meet <hi>Nugnes Fernando.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which, was executed with more ſucceſs than we hoped for: I married <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneſilde</hi> that very Night, for ſo, Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and my Love required; beſides that, it tyed <hi>Nugnes Fernando</hi> more cloſe to my Intereſt: In the mid'ſt of our Merriments we ſpoke of you with Regret: I confeſs'd to your Father what occaſion'd your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, we lamented our Misfortune of being Ignorant in what part of the world you were gon to. I could not ſatisfie my ſelf without you, and I was unconſalable for your loſs; I looked upon Don <hi>Ramires</hi> with horror, as the cauſer of my fault: His marriage was put off, becauſe <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> would ſtay for her Father, who ſtay'd behind in <hi>Caſtile,</hi> to gather the Troops which were raiſed there.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53855:6"/>
               <p>In the mean time, moſt part of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom declared for me, for all that, the King had a conſiderable Army, and made Head againſt me, many Battels we refought; in the firſt of which, Don <hi>Ramires</hi> was Kill'd upon the Spot; for which, <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> appeared very much Afflicted; your Siſter was witneſs of her Grief, and took pains to comfort her. In leſs than too months I made ſo conſiderable a progreſs, that the Queen deſpairing of better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, perſwaded the King to come to an Accomodation: She came towards the place where I was; ſhe told me the King was reſolved to ſeek out a quiet Retreat, and to depoſe himſelf, and reſigne his Throne to me; that he would only reſerve to himſelf the Soveraignty of <hi>Zamara,</hi> to paſs the reſt of his days in, and that of <hi>Oviedo,</hi> to beſtow upon my Brother. It were hard to reject ſuch advantagious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers: I accepted of them; all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the accompliſhment of this Treaty we performed: I came to <hi>Leon,</hi> where I ſaw the King; he reſigned to me his Crown, and parted that very day for <hi>Zemara.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Give me leave Sir, interrupted <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to tell you my wonder at all this: Stay a little, ſaid Don <hi>Garcia,</hi> untill I have told
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53855:7"/>you what became of <hi>Nugna Bella:</hi> I know not whether what I am going to tell you, will make you glad or ſorry, for I am ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of your thoughts of her. I have none Sir, anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> but a calme indifference for her. Then you will hear me out, without much pain, replyed the King: Preſently after the Peace was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, She came to <hi>Leon</hi> with the Queen; ſhe ſeemed to wiſh for your return: I ſpoke to her of you, and I found in her a hearty Repentance for her Infidelity to you. We reſolved to make a diligent ſearch after you, though we found it difficult, not knowing to what corner of the Earth you were gon to: She told me, if any one could give me light in it, it muſt be Don <hi>Olmond:</hi> I ſent for him at that very inſtant; I conjur'd him, to tell me where you were: He told me, That ſince my being Marryed, and the Death of Don <hi>Ramires,</hi> he had often a great mind to ſpeak to me of you; judging, that the reaſons that cauſed your abſence, might now be ceaſed; but that being not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of the place of your abode, he did believe it to no purpoſe: Laſtly, that he had very lately received a Letter from you, wherein you gave him no account of your Reſidence, but deſired him to write to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53855:7"/>you to <hi>Taridgone,</hi> which made him judge that you were not out of <hi>Spain:</hi> I imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly diſpatched away ſeveral Officers of my Guard to go look for you; I found by the Letter, you writ to Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> that you knew nothing of the alterations that happen'd: I gave them order not to let you know any thing of the ſtate of the Court, or my intentions; for I fancied to my ſelf an extream pleaſure in being the firſt that ſhould inform you both of the one and the other: Some days after, Don <hi>Olmond</hi> parted likewiſe in queſt of you, with an opinion that he ſhould find you ſooner than thoſe I ſent. <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed extreamly ſatisfied with the hope of ſeeing you again; but her Father, whom I acknowledged as Soveraign Prince (as well as your Father) ſent to the Queen to beg ſhe might be ſuffered to come to him: Though <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> was infinitly grieved at this ſeparation, yet ſhe could not avoid it; ſhe went away: As ſoon as ſhe was Arrived in <hi>Caſtile,</hi> her Father Marryed her againſt her will to a <hi>German</hi>-Prince, whom Curiouſity, or Devotion had brought into <hi>Spain:</hi> he fancied an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary merit in this Stranger, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made choyce of him for his Son-in-Law, he may be both Wiſe and Valiant,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53855:8"/>but neither his Humour nor his Perſon are agreeable; and in a word, <hi>Nugna Bella</hi> is moſt unhappy.</p>
               <p>Thus have you, ſaid the King, all that has happen'd here ſince your departure; and if you are no more concern'd for <hi>Nug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Bella,</hi> and Love me ſtill, I have nothing more in the world to wiſh for, ſince you may be as happy as ever you were, and I ſhall be ſo likewiſe by the return of your Friendſhip. You Confound me Sir, with ſo many, and ſo great favours, anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> I fear I ſhall not be able to make you ſenſible enough of my joy and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments; for my Misfortunes, and my Solitude have ſo accuſtomed me to ſadneſs, that I cannot of a ſuddain ſhake off their impreſſion, which clouds the chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thoughts of my heart.</p>
               <p>After this, the King withdrew, and <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was Conducted to an Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which was prepared for him in the Court. When he ſaw himſelf alone, and made ſome reflection upon his own inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, of ſo advantagious a change, he was angry with himſelf for having ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely given himſelf over to Love.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Zayde,</hi> it is you alone, ſaid he, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders me from enjoying the return of my Fortune, and of a Fortune ſo far above
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53855:8"/>what I loſt: My Father is a Soveraign Prince, my Siſter is a Queen, and I am revenged of all thoſe that betrayed me; and yet am Unfortunate, and would pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe at the hazard of all theſe advantages, the occaſion I have loſt of following you, and ſeeing you once more.</p>
               <p>The next day, all the Court was full of <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s return; the King thought he could never ſhew enough, how much he eſteemed him, and took all the care imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to give publick demonſtrations of it, to Repair, in ſome meaſure, what had paſs'd: So great a favour could be no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to this Lover for the loſs of <hi>Zayde;</hi> nor was it in his power to conceal his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. The King took notice of it, and preſſed him ſo hard to declare the cauſe of it, that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was fain to tell it him. After having informed him of his Paſſion for <hi>Zayde,</hi> and all that had befallen him ſince his departure from <hi>Leon.</hi> Thus Sir, ſaid he, have I been puniſhed for daring to maintain againſt you, that none ought to Love, but after a long acquaintance: I was deceived by a Perſon, whom <hi>I</hi> believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>I</hi> knew well, and this experience could not defend me againſt <hi>Zayde,</hi> whom <hi>I</hi> did not know at all, nor know not yet; and for all this, diſturbs the happy ſtate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53855:9"/>in which you are pleaſed to place me. The King was too ſenſible of Love, and had too great a feeling of all that concern'd <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> not to be touched at his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, he began to conſult with him of the means how to learn ſome tidings of <hi>Zayde;</hi> they reſolved to ſend to <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> to the Houſe where he heard her voyce to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be informed of her Country at, leaſt, and whether ſhe might be gon. <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> who had a deſign to let <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo</hi> know all that had happen'd to him ſince he left his Solitude, laid hold of this occaſion to write to him, and to renew the aſſurances of his Friendſhip towards him.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, the <hi>Mores</hi> taking their time, when the Kingdom of <hi>Leon</hi> was in theſe diſorders, had ſurprized ſeveral Towns, and continued ſtill to enlarge their bounds without ſo much as declaring War. Don <hi>Garcias,</hi> prompted by his natural Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and fortified by <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Valour, reſolves to Invade their Country, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take from them all thoſe places which they had Uſurped. His Brother Don <hi>Ordogno</hi> joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to him, and betwixt them, they brought a powerful Army into the Field, whereof Don <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was made General: He made a very conſiderable Progreſs in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53855:9"/>a very ſhort time, he took divers Towns; he had the better in ſeveral Battels, and at laſt, Beſieges <hi>Talauera,</hi> a place of great Importance, conſiderable for its Scituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Greatneſs. <hi>Abderam,</hi> King of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowa,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Abdala,</hi> came in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to oppoſe the King of <hi>Leon:</hi> He came towards <hi>Talauera,</hi> with hopes to force them to raiſe the Siege. Don <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias,</hi> and the Prince <hi>Ordogno,</hi> having left <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> with part of the Army to ſtreigthen the Town, Marches with the reſt of the Army to meet him in order to fight him. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was extream glad of the employment; for, his aſſurance either to win or dye, would not let him fear any ill ſucceſs. Having no news of <hi>Zayde,</hi> he was more afflicted than ever, with the paſſion he had for her, and his great deſire of ſeeing her; ſo that in ſpite of his Fortune and Glory, being not able to hope for any thing but a miſerable kind of life, he run head-long into all occaſions of ending it.</p>
               <p>The King Marches againſt <hi>Abderame,</hi> whom he found Incamped in an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious poſt, within a days March to <hi>Talauera;</hi> they paſſed ſome days without action, for the <hi>Moores</hi> would not come out of their Poſt; and Don <hi>Garcias</hi> did
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53855:10"/>not think himſelf ſtrong enough to Attack them: In the mean time, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> judged it impoſſible to continue the Siege, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Forces being not numerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to encompaſs the whole Town, and Parties getting into the Town every Night, might put the Beſieged in a poſture of making ſtronger Sallies than he could ſuſtain; and therefore having made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable breach, he reſolved to hazard a general Aſſault, and to endeavour by ſo bold an attempt, to carry the Victory, which otherwiſe was deſperate. He puts this reſult into execution; and after giving all neceſſary orders, he begun the Attack before day, but with ſo much reſolution, and hope to overcome, that he inſpired the ſame courage into all his Men: They performed incredible things, and at laſt, in leſs than two hours, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> carryed the Town: He did what was poſſible to hinder the Souldiers from Plundering, but it was impoſſible to ſtop an Army from it, whom the hope of Plunder encouraged, more than any other motive whatever.</p>
               <p>As he run about the Town himſelf, to prevent the diſorder (which upon ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions are too frequent) he ſaw a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, defending himſelf with incredible Valour againſt a great many; he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53855:10"/>by Retreating, to get into a Caſtle which held out ſtill: Thoſe that attacked him, preſſed him ſo home, that he had been infallibly kill'd, if <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> had not thrown himſelf betwixt them and him, and commanded them to withdraw: He made them aſhamed of the action; they excuſed themſelves, by telling him that, the man they Aſſaulted, was Prince <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lema,</hi> who had kill'd abundance of their Men, and was endeavouring to throw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into that Caſtle. This Name was too famous, by the greatneſs of this Prince, and the general Command he had amongſt the <hi>Mores,</hi> not to be known to <hi>Gonſalvo:</hi> He advances towards him; and this Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Man ſeeing it impoſſible any longer to defend himſelf, deliver'd his Sword, with ſo noble and ſo bold an aire, that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> could no longer doubt, but that he well deſerved the great Reputation which he had gain'd: He gave him to be kept Priſoner to ſome Officers that followed him, and Marches to Summon the Caſtle: He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promis'd Quarter to all that were in it. The Gates were opened for him; he was told (as he enter'd) that there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Arabian</hi> Ladies, who caſt themſelves into it for ſafety. He was Conducted to the place where they were; he enters a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53855:11"/>ſpacious Appartment, richly furniſhed after the Moriſh faſhion; ſeveral Ladies lying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long upon Carpets (by their melancholly ſilence) made appear how ſad they were for their Captivity: they lay at ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, out of reſpect to a Lady Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently Arrayed, that was ſitting upon a Pallet, with her head leaning upon one of her Hands, and with the other wiping her Tears, and hiding her Face, as it were to keep her ſelf for ſome moments from being ſeen by her Enemies: At laſt (at the noiſe which thoſe that followed <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo,</hi> made) comeing into the Room, ſhe turned her Head, and let <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſee it it was <hi>Zayde:</hi> But <hi>Zayde,</hi> far more beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful than he had ever ſeen her, in ſpite of all the grief and trouble that appear'd in her Face. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was ſo ſurpriz'd, that he ſeemed more troubled than <hi>Zayde;</hi> and <hi>Zayde</hi> ſeemed to take courage, and loſe ſome part of her trouble, at the ſight of <hi>Gonſalvo:</hi> They advanced towards one another; and beginning both to ſpeak at once, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> making uſe of the Greek Tongue, asked her pardon for appearing before her like an Enemy: At the ſame time <hi>Zayde</hi> ſaid in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> ſhe fear'd no more thoſe Misfortunes which ſhe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and that this was not the firſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53855:11"/>danger in which he had relieved her: they were ſo amazed to hear each other ſpeaking their Language, and their ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe repreſented to them, ſo plainly, the reaſons why they learnt thoſe Languages, that they both Bluſh'd, and remained ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for ſome time. At laſt <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> broke ſilence, and continuing to make uſe of the Greek Tongue, ſaid, I know not (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam) whether I had reaſon to wiſh as much as I have done, that you might un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand me, perhaps I ſhould not be leſs unhappy: But happen what will, ſince I have the Joy of ſeeing you once again, after having ſo often loſt all hope of you, I will never more complain of my For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. <hi>Zayde</hi> ſeemed ſomewhat puſled at what <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſaid; and looking upon him with thoſe fair eyes, wherein (neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, he could read nothing but Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly. I know not yet (ſaid ſhe to him in her own Language, being not willing to ſpeak any more <hi>Spaniſh</hi>) whether my Father has eſcaped with his Life, amid'ſt ſo many dangers, to which he has expoſed himſelf this day; you will excuſe me if my concern for him hinders me from making Anſwer to what you ſaid. <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> cauſed ſome of thoſe that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, to enquire after what ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53855:12"/>to know: He had the pleaſure to learn that the Prince (whom he ſaved) was <hi>Zayde's</hi> Father; and ſhe ſeemed to be over-joy'd to know by what happy means her Fathers Life came to be ſav'd. After this, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was oblig'd to pay his reſpects to the reſt of the Ladies that were in the Caſtle: He was not a little ſurpris'd to find Don <hi>Olmond</hi> in that Caſtle, of whom, there had been no tydings ſince he went from <hi>Leon</hi> to ſeek him out. Having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Civilities that were due to ſo faithful a Friend, he returned to the place where <hi>Zayde</hi> was. As he began to ſpeak to her, word was brought that the Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Diſorder was ſo great in the Town, that nothing but his Preſence could put a ſtop to it. He was fain to go where his Duty call'd him; he gave the orders that were neceſſary to appeaſe the tumult which the Avarice of the Souldiers, and the terror of the Inhabitants had cauſed: After which, he ſent away an expreſs to the King, to acquaint him with the taking of the Town, and ſo came back with what haſt he could to <hi>Zayde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the Ladies that were with her, were, by chance, at ſome diſtance from her: <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was reſolved to take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of this favourable moment, to ſpeak
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53855:12"/>to her; but as he was going to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her with the declaration of his Paſſion, he felt in himſelf an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Irreſolution, and found that it is not enough at all times to be in a capacity of being underſtood, to make a man reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute enough to declare his mind; he was fearful, nevertheleſs, of loſing an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which he ſo much long'd for; and after, having for ſome time admir'd the Caprice of Chance, that made them be ſo long together, without being able to be acquainted, or to ſpeak to one another: We are now (ſays <hi>Zayde</hi>) far from fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the ſame difficulty, ſince <hi>I</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and you know my Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. <hi>I</hi> fancied my ſelf ſo unhappy (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) in not knowing it, that <hi>I</hi> have learnt it, even when <hi>I</hi> was out of hope, that it ſhould ever be uſeful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair what <hi>I</hi> have endured for not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it. For my part, (Anſwered <hi>Zayde,</hi> Bluſhing) <hi>I</hi> have learnt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue, becauſe it is hard to live in a place without acquiring the Language thereof, that one may not be always in trouble how to make themſelves under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> often underſtood you, Madam, (ſaid <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) and though <hi>I</hi> knew not your
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53855:13"/>Language, yet <hi>I</hi> could give a very exact account of ſome of your Sentiments. <hi>I</hi> am likewiſe perſwaded you ſaw mine much better than <hi>I</hi> did yours. <hi>I</hi> aſſure you (Anſwered <hi>Zayde</hi>) <hi>I</hi> am not ſo quick of Apprehenſion as you take me to be; and that all <hi>I</hi> could judge of you, was, that you were ſometimes very ſad. I alſo let you know the cauſe thereof (replyed <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi>) and <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you knew not the meaning of my words, you could not chufe but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand me: Go not about to deny it Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, for you have Anſwered me with a Severity that may pleaſe you; but ſince <hi>I</hi> found your indifference, how could you avoid finding out Sentiments which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear much more plainly than indifference, and which expound themſelves often e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt our will? Yet <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs <hi>I</hi> obſerved ſometimes thoſe bright eyes turned towards me, after a manner that might give me Joy, if at the ſame time <hi>I</hi> did not believe my ſelf beholding to ſome other, for what was of obliging in them. <hi>I</hi> will not diſ-own, (Anſwered <hi>Zayde</hi>) but that <hi>I</hi> did fancy you like one; but you would have no cauſe to be angry at it, if you knew how often <hi>I</hi> wiſhed you the ſame Perſon whom you reſembled. <hi>I</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53855:13"/>know not Madam (Anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) whether I ſhould fancy what you have ſaid, to be to my advantage; nor can <hi>I</hi> thank you for it, unleſs you did explain your ſelf better: I have told you too much (replyed <hi>Zayde</hi>) to need any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Expoſition; and my laſt words ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidge me to keep it as a ſecret: Sure <hi>I</hi> am reſerv'd for nothing but Misfortunes, (Anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) ſince <hi>I</hi> cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what you ſay, even when you ſpeak to me in <hi>Spaniſh:</hi> But Madam, can you yet be ſo Cruel, as to add more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties to thoſe in which I have liv'd ſo long? <hi>I</hi> muſt dye at your feet, or you muſt tell me who it was you wept ſo much for in <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s Solitude; who it is that my good or bad Fortune has made me reſemble: Doubtleſs my curioſity would not ſtop at theſe two things, if the reſpect I bear you, did not with-hold it; but <hi>I</hi> will wait with patience, until time and your goodneſs will give me leave to ask you more.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Zayde</hi> was going to anſwer, ſome <hi>Arabian</hi> Ladies that were in the Caſtle, deſired to ſpeak to <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> and there came afterwards ſo many other People in, that (with the care the Princeſs took to avoid a particular Conference, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53855:14"/>for him to find any further oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</p>
               <p>He ſhut himſelf up alone, to abandon himſelf to the pleaſure of having found <hi>Zayde</hi> again, and in a place where he had the ſole command. He believed alſo to have obſerved ſome joy in her eyes when ſhe ſaw him; he was very glad that ſhe had learnt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue; and ſhe made uſe of his Language with ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs and promptneſs, as ſoon as ſhe ſaw him, that he flatter'd himſelf with the opinion that he had a great ſhare in the care ſhe took to learn it; at leaſt, the ſight of <hi>Zayde,</hi> and the hope he had, not to be hated by her, made <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> feel all the pleaſure that a Lover (that is not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the affections of his Miſtreſs) can be ſenſible of.</p>
               <p>The return of Don <hi>Olmond</hi> from the Caſtle, whether he had ſent him to place ſome of his Troops, interrupted his thoughts; as he found him in the ſame place with <hi>Zayde,</hi> he thought he might inform himſelf of that fair Princeſſes Birth and Adventures; but he apprehended that he might be in Love with her, and his fear of finding a Rival in the Man he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved his Friend, retarded for a long time his Curioſity; but could not forbear, at
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53855:14"/>laſt, asking Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> by what Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent he was brought to <hi>Talevera.</hi> After he had learnt that he was taken Priſoner, going to look after him at <hi>Tarragon,</hi> he ſpoke to him of <hi>Zulema</hi> firſt, the better to bring on the diſcourſe of <hi>Zayde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You muſt know (ſaid Don <hi>Olmond</hi>) that he is Nephew to the <hi>Caliph Oſman,</hi> and that he ſhould have been in the place of <hi>Carmadan,</hi> that reigns at this day, if he had been as fortunate as his Merit deſerves; he holds yet a conſiderable rank among the <hi>Arabians:</hi> He came into <hi>Spain</hi> to be General of the King of <hi>Cordoua</hi>'s Army, where he has lived with ſo much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Grandeur, that <hi>I</hi> was ſurpriſed at it. At my Arrival here, I found a very agreeable Court: <hi>Belleny,</hi> the Wife of Prince <hi>Oſmin, Zulema</hi>'s Brother, was then here; this Princeſs was no leſs reſpected for her Virtue, than her high Birth: She had with her the Princeſs <hi>Felime,</hi> her Daughter, whoſe Wit and Beauty are full of Charms, though there appears (in both) ſomething of Languiſhing and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly. You have ſeen the incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Beauty of <hi>Zayde,</hi> and you may judge how great my Aſtoniſhment was to find at <hi>Talevera</hi> ſo many Perſons worthy of Admiration. It is true (replyed <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53855:15"/>that <hi>Zayde</hi> is the moſt accompliſh'd Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I ever ſaw; and I queſtion not, but ſhe has a great number of Admirers here, <hi>Alamire,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> is paſſionately in Love with her, anſwered Don <hi>Olmond;</hi> he began to be in Love with her in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and came along with her from thence: <hi>Zulema</hi> ſuffer'd Shipwrack upon the Coaſt of <hi>Catalonia;</hi> he is come (ſince that) into <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Alamire</hi> came to <hi>Talevera</hi> to find out <hi>Zayde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words of Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> ſtruck Don <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> to the heart; they confirm'd him in all his Suſpicions, and he found in an inſtant that all his Imaginations were true; the hopes of being deceived (with which he had ſo often flatter'd himſelf) quite left him; and the Joy which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in his laſt Converſation with <hi>Zayde,</hi> ſerved only to augment his grief. He was no longer in doubt, but that thoſe Tears which ſhe ſhed at <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s, were for <hi>Alamire,</hi> that it was him he was like; and that it was he that carryed her away from the Coaſt of <hi>Catalonia:</hi> Theſe thoughts gave ſo much diſquiet to his mind, that Don <hi>Olmond</hi> believed he was Sick, and gave him to know that he was much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd thereat. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> concealed the cauſe of his Affliction, and was aſhamed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53855:15"/>to own that he was in Love after what he had already ſuffer'd by it: he told him he ſhould be well again in a little while, and ask'd him if he had ever ſeen <hi>Alamire,</hi> whether he was worthy of <hi>Zayde,</hi> or whether ſhe Loved him? I never ſaw him (replyed Don <hi>Olmond</hi>) for he was gone to joyn with <hi>Abderam,</hi> before <hi>I</hi> was brought to this Town; his Reputation is great, but <hi>I</hi> know not whether <hi>Zayde</hi> Loves him or not; but <hi>I</hi> believe it is not eaſie for her to deſpiſe the Application of a Prince, ſo deſerving as he is given out to be, and he appears ſo aſſiduous about her, that it is hard to ſay, that he ſhould be altogether neglected by her; the Princeſs <hi>Pelime,</hi> with whom <hi>I</hi> have contracted a ſincere Friendſhip, in ſpight of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedneſs, in which the People of her Country and Quality live, has often ſpoke to me of <hi>Alamire,</hi> and to judge of him by what ſhe ſays, there cannot be a more accompliſh'd Perſon, or a more paſſionate Lover than he is. If Don <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> had followed the impulſe of his thoughts, he had ask'd many more queſtions of Don <hi>Olmond;</hi> but he was with-held by the fear he had of diſcovering to him what he ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died to conceal; he only asked him what became of <hi>Felime:</hi> Don <hi>Olmond</hi> told him,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53855:16"/>that ſhe was gone after the Princeſs her Mother, to <hi>Oropeſe,</hi> where <hi>Oſmin</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Body of an Army.</p>
               <p>After this, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> withdrew, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take ſome reſt; but in reality, to be at Liberty to Afflict himſelf, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the ſtubbornneſs of his invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Misfortunes. Why did not <hi>I</hi> know that <hi>Zayde</hi> was in Love with <hi>Alamire,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I found her again? If I had been aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of that, when I loſt her, I ſhould have been leſs afflicted for her abſence; I ſhould not be ſo joyful for having found her, nor ſhould I endure now the cruelty of loſing all the hopes ſhe came from giving me. What kind of Deſtiny is mine, that even the ſweetneſs of <hi>Zayde</hi> muſt create me nothing but Misfortune? Why ſhould ſhe ſeem to Countenance my Love, if ſhe approves <hi>Alamires</hi> paſſion? Or what means that wiſh of hers, that I might be the man I reſemble?</p>
               <p>Theſe kind of reflections augmented his Grief; and the next day, which he ought to have wiſhed for with impatience, and which ought to be to him ſo grateful, ſince he was ſure to ſee <hi>Zayde,</hi> and to ſpeak to her; ſeemed to him the moſt frightful of all his Life; for he fancyed, that in ſeeing her, he could hope for no
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53855:16"/>other thing, but the Confirmation of all his Diſaſters.</p>
               <p>About Mid-night, the Meſſenger whom he had ſent to the King, to acquaint him with the taking of the Town, came back with Orders, for <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> to March away at that very inſtant, with all his Cavalry, to joyne the Army. Don <hi>Garcias</hi> knew that the <hi>Moors</hi> expected a conſiderable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit; and as ſoon as he knew that <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> had taken <hi>Talevera,</hi> he thought it expedient, by the benefit of this Victory, togeather all his Forces, and to fall upon the Enemy before they were re-inforced by their new Succours.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſaw the difficulty of executing his Majeſties Orders, by the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he ſhould find to make his Souldiers March, being ſcarce refreſhed after the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue of the precedent Night; yet the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Deſire he had to be at the Battle, made him uſe ſo much Diligence, that he put his Men in a very ſhort time, in a readineſs to March; and he did himſelf the cruel Violence of parting with <hi>Zayde,</hi> without taking his leave of her. He ordered <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lema</hi> to be brought into the ſame Caſtle where the Princeſs was; and commanded him that was Governour of it, to acquaint her with the Reaſons that obliged him to leave <hi>Talavera</hi> in ſuch haſt.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:53855:17"/>
               <p>At Break of Day he put himſelf in the Head of his Cavalry, and began to March with a Sadneſs proportionable to the cauſe of his imagined Grief. When he came near the Camp, he met the King that came out to receive him: He alighted, and went towards him, to give him an account of what paſſed at the taking of <hi>Talavera.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had diſcourſed with him about what concern'd Martial Affairs, he ſpoke to him of his Love: He told him how he had found <hi>Zayde;</hi> but that he had likewiſe found out that Rival, whoſe only Shaddow had created him ſo much trouble. The King told him how much he was concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in all that touched him, and how much he was ſatisfyed with the Victory he had gained. After this, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> went to quarter his Men, and to put them into a Condition, by a few Hours Reſt, to be ready for the Battle which was intended to be given: They had not yet reſolved upon it; for the advantagious Poſt in which the Enemy was, their Number, and the length of the March to them, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd this Reſolution hard to be embraced, and dangerous to be put in Execution. Nevertheleſs, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was for giving Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and the hope he had of meeting <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamire</hi> in the Combat, made him maintain
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53855:17"/>his Opinion with ſo much earneſtneſs, that the giving Battle was reſolved upon the next Day.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arabians</hi> were Encamped in a Plain, within ſight of <hi>Almeras;</hi> their Camp was encompaſſed by great Woods; inſomuch, that there was no Acceſs to them, but by ſuch narrow wayes, that it did ſeem unſafe to attempt it; notwithſtanding, <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> in the Head of the Horſe, begun firſt to paſs the Wood, and appeared firſt in the Plain, followed by ſome Squadrons. The <hi>Arabians</hi> were ſo ſtarted to ſee their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſo near, that they employed the time of Fighting, in conſulting what they had beſt to do; ſo that, they gave the <hi>Spaniards</hi> the leaſure to March all their Men through the Wood, and draw them up in <hi>Battalia,</hi> on the Plain. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> Marched directly towards them, with the left Wing, beat back their Battalions, and put them to a diſorderly Rout: He did not amuſe himſelf to purſue thoſe that fled; but ſeeking up and down, the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> and freſh Lawrels, turns ſhort upon the <hi>Arabian</hi> Infantry: But the right Wing did not fare ſo well; for, the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> routed it, and beat it back to the main Body, which was Commanded by the King of <hi>Leon;</hi> But the King put a ſtop to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53855:18"/>Fury, and repulſed them even to the very Gates of <hi>Almaras;</hi> ſo that, the Foot only was left Commanded by <hi>Abderame,</hi> and ſtoutly attacqued by <hi>Gonſalvo:</hi> This Body of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry ſtood firm to their Ground, and opening their Battalions to the Right and Left, made way for their Archers; which ſo terribly gall'd the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that they could not abide it: <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> Rallied his Men, and Charged them the ſecond and third time; and, at laſt, ſurrounded them on all ſides: But <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> moved with Compaſſion to ſee ſo many Gallant Men knocked on the Head, commanded Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be given to all: The <hi>Arabians</hi> laid down their Arms, and came flocking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, to admire his Clemency, after having felt the ſmart of his Valour. Then likewiſe came the King of <hi>Leon</hi> up to <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> and gave him all the Praiſe that was due to his Courage. They underſtood that King <hi>Abderame</hi> was Retreated during the Shock, and was gotten into <hi>Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Glory which <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> acquired in this Dayes Action, might have given him cauſe to rejoyce; but he felt no other, than Grief of having ſurvived it, and not to meet with <hi>Alamire.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53855:18"/>
               <p>He underſtood afterwards, by ſome of the Priſoners, that this Prince was not in the Army; that he commanded the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforcement, which the Enemy expected; and, that it was the Hope of this Succour, that made them endeavour to avoid coming to a Battle.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Arabians,</hi> having Rallied a part of their Army, and being Re-inforced by the Addition of thoſe Succours which <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> brought to them, and lying under the Walls of a ſtrong City; the King of <hi>Leon</hi> could hope for no other Advantage by his late Victory, but the Glory of having gained it. Nevertheleſs, <hi>Abderame,</hi> under pretence of Burying the Dead, deſired a Truce for ſome few dayes, with deſigne to Commence a Treaty of Peace.</p>
               <p>During the time of this Ceſſation, <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> paſſing from one Quarter of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to another, ſaw upon a little Emmence, two of the Enemies Horſe-men, defending themſelves againſt a good number of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cavalry, who by their multitude, were upon the point of deſtroying them: He was amazed to ſee this Combat, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Truce, at ſo much inequality: He ſent ſome of his Guards, with all ſpeed, to interpoſe, and to know the reaſon of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his: They brought him back word,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53855:19"/>that theſe two <hi>Arabian</hi> Horſe-men had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to paſs their outmoſt Guards, that the Centries were rude in ſtopping them; that they drew their Swords thereupon; and that the reſt of the Guard fell upon them. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſent an Officer to beg theſe two Cavaliers excuſe, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct them whither they deſired to go, beyond all the Guards: This done, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his way, viſiting all the Quarters as he went towards the Kings; ſo that, it was late before he came back. The next Morning, the Officer that was ſent to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the two <hi>Arabians,</hi> came to him, and told him, That one of thoſe whom they Conducted, gave him in charge to tell him, That he was ſorry, that an important Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, which concerned not the War, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him from coming to return him Thanks; and that he was willing he ſhould underſtand, that it was the Prince <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire,</hi> that owed him his Life. When <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> heard the Name of <hi>Alamire,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that this Rival, whom he had ſo great a mind to ſeek all over the World, even when he did not ſo much as know his Name, nor his Country, was then paſſed through his Camp, &amp; in his own fight, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, to go to find out <hi>Zayde:</hi> he was in a maze; all he had power to do, was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53855:19"/>to ask, which way he ſteer'd his Courſe? Being told, towards <hi>Talavera;</hi> he diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all that were in his Tent; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd alone full of deſpair, for not having known that it was <hi>Alamire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How? He has not only eſcaped my Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Revenge, but I muſt likewiſe open him the way to go ſee <hi>Zayde!</hi> This moment he ſees her; he is with her; he tells her by whoſe means he has paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through this Camp: It was only to inſult over me, and up-braid me with my Misfortunes, that he ſent me back word, that he was <hi>Alamire:</hi> But may be, he may not long Regale himſelf at the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of my Misfortunes; and I will ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace my grief, with the pleaſure of being Reveng'd.</p>
               <p>He reſolves at that very inſtant, to ſteal out of the Camp, and to go to <hi>Talavera;</hi> by his Preſence, to interrupt <hi>Alamire,</hi> and <hi>Zayde</hi>'s Interview, and take away his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals Life, or dye before the Princeſſes Eyes. As he was muſing how to execute his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, News was brought him, That ſome of the Enemies Troops appeared not far off of the Camp, and that the King Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded he ſhould go to diſcover them; he was forced to obey, and to defer the Execution of his Purpoſe: He got a Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53855:20"/>and after he had Rid a little way, word was brought him, as he came out of a Wood, that they were only ſome few <hi>Arabians,</hi> that came from Conducting a Convoy. He commanded the Cavalry that were with him, to return to the Camp; and followed by a few of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, he Rid on ſlowly, on purpoſe to ſtay in the Wood until his Cavalry were at ſome diſtance, that he might directly go undiſcover'd to <hi>Talavera.</hi> Being in the middle of a great Walk, he met with an <hi>Arabian</hi> Cavalier, of an excellent Preſence and Meine, that came ſadly along that way: Thoſe that were with <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> by accident, pronounced his Name; at the ſound of which, this Cavalier, that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed plunged in ſome ſerious and deep ſtudy, came to himſelf; and asked them, if he that Rid before alone, were <hi>Gonſalvo?</hi> As ſoon as they anſwered, It was: I ſhall be glad (ſaid he, loud enough to be heard by <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) to ſee a Man of ſo extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary a Merit, and to thank him for the Favours I have received from him: With this he advances towards <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> lifting up the Beavoir of his Helmet to Salute him: But ſo ſoon as he had viewed his Face, he cryed out, O Gods! Is it poſſible, this ſhould be <hi>Gonſalvo?</hi> And looking
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53855:20"/>ſtedfaſtly upon him, he remained without Motion, like a Man that had been Planet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruck, and divided within himſelf, with very different Imaginations: After re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining thus for ſome time; <hi>Alamire</hi> (cryed he of a ſuddain) muſt not let him live for whom <hi>Zayde</hi> is deſign'd, or for whom ſhe reſerves her ſelf. <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> who appear'd aſtoniſht at this Strangers firſt Words and Action; and who, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, expected the Event with a great Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, was likewiſe ſtruck with an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Amazement, when he heard the Names of <hi>Zayde,</hi> and <hi>Alamire;</hi> and ſaw before him this formidable Rival, whom he was going to find out with ſo much Hatred, and deſire of Revenge. I know not (replyed he) whether <hi>Zayde</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for me; but if you be the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> as you make me believe you are, you muſt not hope to poſſeſs her but by my Death: Nor you, but by mine, anſwered <hi>Alamire;</hi> and your words too clearly inform me, that you are the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that cauſes my Misfortune. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> heard but confuſedly theſe laſt Words: He went back ſome Paces, and with-held his impatience to Fight, only to hinder that their Combat might not be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: He commanded thoſe that followed,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53855:21"/>to go further off; but with ſuch an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that they durſt not diſobey: But they with all ſpeed, Rid after the Party that left <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to call back ſome of the principal Officers of the Army, who could not yet be far gone from them. In the mean time, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> and <hi>Almire</hi> began a Combat; where Courage and Reſolution made appear all that could be <hi>Heroick</hi> and Wonderful: <hi>Alamire</hi> was wounded in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Places, that his Strength begun to fail him; and though <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was ſo too, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of an approaching Victory, ſupplyed the Defects of his Ability with new Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour which made him Maſter of this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Life. The King, who by chance was not far from this Wood, drawn thither by the Noiſe and Out-cryes of thoſe that <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> Commanded away, arrived in this place, and ſeparated the Combatants: He underſtood by <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Squire, who came in at that inſtant, his Maſter's Name; and <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſeeing <hi>Alamire</hi> bleed in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, gave order to help him.</p>
               <p>If the King had followed the firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of his angry Thoughts, he had given contrary Orders; but he contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the Command, that the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> ſhould be forth-coming, and turn'd all his care towards the Preſervation
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53855:21"/>of his Favourite. He cauſed him to be carryed to the Camp; <hi>Alamire</hi> was not in a Condition to be carryed ſo far, but was brought to a Caſtle that was not far off. As ſoon as <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was arrived, the King deſired to know what the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans thought of his Wounds: They aſſured him, there was no danger of his Life. Don <hi>Garcias</hi> would not leave him, until he had known from his own Mouth, the occaſion of this Fight. <hi>Gonſolvo,</hi> who had nothing in reſerve from the King, told him the whole Truth: The King being apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, that too long a Diſcourſe would be hurtful to <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Health, would have left him to take his Reſt: But <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> holding him, ſaid; Leave me not, Sir, to the diſorder and confuſion of my Thoughts; Help me to diſ-intangle my ſelf from the new Trouble, which the Actions, and the Words of <hi>Alamire</hi> has put me into: He met me without ſeeming to look for me; He accoſts me like one that would Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement and Thank me; and of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, I ſee him ſurpriz'd, troubl'd, and ready to draw upon me: What could he learn in ſeeing me? Who made him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Intentions? Who made him fancy, that <hi>Zadye</hi> was deſtin'd for me, either by <hi>Zulema,</hi> or by her ſelf? He could not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53855:22"/>know from any but her ſelf, that I was his Rival: And if ſhe has given him an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my Love, it was not to make him fear my Pretenſions: He alſo knows very well, that ſhe is not deſtin'd for me by <hi>Zulema,</hi> who knows me not, who is ignorant of my Paſſion for his Daughter, and whoſe Religion is oppoſite to mine. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, upon what are his Words grounded? and, by what reaſon ſhould my Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance provoke his Anger, rather than my Name? It is hard, my dear <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd the King) to dive into this Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Adventure: I think ſeriouſly of it, but cannot find any ſatisfactory Reaſon: Is it not perhaps (ſaid he, of a ſuddain) for having ſeen you in <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s Solitude, when you went by the Name of <hi>Theodoric,</hi> and ſo, knew you again by your Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to be his Rival? Ah Sir (replyed <hi>Gonſalvo!</hi>) that Thought came into my Imagination too; I found it ſo funeſtous to me, that I cannot fancy it to be that: Can it poſſible be, that <hi>Alamire</hi> could be hidden in that Defart? Or, Can it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible happen, That the Joy which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſometimes to me to be in <hi>Zaydes</hi> Eyes, and which cauſed all my Happineſs, was only the Remains of what the ſight of <hi>Alamire</hi> had produced in them? But Sir,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53855:22"/>continued he, I ſcarce ever was from her; I ſhould have ſeen this Prince, if he had ever come to <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s: More-over, this Princeſs knows who I am; he comes now from her; there is no doubt, but that ſhe has told him; and ſo, muſt needs have known <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> to be the Lover of <hi>Zayde,</hi> when he met me. I cannot comprehend what ſhould cauſe ſo ſuddain a Change; and I find nothing but Impoſſibilities in all that I can imagine. Are you ſure (ſaid the King) that <hi>Alamire</hi> has ſeen <hi>Zayde?</hi> He paſs'd thorow our Camp Yeſter-day very late; You met him this Morning; It ſeems to me hard to believe, that he was at <hi>Talavera,</hi> and came back in ſo ſhort a time: But, it is no hard matter to know the Truth of this; for, two of my Officers have aſſur'd me, that they lay laſt Night where this Prince did; and we ſhall know from them, where they met him. The King commanded theſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to be ſent for preſently; and when they were come, he asked them, in what Place, and what Time they met with <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of theſe Officers made Anſwer; Sir, We were coming Yeſter-day from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riobisbe</hi> whither we were ſent; we made a Halt in the Evening in a great Wood,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53855:23"/>that is three or four Leagues from the Camp; we lighted, and lay down to ſleep in this Wood: I over-heard a Noiſe that waked me; I ſaw at a diſtance (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Trees) this <hi>Arabian</hi> Prince ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Lady that was Magnificiently Dreſs'd: This Lady, after a long Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, left him, and came to ſit down by another Lady, not far from the Place where I lay: They ſpoke loud enough; but I could not underſtand what they ſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſpoke a Language that I knew not, and which is not the ſame that the <hi>Arabians</hi> uſe: They named <hi>Alamire</hi> divers times; and, tho their Backs were turn'd ſo to me, that I could not ſee their Faces; yet my thought, that ſhe who ſpake to <hi>Alamire,</hi> wept bitterly. After this, they went away: I heard Waggons, and a great Noiſe of Horſes going towards <hi>Talavera:</hi> I awaked my Comrade, and purſued our Way: We ſaw <hi>Alamire</hi> at a diſtance, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under a Tree, as if he had been indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; his Squire asked me, whether they could reach the Camp of the <hi>Arabians</hi> by Day-light? I told them, they could not; ſo they came, and lodged in the ſame Village where we lay.</p>
               <p>The King repented him to have exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd theſe Officers: As ſoon as they were
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53855:23"/>gone, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſaid; You ſee, Sir, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I was in the wrong to believe, that <hi>Alamire</hi> had ſeen <hi>Zayde.</hi> But, can you imagine, that it was poſſible (ſaid the King) for her to come out of the Town, being ſhe is a Priſoner? My ill Fate (Replyed <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) never lets me fail of any thing that can prejudice me: I gave order at my coming away, That <hi>Zayde</hi> might have the Liberty of going out of the Town to take the Aire, as often as ſhe would: She ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <hi>Alamire</hi> in theſe Woods: He had reaſon to ſend me word, That an Affair of Importance, that concerned not the War, hinder'd him to make any ſtay in this Camp. He has ſeen her then Yeſter-day; She wept when he was gone: It is true then, that <hi>Zayde</hi> is in Love with <hi>Alamire;</hi> and now I am no longer in doubt. Leave me Sir! Caſt off your Care of a Man, that is too much perſecuted by ill Fortune, to deſerve your Eſteem: I am aſhamed to be prized and beloved by you, being ſo Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Garcias</hi> was ſenſibly touched at the Condition <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was in, and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to comfort him by the Aſſurances he gave him of his Affection and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:53855:24"/>
               <p>The next Day, word was brought, that the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> his Wounds were very dangerous; his Feaver was ſo violent the enſuing Dayes, that there was little hopes of his Recovery. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> imagin'd, that as ſoon as <hi>Zayde</hi> ſhould come to know the danger this Prince was in, ſhe would ſend to know how he did: He gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to one of his Servants, in whom he confided, to go every day to the Caſtle where <hi>Alamire</hi> was kept, to diſcover whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any came to try if they could ſee him: He would fain have known, like-wiſe, Whether there were any of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance betwixt them, which cauſed in him ſo much Curioſity: But the Extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, to which this Prince was reduced, hinder'd all Diſcoveries of that Nature; few or none of the Features of his Face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now diſtinguiſhable.</p>
               <p>He that was commanded to go to the Caſtle, acquitted himſelf of his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with Induſtry: For, he told <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> That ſince <hi>Alamire</hi> had been there, none had deſired to ſee him; but that certain People, whom he knew not, came every day to know the ſtate of his Health, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out telling who ſent them. Although <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> doubted no longer of <hi>Zaydes</hi> Love to <hi>Alamire;</hi> yet every little Circumſtance
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53855:24"/>that aſſured him of it, gave him new trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and diſquiet: the King came into his Tent, as he was agitated with the freſh Affliction he had received; and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending that ſo many Diſpleaſures would hazard his Life, he forbid all thoſe that came about him, to ſpeak to him of <hi>Alamire,</hi> or the Princeſs <hi>Zayde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean while, the Truce was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the two Armies fell to Action: <hi>Abderame</hi> Beſieged a little Place, where he expected no great Reſiſtance, by reaſon of the Inconſiderableneſs and Weakneſs of the Place: But it happened, that the Prince of <hi>Gallicia,</hi> nearly related to Don <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias,</hi> who by chance was carryed to this Place, the more commodiouſly to be cured of ſome Wounds he had received in the laſt Battle, undertook the Defence of it, with more Raſhneſs than Courage: At which, <hi>Abderame</hi> was ſo enraged, that, as ſoon as the Town was ſurrender'd, he caus'd his Head to be ſtruck off. It was not the firſt time that the <hi>Moors</hi> abuſed their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, and treated the braveſt of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Spain,</hi> with a barbarous &amp; unparallel'd Inhumanity. Don <hi>Garcias</hi> was extreamly incenſed at the News of the Death of the Prince of <hi>Gallicia:</hi> The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army was no leſs; they lov'd the Prince; and, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53855:26"/>weary of ſo many Cruelties, for which no publick Satisfaction was made or required; they came in Troops, to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition the King, that <hi>Alamire</hi> might be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as the <hi>Moors</hi> had done the Prince of <hi>Gallicia.</hi> The King conſented to their Deſires; becauſe it was dangerous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to pleaſe an Army ſo much incenſed: He ſent word to the King of <hi>Cordoua,</hi> That he would cauſe the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> his Head to be cut off, ſo ſoon as he ſhould be in a better condition of Health; and that his Wounds would permit him to be made a Publick Example off, without lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Cauſe to report, that he had only haſten'd his End.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> by the King's Order, was ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what had been tranſacted, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Alamire.</hi> Some Dayes after, they brought him word, that a <hi>Gentleman</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> deſired to ſee him: He order'd him to be admitted. This Gentleman, after having told him, That his Maſter was extreamly troubled, that the King's Order did detain him at <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ragel,</hi> and hinder'd him from coming in Perſon, to ask him how he did, gave him ſeveral Pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> open'd that which was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed to him, and read in it theſe Words.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:53855:26"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The LETTER of DON <hi>OLMOND</hi> TO DON <hi>GONSALVO.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF I were not well aſſured of the Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you have to do great Actions, I would not ſend you the Incloſed; and ſhould believe it to no purpoſe, to intreat you in the behalf of your Enemy: But I am too well acquainted with your generous Soul, to doubt of your kind Entertaining the Requeſt I am deſired to make to you. However juſt it may appear to treat the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> as the Prince of <hi>Gallicia</hi> has been uſed; it will become you to preſerve a Man of the Merit and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Alamire:</hi> I think, more-over, you ought to allow ſome Pity to a Paſſion that is not altogether unknown to you.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Name of <hi>Alamire,</hi> and the laſt Words of this Letter, cauſed a very great Diſ-order in <hi>Gonſalvo:</hi> He asked the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, What his Maſter meant, by what he writ concerning the Prince of <hi>Gallicia?</hi> Although this Gentleman ought not to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53855:25"/>think, that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was ignorant of what had been done; nevertheleſs, he infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him in few words, of the whole Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> Read the Letter which Don <hi>Olmond</hi> had incloſed, which contained theſe Words:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The LETTER of <hi>FELIME</hi> to Don <hi>Olmond.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YOU have a great Power with <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi> order it ſo, that he preſerve the Life of <hi>Alamire</hi> from the King of <hi>Leon's</hi> Fury: In ſecuring him from the Death which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him, he will not ſave his Life; his Wounds will ſoon bereave him of that: And <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> is already ſufficiently Revenged of this wretched Prince, ſince we are obliged to have Recourſe to him for his Preſervation. I conjure you, to uſe all your Intereſt in this Matter: You will ſave more than one Life, in ſaving <hi>Alamires.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Ah <hi>Zayde,</hi> cryed <hi>Gonſalvo! Felime</hi> do's but write by your Order: And you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me by this Letter, to preſerve your <hi>Alamire:</hi> How Inhumane is your Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? To what Extreams do you reduce me? Are not my Misfortunes great enough?
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53855:25"/>Muſt I be obliged more-over, to labor for his Preſervation, that creates them? Muſt I oppoſe the King's Pleaſure? His Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution is juſt: He has been driven to it againſt his Inclination: I had no ſhare in it: I ought to let <hi>Alamire</hi> periſh, though I were ignorant of his being my Rival, and being beloved of <hi>Zayde;</hi> But I know it: And this Reaſon, as Cruel as it is, will not let me conſent to his Ruin. What kind of Law is this that I impoſe upon my ſelf? What manner of Generoſity is it, that obliges me to ſave <hi>Alamire?</hi> Is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know he robs me of <hi>Zayde,</hi> that I muſt ſave his Life? Ought I to pretend, that the King in granting me this Requeſt, ſhould expoſe himſelf to the hazard of making his Army Revolt? Shall I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Intereſts of Don <hi>Garcias,</hi> to tear from my own Heart, thoſe ſweet Hopes with which the Death of <hi>Alamire</hi> flatters me? This only Man ſtands betwixt me and <hi>Zayde;</hi> and, how-ever ſhe may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs'd in his Favour; if ſhe were never more to ſee him, I might promiſe my ſelf to be Happy.</p>
               <p>After theſe Words, he remain'd a great while, as it were, buryed in a profound Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: At laſt, he ſtarts up of a ſuddain; and, though he was extream weak, he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53855:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:53855:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:53855:28"/>cauſed himſelf to be carryed to the King's Tent: This Prince was ſtrangely ſurprized when he ſaw him, and more when he underſtood what he came to ask.</p>
               <p>Sir, ſaid <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> if you have any kindneſs for me, be pleaſed to grant me <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Life: I cannot live if you make him dye. What is this you ſay <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> replyed the King? By what Accident do's the Life of the Man that makes you miſerable, become ſo neceſſary to your Quiet? <hi>Zadye</hi> Sir, commands me (ſaid he) to preſerve it; I muſt endeavour to anſwer the good Opinion ſhe has conceived of me: She knows I Adore her, and ought to hate this Prince; and yet ſhe has ſo much Confidence in me, that ſhe believes me ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to his Death, that I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſave him from the Death that is intended him. She is willing to owe me the Life of her Lover; I beg it of you, by all your Goodneſs. I muſt not hear (ſaid the King) ſuch Deſires, which a blind kind of Generoſity inſpires, and a Paſſion that leaves you not the uſe of your Reaſon: I muſt Act purſuant to my own Intereſt and yours. The Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> muſt dye, to teach the King of <hi>Cordoua,</hi> to make better uſe of the Law of Arms; and to appeaſe my Troops, which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53855:28"/>are ready to Mutiny: He muſt dye like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to leave you ſole Poſſeſſor of <hi>Zayde,</hi> and to hinder him from diſturbing your Quiet hereafter. Ah Sir! ſhall I find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Quiet (replyed <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) in ſeeing <hi>Zayde</hi> diſpleaſed with me? and in deſpair for the Death of her Lover? I muſt think no more of diſputing <hi>Zayde</hi> with <hi>Alamire,</hi> whether he lives or dyes; I muſt not render my ſelf worthy of the ill uſage of Fortune, by an unreaſonable Obſtinacy: I will make <hi>Zayde</hi> pity me, ſince ſhe could not love me; nor will I leave it in her Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, either to deſpiſe or hate me. Take time (ſaid the King) to examine what it is you ask me; and conſider with your ſelf, whether you ought to deſire it. No Sir (replyed <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) I will not have the leaſure to change my Opinion; nor to be expoſed to oppoſe a ſecond time, thoſe vain and flattering Hopes, which the thought of <hi>alamire</hi>'s Death has already given me; nor would I give <hi>Zayde</hi> room to believe, that I was any way irreſolute in the Choiſe I make: And I beg of you the Favour, to declare even now, That you have granted me this Princes Life. I do promiſe you (replyed the King) to leave him to your Diſpoſal; But you muſt conceal it yet a while from the Knowledg
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53855:29"/>of the World. You know our Deſigne upon <hi>Oropeſe;</hi> the Inhabitants are this Night to open us the Gates; If the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize ſucceeds, the Joy of the happy Succeſs, may perhaps diſpoſe the Army to milder Thoughts: <hi>Felime</hi> will be in our Power; know of her, whether <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> be beloved of <hi>Zayde:</hi> Dive into the Secrets of your Deſtiny, before you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the Fate of this Prince; and put your ſelf into a Condition of taking ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, whereof you may not Repent hereafter. But Sir, perhaps <hi>Felime</hi> may not be willing to diſcover the Sentiments of <hi>Zayde</hi> to me. To oblige her to it (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted the King) ſend word to Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> that you will not undertake what ſhe deſires, unleſs you know the true Reaſons why ſhe is ſo much concerned for the Preſervation of <hi>Alamire.</hi> It is Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> that is ordered to enter <hi>Oropeſe;</hi> and you will know by him, all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you to learn. I ſubmit, Sir, (anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>) upon Condition, that you will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to oblige the Army, to come of themſelves to you, to beg <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Life, at the ſame time, that the News of the taking <hi>Oropeſe</hi> is Publiſhed: And as <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime</hi> ſhall be our Priſoner, Don <hi>Olmond</hi> may conceal from her the Grace you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53855:29"/>until ſhe has diſcovered all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns this Prince. <hi>Zayde</hi> ſhall know, that I have obeyed her Commands, at that very inſtant, that I received them; and ſhe ſhall judge by this blind Obedience, that if I renounce the Pretenſions I had to her Affections, I was not unworthy to poſſeſs them.</p>
               <p>The King granted all that Don <hi>Gonſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo</hi> deſired; but, at the ſame time, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to write to Don <hi>Olmond</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what they had reſolved: The King ſpent part of the Night with his Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, who began to ſink under the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence he had uſed againſt himſelf, in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing to an exact Generoſity (from which he expected no Advantage) all the Hopes of a Paſſion, which poſſeſs'd his whole Heart.</p>
               <p>The next Day, Don <hi>Garcias</hi> received Letters of the Proſperous Succeſs of their Enterprize upon <hi>Oropeſe;</hi> he ſent the News of it to <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi> and, at the ſame time, ſent him word, that he gave him Liberty to uſe his Endeavours for the ſaving of <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi>'s Life. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> cauſed himſelf to be carryed into the Camp, with the ſame Alacrity and Earneſtneſs of Mind, as if the Succeſs of his Undertaking were to aſſure the Conqueſt of <hi>Zayde:</hi> And with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53855:30"/>the ſame Countenance, and the ſame Voyce, which he ſo often had made uſe of, to inſpire Courage into his Souldiers, to follow him to Victory, ſhewed them what a ſhame they went about to cauſe him, in deſiring to take away a Princes Life, who had not been in their Power, but for his ingaging with him: He told them, That by this Death (of which he ſhould ever be thought the Author) they made him loſe all the Honour he had won with them in ſo many Battles: That he was at that inſtant, going to the King, to lay down his Commiſſion, and the Command he had of the Army, in order to his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of <hi>Spain:</hi> That he left it to their Choyce, either to be Witneſſes of his taking his leave of the King; or elſe, to go at that inſtant, and beg <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Life. Scarce did the Souldiers give him leave to make an end of his Speech; but thronging about him (as it were), to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from going away, followed him to Don <hi>Garcias</hi> his Tent; ſo animated by the General's Words, that it ſeem'd now as dangerous to refuſe them <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Life, as ſome Days paſt not to grant them his Death.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> amidſt ſo many Troubles he had in the ſetling a Town newly taken, bethought him of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53855:30"/>
                  <hi>Conſalvo,</hi> whoſe Intereſt requir'd he ſhould entertain <hi>Felime:</hi> He ſent to deſire leave to ſpeak to her, with the ſame Reſpect, as if the Law of Arms had not given him a free and full Diſpoſal of her: He found her in a deep Melancholly, for, what happen'd that Day, as well as a great Fit of Sickneſs, which her Mother had for ſome time, ſeemed the Cauſes thereof.</p>
               <p>So ſoon as they could talk without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard; Well (ſaid ſhe) Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> Have you prevail'd with Don <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to ſave <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Life? Madam (anſwered he,) that Princes Deſtiny is in your Hands. In my Hands, cryed ſhe? Alas, by what Accident can it be in my Power to do any thing, that may preſerve him? I'le ſecure you his Life, replyed he: But to make me able to keep my Word; you muſt inform me of the Reaſons that move you ſo eagerly to work his ſafety: You muſt tell it to me truly, with all the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and every thing you know concerning this Prince. Ah, Don <hi>Olmond</hi> (replyed ſhe!) what is this you ask me? At this, ſhe remain'd ſilent for a while; then, of a ſuddain, ſaid; Do not you know, that he is <hi>Oſmin</hi> and <hi>Zulema</hi>'s near Kinſ-man? That we have been acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him a great while? That he is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53855:31"/>a Perſon of extraordinary Merit? Is not this enough to make me concern'd for his Life? But, Madam, (replyed Don <hi>Olmond,</hi>) the concern you have for his Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, has other more preſſing Reaſons: If you think it too much trouble to let me know it, you are free to let it alone; but you muſt be content to free me from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement I gave you. How Don <hi>Olmond</hi> (ſaid ſhe?) Muſt this be the Ranſom of <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Life? What will it avail you, to know what you ask? <hi>I</hi> am ſorry, <hi>I</hi> cannot tell you (anſwered Don <hi>Olmond</hi>): But Madam, once more, <hi>I</hi> cannot do any thing for him, but upon theſe Terms: All is left to your Choice. <hi>Felime</hi> remain'd a good while, with her Eyes fix'd upon the Ground, in ſo profound a ſilence, that Don <hi>Olmond</hi> wondered at it: At laſt, taking Courage; <hi>I</hi> am going (ſaid ſhe, to him) to do that thing, which of all things in the World, <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> ſhould never have the Power over my ſelf to do: The good O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion <hi>I</hi> have of you, and the Friendſhip <hi>I</hi> have for you, help much to confirm me, as well as the Deſire <hi>I</hi> have to ſave <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Life. You muſt keep my Counſel invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably; and give ear, with Patience, to the Relation I am going to make you; which cannot but be tedious to you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:53855:31"/>
               <head>The HISTORY of <hi>ZAIDE</hi> and <hi>FELIME</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cid Rahis</hi> was Brother to <hi>Caliphe Oſman,</hi> and might have diſputed (by Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right) the Empire with him, had he not been ſo unfortunate, as to be abandoned by all thoſe that gave him Hopes of their Aſſiſtance; and thereby, was compelled to renounce his pretenſion, and conſent to be baniſhed into the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of being made Commander in Chief there. <hi>Zulema,</hi> and <hi>Oſman,</hi> whom you know were his Children; They were Young and Handſome, and had given many Signal Teſtimonies of their Valour: They both fell in Love with two Women of extraordinary Beauty, and great Quality; who were Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and were deſeended of a long ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Princes; Who formerly bare the chief ſway in this Iſland, before it fell un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of the <hi>Arabians:</hi> The one was called <hi>Alaſinthe,</hi> the other <hi>Belenia. Oſman</hi> and <hi>Zulema,</hi> being well skild in the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue, found no difficulty to make themſelves to be underſtood, by theſe two Ladies, who were Chriſtians; But the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of their Religion, made none in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53855:32"/>their inclinations; They mutually loved paſſionately: And ſo ſoon as the <hi>Cid Rahis,</hi> his death, left them their liberty; <hi>Zulema</hi> married <hi>Alaſinthe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Oſmin</hi> married <hi>Belenia:</hi> They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, that their Children ſhould be brought up in the Chriſtian Religion; and made them believe, they would be ſo themſelves within a ſhort time. I was born of <hi>Oſmin</hi> &amp; <hi>Belenia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Zayde</hi> of <hi>Zulema</hi> and <hi>Alaſinthe:</hi> The Paſſion of <hi>Oſimin</hi> and <hi>Zulema</hi> made them continue ſome years in <hi>Cyprus:</hi> But, at laſt, the deſire they had to find out a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Conjuncture of renewing the pretenſions of their Father, call'd them back into <hi>Affrick:</hi> At firſt, they conceived great hopes; For, contrary to the Rules of true Policy, the <hi>Caliphe</hi> that ſucceeded <hi>Oſman,</hi> gave them ſuch conſiderable Employments, that <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> and <hi>Beleny</hi> could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of their being far from them: But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter five of ſix years abſence, they began to murmur, and be much afflicted: They found that they were not all this while in the Wars, but had other Occupations: They heard from them ſometimes; but they not coming, made them believe themſelves for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken: <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> therefore thought no more of any thing, but of <hi>Zayde,</hi> who even at that age deſerved all her Application: And <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenia</hi> made me the ſole object of all her care.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:53855:32"/>
               <p>When we were paſs'd our Infancy, <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> and <hi>Belenia</hi> retired into a Caſtle upon the Sea-ſide; where they led a Life conformable to their Sadneſs: The regard, they had for <hi>Zayde</hi> and me, made them live with a Grandure and Magnificence, which perhaps by their own inclinations, they would have been glad to leave. We had divers young people of Quality about us; and there was nothing wanting, that might contribute to our Education, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement, that were ſutable to the place where we were brought up. <hi>Zayde,</hi> and I, had as great tyes of Love and Friendſhip for each other, as we had of Blood and Affinity. I was two years older than ſhe: There was alſo ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in our Humours; Mine was leſs inclinable to Mirth; it was eaſie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it in our Converſation: <hi>Zayde</hi> had alſo a great advantage of Beauty over me.</p>
               <p>Some time before the Emperor <hi>Leo</hi> ſent to invade <hi>Cyprus,</hi> we were walking by the Sea-ſide; The Sea was very Calm, there was not a breath of Wind ſtirring; We pray'd <hi>Alaſinthe,</hi> and <hi>Belenia,</hi> to be pleaſed to let us go to Sea in Boats, to divert us. We took divers Young People with us; we made our Barge-men Row towards
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53855:33"/>ſome great Ships, that were at Anchor in the Road: As we came neer theſe Veſſels, we ſaw ſeveral long Boats put off, whom we judged to be full of <hi>Arabians,</hi> that were going aſhore: Theſe Boats Steared towards us; In the firſt of which, were ſeveral perſons richly attired; one of which, by his Noble Aire, and the Beauty and Comlineſs of his Perſon, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to be ſomewhat more then any of thoſe that were about him; This Rencounter Surprized us, and made us judge it not fit for us to venture further to Sea; and that we ought not to give, thoſe that were in the other Boats, occaſion to believe that our Curioſity to ſee them, had led us that way: We made our Barge fall off to the Leeward; the Boat we endeavoured to avoid, Tacked after us; but the reſt made towards the Shore; The other followed us ſo neer, that we could perceive the man we remarked above the reſt, looking ſteadfaſtly upon us; who ſeemed to take pleaſure in following us. <hi>Zayde</hi> was extreamly taken with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, and cauſed our Boat to Tack, to ſee if the other would follow us ſtill, For my part, I was ſtrangely concern'd, without knowing why: I looked earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon him, that ſeemed the Chief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53855:33"/>them; and conſidering him at ſo neer a diſtance, I found ſomthing in his face ſo fair, and ſo agreeable, that I thought I had never ſeen any thing more pleaſing in all my life. I told <hi>Zayde,</hi> we muſt put to ſhore; and that, without doubt, when <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> and <hi>Belenia</hi> had given us leave to come off, they did not think we ſhould have met with ſuch an Adventure. She was of my opinion; we rowed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſhore! The Boat followed us, got a head of us, and put to ſhore near the other Boats, that were already landed.</p>
               <p>So ſoon as we touched, we ſaw him that we had remarked, followed by a great many other, advancing towards us; and offered us his hand, with an Ayre, that ſhewed he had already learnt vvho vve vvere. <hi>Zaydes</hi> and my aſtoniſhment vvas great; vve were not uſed to be accoſted vvith ſo much boldneſs; and above all, by <hi>Arabians,</hi> for vvhom we vvere taught an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream averſion: We believed, that he vvould be ſurprized, vvhen he ſhould find, that vve did not underſtand his Language; but vve vvere more our ſelves, vvhen vve found that he Spoke ours vvith the ſame exactneſs, and Eloquence, vvhich the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Greeks</hi> uſed in former times.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:53855:34"/>
               <p>I know Madam (ſaid he, to <hi>Zayde,</hi> vvho went before) that an <hi>Arabian</hi> ſhould not be ſo bold as to approach your Preſence, vvithout firſt asking your leave: But I believe, that vvhat vvould be thought a crime in another, is pardonable in a man that has the honour, to be allied to the Princes <hi>Zulema,</hi> and <hi>Oſmin.</hi> Being Curious to ſee vvhat was moſt remarkable in Greece, I thought, I could not ſatisfie that Curioſity better, than in beginning vvith the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus:</hi> And my good fortune made me find at my firſt Arrival in it, that vvhich I ſhould have fought in vain, in all the other parts of the World.</p>
               <p>In ſaying theſe vvords, he fixed his eyes ſometimes upon <hi>Zayde,</hi> and ſometimes upon me, vvith ſuch demonſtrations of a true Admiration, that vve could hardly doubt, but that he really thought, vvhat he ſaid to us. I know not vvhether I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready prepoſſeſſed, or vvhether it vvas the ſolitude of the place vvhere vve lived, that made me think this Adventure very agreeable: But I muſt confeſs, that I never ſaw any thing ſo ſurpriſing. <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> and <hi>Belenia,</hi> vvho vvere at ſome diſtance from us advanced towards us; and ſent before, to knovv the Name of this nevv-come Stranger: They vvere informed, that it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53855:34"/>vvas <hi>Alamire</hi> Prince, of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> Son to that <hi>Alamire,</hi> vvho aſſumed the Title of <hi>Calyphe,</hi> and vvhoſe power vvas ſo terrible to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: They knevv the affinity that vvas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt this Prince and <hi>Zulema;</hi> So that, the reſpect vvhich vvas due to his Birth, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the deſire of hearing from them, made them receive him with a leſſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, than they uſed to have for the <hi>Arabians. Alamire</hi> by his words, increaſed the diſpoſition they had to receive him more favourably: He ſpoke to them of <hi>Zulema,</hi> and <hi>Oſmin,</hi> whom he had ſeen a little before his Departure; and blamed them for being Capable of abandoning two Perſons ſo worthy of their Love. Their Converſation was ſo long upon the Sea-ſide, and <hi>Alamire</hi> appeared ſo agreeable, even in the eyes of <hi>Alaſinthe,</hi> and <hi>Belenia,</hi> that contrary to the Reſolution they had taken of avoiding the company of all ſtrangers, they could not avoid offering him Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in their Habitation. <hi>Alamire</hi> told them, that although, he knew that Civility ought to forbid him, accepting the offer they made him; yet that he could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it, becauſe he would not deprive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the pleaſure he took, in being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant with perſons that had given him ſo much Admiration: Wherefore he walked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53855:35"/>with us, and preſented to us a perſon, for whom he ſhewed much eſteem, whoſe name was <hi>Mulziman.</hi> All that evening, <hi>Alamire</hi> continued to confirme us in the eſteem, we at firſt conceived of him. I was every Moment ſo aſtoniſhed at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſſe of his wit, and gracefulneſs of his perſon; And this aſtoniſhment was ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull upon me, that I might well even then Judge, there was ſomething more in it, then a bare Surprize; Me thought he viewed me with a great deal of attention, and gave me Commendations that made me think, that my perſon was at leaſt as pleaſing to him as <hi>Zaydes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next day, inſtead of going away, as in all likelihood he ſhould have done, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged <hi>Alaſinthe,</hi> and <hi>Belenia,</hi> to pray him to ſtay. He ſent for very fine Horſes, which he had brought with him, and cauſed them to be rid by ſeveral of his People; and rid them himſelf with that grace, and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, which is particular to thoſe of his Nation; He found pretences to ſtay three or four dayes with us; and wrought ſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Alaſinthe,</hi> and <hi>Belenia,</hi> that they conſented to admit his viſits, during his abode in <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus.</hi> At his going from us, he told me, that if his preſence had been troubleſome to me, or ſhould be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53855:35"/>for the future, I muſt blame my ſelf alone for it; Nevertheleſs I had taken notice, that his looks were often upon <hi>Zayde;</hi> And I obſerved likewiſe that his eyes, were as often fixed upon me, after a manner which appeared ſo natural to me, that joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Language of his Eyes, with many things which he had ſaid to me, I remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed convinced, that I had made ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon his heart. O Gods! How deep were thoſe he made upon mine: As ſoon as he was out of my ſight, I felt a ſadneſs that was utterly unknown to me; I quitted <hi>Zaydes</hi> company; I went dreaming about; my thoughts were confuſed; I was weary of my ſelf: I came again to find <hi>Zayde,</hi> and my thoughts it was onely, that I might ſpeak to her of <hi>Alamire;</hi> I found her buſy with her Maids, making Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands of Flowers: And ſhe ſeemed to me as unconcerned, as if ſhe never had ſeen this Prince; I felt a kind of a Mazement at her being ſo buſy with her Flowers, and found my ſelf ſo little diſpoſed to amuſe my ſelf with them, that I ſnatched them from her whether ſhe would or no. We went to walk; I talked to her of <hi>Alamire;</hi> I told her, that I ſaw him look very much upon her; ſhe made anſwer, that ſhe did not obſerve it; I endeavoured to find out
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53855:36"/>whether ſhe had taken notice of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination which he profeſſed for me; but I found, ſhe had not ſo much as a thought of it; And I remained ſo aſtoniſhed, and ſo confounded to ſee the different Effects, which the ſight of <hi>Alamire</hi> had upon <hi>Zayde,</hi> from thoſe it had wrought upon me, that I blamed my ſelf, and uſed ſuch reproaches againſt my ſelf, as were already but too juſt.</p>
               <p>Some days after, he came to ſee us; at a time, when <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> and <hi>Beleny</hi> were gone abroad, and were not to return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till night; <hi>Alamire</hi> appeared to me more Lovely than ever; and as <hi>Zayde</hi> was not preſent, it was my Misfortune to ſee him, when there was nothing that could divert his attention from looking upon me; and made me ſo many proteſtations of his love, that the inclination <hi>I</hi> had for him, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me that <hi>I</hi> was as acceptable and pleaſing to him, as he was to me; He took his leave of me before the hour that <hi>Zayde</hi> was to return, after ſuch a manner, that <hi>I</hi> flattered my ſelf with the opinion, that he had no thoughts of ſeeing her; ſhe returned a great while after, and <hi>I</hi> was ſurprized when <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> told me that they met him very neer the Caſtle, and that he came back to conduct them to the Caſtle Gate; <hi>I</hi> fancied by the ſpace of time,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53855:36"/>ſince he left me, he ſhould have been far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther off than they ſaid; and that if he had not waited for them, he could not have met them, This thought gave me ſome diſquiet; Nevertheleſs <hi>I</hi> did attribute their meeting, to Chance rather than any thing elſe, yet <hi>I</hi> was in greater impatience to ſee <hi>Alamire</hi> again, then ever <hi>I</hi> had felt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: He came ſome dayes after to bring <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> the news of the Warr the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Leo</hi> Deſigned to make againſt <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus.</hi> And this news that was of ſuch Conſequence, ſerved him as a pretence to come more often to ſee us; And as often as he came, he ſtill made the ſame proteſtations of love to me, as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>I</hi> had need of all my reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal from him the Diſpoſition of mind in which <hi>I</hi> was towards him; and perhaps all my reaſon would have been too weak, if the Concern <hi>I</hi> ſaw he had ſometimes for <hi>Zayde</hi> did not help to retain me, for all that <hi>I</hi> attributed what <hi>I</hi> ſaw him do to pleaſe her, onely to his innate Civility and he had addreſſe enough, to hide from me what might give me other thoughts.</p>
               <p>We had intelligence that the Emperors Fleet was in ſight of our Coaſts; <hi>Alamire</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <hi>Alaſinthe,</hi> and <hi>Beleny</hi> to leave the place we were in; Although our Religion
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53855:37"/>gave us no Apprehenſion of the Emperors forces; yet the Alliance we had with the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and the apprehenſions we had of the diſorders, which attends upon War, obliged us to follow <hi>Alamire's</hi> Counſels, and remove to <hi>Famagoſta; I</hi> was very glad of it, both becauſe <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> ſhould be in the ſame place with <hi>Alamire,</hi> and that <hi>Zayde</hi> and <hi>I</hi> ſhould be no longer Lodged together: Her Beauty was ſo dreadfull to me, that <hi>I</hi> was glad to be where <hi>Alamire</hi> might ſee me, without ſeeing her. <hi>I</hi> believed, <hi>I</hi> ſhould be fully ſatisfied of his intentions towards me, and ſhould ſee whether <hi>I</hi> ought to abandon my ſelf to the inclination <hi>I</hi> had for him; but my heart was no longer in my power: <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded nevertheleſſe, that if <hi>I</hi> had been then as well informed of <hi>Alamires</hi> humours as <hi>I</hi> have been ſince, <hi>I</hi> might have defended my ſelf againſt the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which drew me to Love him: But as <hi>I</hi> knew onely the agreeable, and charming qualifications of his Wit and Perſon, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Paſſion he pretended for me, it was hard for me to reſiſt an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which was ſo violent and ſo natural.</p>
               <p>The day we arrived at <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> he came to meet us; <hi>Zayde</hi> was that day ſo Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Beautifull, that ſhe appeared in the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53855:37"/>eyes of <hi>Alamire,</hi> what he appeared in mine; That is to ſay, the only perſon, that can pleaſe; <hi>I</hi> perceived the extraordinary care he took to view her attentively. When we were arrived, <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leny</hi> ſeparated; <hi>Alamire</hi> followed <hi>Zayde,</hi> without ſo much as pretending an excuſe to leave me; I remained ſtruck with the ſharpeſt grief I ever felt; I knew by the violence thereof, the true Paſſion <hi>I</hi> had for this Prince, and this knowledge increaſed my ſadneſs: I now ſaw the Horrible Misfortune, <hi>I</hi> was fallen into by my own fault; but after having afflicted my ſelf for a long time, I ſaw ſome beams of hope ſtill: <hi>I</hi> Flattered my ſelf, as all thoſe that are in Love do; and <hi>I</hi> fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied that ſome Reaſons, unknown to me, might occaſion what diſpleaſed me; <hi>I</hi> was not long fed with this weak hope: <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> for a while would have us believe, that he lov'd us both; that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine afterwards, according to the uſage he received, to whom he ſhould ſtick: But the Beauty of <hi>Zayde,</hi> without the ſuccour of hope, carried it; Nay, he had forgotten, that he had ever endeavoured to perſwade me to believe that he had a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for me: He ſeldom or never came to ſee me after; or if he did, it was to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53855:38"/>follow <hi>Zayde;</hi> he loved her with an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary paſſion. In ſine, <hi>I</hi> ſaw him in that condition for her, as <hi>I</hi> ſhould have been for him if decency would have pormitted me to ſhew my ſentiments for him.</p>
               <p>I know not, whether it be neceſſary, for me to tell you what I ſuffered, and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious impulſes that perplexed my heart; I could not endure to ſee him with <hi>Zayde,</hi> and to ſee him ſo Amorous of her; and of the otherſide, I could not live without him; I had rather ſee him with <hi>Zayde,</hi> than not to ſee him at all; in the mean while, what he did to gain her eſteem inſtead of leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my Paſſion, raiſed it to the higheſt pitch: All his words, and all his Actions were ſo adapted to my fancy, that if I could inſpire a conduct into thoſe that ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pleaſe me, it ſhould be that which <hi>Alamire</hi> uſed towards <hi>Zayde.</hi> It is true, that it is ſo dangerous a matter to ſee Love made, that it inflames even thoſe to whom it makes no tenders nor addreſſes; <hi>Zayde</hi> gave me an account of his thoughts for her, and her averſion for him; when ſhe ſpoke to me after that manner of him, I was ſometimes ready to diſcover to her the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition I was in, to engage her by this confeſſion not to ſuffer the continuation of this Princes love, but I was fearfull of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53855:38"/>making him appear more lovely to her, by ſhowing how much he was beloved; yet I ſet my ſelf a Rule not to render any ill offices to <hi>Alamire;</hi> I was ſo ſenſible of the Horrible Misfortune of not being lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, that I reſolved not to contribute to his feeling of it, whom I ſo paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loved; and perhaps, it was the little propenſity I ſaw in <hi>Zayde</hi> towards him, that made me ſtedfaſt to that reſolution.</p>
               <p>The Emperors Troops were ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that there was no doubt made but that <hi>Cyprus</hi> would quickly fall into his hands: upon the noiſe of this invaſion <hi>Zulema,</hi> and <hi>Oſimin</hi> awakened out of their profound Oblivion, in which they had ſo long continued; the <hi>Caliphe</hi> began to be afraid of them, and ſeemed to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſend them further off, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him by deſiring him to give them the command of thoſe forces, which he intended for the relief of <hi>Cyprus;</hi> and we ſaw them arrived, when we leaſt expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them: this was a ſenſible joy for <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinthe</hi> and <hi>Beleny,</hi> and it would have been ſo for me, if I had been capable of it; but <hi>I</hi> was oppreſſed with ſorrow, and the Arrival of <hi>Zulema</hi> gave me new appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, fearing he ſhould favour <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires</hi> deſignes. My fears were not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53855:39"/>cauſe, <hi>Zulema,</hi> who by his long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in <hi>Affrica,</hi> grew more ſtubborn and ſtedfaſt to his Religion than ever; wiſhed, that <hi>Zayde</hi> would leave hers: He came from <hi>Tunis,</hi> with deſign to carry her thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to marry her to the Prince of <hi>Fez,</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Idris:</hi> But the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> appeared ſo deſerving of his Daughter, that he approved of his paſſion for her: I ſaw then a neceſſity of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to hinder, that <hi>Zayde</hi> ſhould not love <hi>Alamire;</hi> it being the only thing I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended moſt in the world, to ſee him happy by her means.</p>
               <p>This Princes paſſion was grown ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that all that knew him were amazed at it. <hi>Mulziman,</hi> of whom I ſpoke to you, whom I entertained ſometimes becauſe <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amire</hi> had a kindneſs for him, ſeemed to me ſo aſtoniſhed at it, that I concluded that this Prince never until then; had been ſuſceptible of a Paſſion ſo ſtrange and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Alamire</hi> made <hi>Zulema</hi> underſtand the intentions he had for his Daughter; and <hi>Zulema</hi> acquainted <hi>Zayde,</hi> with the deſire he had ſhe ſhould Marry <hi>Alamire:</hi> As ſoon as ſhe was told of the thing ſhe moſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, ſhe came to tell me of it, with ſuch marks of diſquiet, that, I confeſs, I was puzled to comprehend the reaſon of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53855:39"/>her Affliction for being deſign'd to ſpend her Days with <hi>Alamire.</hi> This unfaithful Man had ſo throughly forgotten thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations he had made me, that being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by <hi>Zulema,</hi> of the Averſion which <hi>Zayde</hi> had for him, he came to make his moan to me, and to implore my Aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. All my Reaſon, and my Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were ſcarce ſtrong enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain me; I felt ſuch a conflict and agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mind, that he might eaſily have perceived it, if he had not been prepoſſeſs'd with the ſame Paſſion that diſorder'd me. At laſt, after a ſilence, which but two plainly ſpoke my mind; I told him, I wonder'd much at <hi>Zaydes</hi> Reſiſtance againſt <hi>Zulema</hi>'s Will; but I am the moſt unfit Perſon in the World to make her change her Opinion. I ſhould ſpeak againſt my own Judgment; and beſides, the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of being tied to one of your Nation, is ſo well known to me, that I cannot perſwade <hi>Zayde</hi> to expoſe her ſelf to it. <hi>Belenia,</hi> has too well informed me ever ſince I was capable of knowing any thing; and I believe <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> has ſo throughly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed her Daughter, that it will not be eaſie to make her Conſent to what you deſire; and for my part, I aſſure you once more, that I am the unfitteſt Perſon in the World to undertake it.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:53855:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> was out of his Wits, to find me ſo indiſpoſs'd to favour him; yet he was in hopes to win upon me, by letting me ſee his Affliction, and the violence of his Paſſion for <hi>Zayde.</hi> I was in deſpair, to hear what he ſaid upon this occaſion; and yet I could not but pity him, through the Conformity that was betwixt our Misfortunes: All my Thoughts were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted: The Averſion which <hi>Zayde</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him, gave me ſome Joy, by the Sweetneſs of Revenge, which I taſted plentifully: And yet my Glory was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to ſee one that I ſo much Adored, thus deſpiſed.</p>
               <p>I reſolved to tell <hi>Zayde</hi> the State of my Heart; but before I would do it, I preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to conſider well with her ſelf, Whether ſhe ſhould alwayes be able to reſiſt the Deſigne <hi>Zulema</hi> had, of Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her to <hi>Alamire?</hi> She told me, There was no Extreamity, which ſhe would not indure, rather than conſent to marry a Man ſo oppoſite in Religion to hers; and whoſe Laws permitted him, to take as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wives as he pleaſed: But, that ſhe believed, that <hi>Zulema</hi> would not compel her; or, if he ſhould endeavour it, that <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> would find means to hinder him. What <hi>Zayde</hi> had told me, gave me all the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53855:40"/>Joy imaginable: And I began to endeavour to tell her, what I had reſolved to diſcover to her; but I found more Difficulty and Relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy, than I thought. In fine, I over-came all the Oppoſitions of Pride and Baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; and I told her, with many Tears, the State I was in: She was ſtrangely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at it; and ſhe ſeemed as much concerned at my ill Fate, as I could wiſh. But why (ſaid ſhe) did you conceal your Thoughts with ſo much Care, from him that gave them Birth? I do not doubt, but that if he had at firſt diſcovered them, he would have Loved you; and I believe, That if he ſhould yet be made ſenſible of your Inclination for him, the Hope of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beloved, together, with the ill Uſage he receives from me, would quickly make him forſake me: Will not you give me leave (added ſhe, Embracing me) to try to make him conceive, that he ought rather to addreſs himſelf to you, than to me? Ah <hi>Zayde</hi> (anſwered I!) Do not rob me of the only thing that hinders me from dying with more Grief; I ſhould not be able to ſurvive <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Knowledge of the Concern I have for him; not only the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of my Honour would make me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolable; but I ſhould be likewiſe ſo, by that of my Paſſion: I might flatter my
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53855:41"/>ſelf with the Hope of being Beloved, if he ſhould know my Inclination to Love him: Yet I know, Love do's not alwayes beget Love: Therefore, I will not deprive my ſelf of that Hope, as weak as it is, ſince it is the only Comfort I have left me. I gave <hi>Zayde</hi> ſo many other Reaſons, that ſhe was of my Opinion, that <hi>I</hi> ought not to diſcover my Paſſion to <hi>Alamire: I</hi> found a great Eaſe, in having open'd my Heart to her, and much Satisfaction in making my moan to her.</p>
               <p>The Wars in the mean-time, held on ſtill; though at ſuch a Rate, as was plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſeen, that we ſhould not be able to hold out long: All the Country was loſt, but <hi>Famagoſta, Alamire</hi> expos'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf every Day, with a Valour or a Teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that clearly ſhewed the Deſpair he was in: <hi>Mulziman</hi> would tell me of it, with an extraordinary Affliction; and he ſo often hinted to me, the Amazement he was in, to behold <hi>Alamire</hi> ſo violently paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate of <hi>Zayde,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> could not forbear asking him the Reaſon; and preſſing him to tell me, Whether <hi>Alamire</hi> had never been in Love before he ſaw <hi>Zayde?</hi> He made ſome difficulty, to tell me the cauſe of his Aſtoniſhment: But, <hi>I</hi> conjured him ſo efficaciouſly, that (at laſt) he told me the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53855:41"/>Adventures of that Prince. <hi>I</hi> will not trouble you with the whole Story, becauſe it would be too tedious; But only, what may ſuffice to let you know <hi>Alamire</hi>'s and my Misfortunes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The HISTORY of <hi>Alamire,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tharſus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have already acquainted you with <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi>'s Birth. What I have told you of his Perſon, and my thoughts of him, ought to perſwade you, that he is as worthy of Love as a man, can be: He had likewiſe, made it his whole Study, from his Youth, to gain the love of all Women: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the manner of living, of the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian</hi> Women, be directly oppoſit to Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, <hi>Alamires</hi> addreſſe, and the pleaſure he took in Surmounting difficulties, made all that eaſie to him, which would have been thought impoſſible by others. As this Prince was unmarried, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion gave him the liberty to have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Wives: ſo there was not a Young Lady in <hi>Tharſus,</hi> that did not flatter her ſelf with the hopes of Marrying him. Nor was he ſorry to find, that this hope made him to be more fayourably
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53855:42"/>uſed; But his inclination lead him to no ingagement that he could not break at pleaſure. He aimed at nothing but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beloved; the pleaſure of being in Love was utterly unknown to him: he never had a ſincere Paſſion; but he was ſo well Verſed in appearing in Love, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ſo; that he perſwaded all thoſe, he had thought worthy, of his Love. It is true alſo, that during the time, he made it his buſineſs to pleaſe; the deſire of making himſelf to be Beloved, gave him a kind of Ardour, which might be taken for a real Paſſion: but as ſoon as 0202 he ſaw himſelf beloyed, having nothing more in his deſires, and not being enough in Love, to find any Pleaſure in Love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ſeparated from Difficulties, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tregues, he thought of nothing more but how to break with thoſe that loved him, and to find out others whom he might draw into the ſame Ingagements.</p>
               <p>One of his Favorites called <hi>Selemin,</hi> was privy to all his Amours, and was himſelf as unconſtant; the <hi>Arabians</hi> do celebrate certain Feaſts at certain times of the year; it is the only time that the Women have any liberty; they are permitted at thoſe times to go about the Town, and to walk in the publick Gardens; they aſſiſt at
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53855:42"/>the ſolemn Plays, which are ſhewed ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, but always Vail'd: <hi>Alamire</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limin</hi> waited with impatience for thoſe Opportunities; they never failed of finding out ſome new unknown Beauties, and ways of ſpeaking to them, and managing ſome private Intregues with them.</p>
               <p>Upon one of theſe Feaſts, <hi>Alamire</hi> ſaw a young Widdow called <hi>Naria,</hi> whoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, Beauty, and Riches, were extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, by chance unveiled as ſhe was ſpeaking to one of her Slaves; he was ſurprized with the Charms of her Beauty; ſhe was a little ſtartled at the ſight of this Prince, but could not forbear looking ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly upon him: which he perceived, he followed her, and made it his buſineſs to let her take notice that he did ſo. In fine, he had ſeen a Fine Woman, and was ſeen by her, and that was enough to erect in him both Love and Hope; the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter he received of <hi>Naria</hi>'s Vertue and Witt, doubled in him the deſire he had to make her in Love with him; he ſought Her in all places with much induſtry, he paſſed very often by her Houſe without ſeeing her, or being ſeen by her; he met her by chance as ſhe was going to a Bath; and was ſo happy as to have a ſight of her Face two or three times, and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53855:43"/>found her moſt Beautiful; and was ſo ſmitten with her, that he believed ſhe deſigned to put a ſtop to all his lightneſs, and inconſtancy,</p>
               <p>Several Days paſſed before <hi>Alamire</hi> could find any ſigne that <hi>Naria</hi> approved of his Love, and begun to be very much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at it; Yet for all that, he did not quit the Deſigne he had laid, to gain the good Eſteem of her, or thoſe other fair Perſons; and above all, of a young Lady, called <hi>Zoromade,</hi> very conſiderable by her Father's Quality, as well as her own Beauty: The difficulty of ſeeing her, was almoſt as great, as that of ſeeing <hi>Naria;</hi> But he was perſwaded, that this Fair Maid would have eaſily found means to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, if ſhe were not ſo narrowly watched by her Mother: So that, he was not ſo eager to ſurmount theſe Obſtacles, as he was to over-come <hi>Narias</hi> Reſiſtance; being ſhe had no Body to controul her: He had endeavoured two or three times, but in vain, to gain ſome of her Slaves, to know from them the Dayes ſhe uſed to go Abroad, and the Places where he might ſee her: At laſt, one of thoſe that ſeemed the moſt Obſtinate, promiſed him to give him Notice of all ſhe did. Two Dayes after, he told him, She was going
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53855:43"/>to a very fine Garden, ſhe had out of Town; and that, if he would pleaſe to walk about that, there were about it Riſings, from whence he might eaſily ſee her. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamire</hi> made uſe of this Intelligence: He goes out of <hi>Tharſus</hi> diſguiſed, and paſſed all the Afternoon about this Garden.</p>
               <p>Towards Evening, as he was ready to return, he ſaw a Door open, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it was the Slave, which he had gained; who beckon'd to him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach: He believed <hi>Naria</hi> was walking, and that he might have a ſight of her from that Door: He advances, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into a Magnificient Arbor, richly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with all things that might add to its Beauty: But what ſurprized him moſt, was the Sight of <hi>Naria,</hi> ſitting upon Cuſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under a ſtately Canopy, after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the <hi>Goddeſs</hi> of <hi>Love;</hi> two or three of her Women ſtood at a Corner of the Arbor: <hi>Alamire</hi> could not forbear running towards her, and caſting himſelf at her Feet, with an Air ſo full of Tranſport and Aſtoniſhment, that he augmented the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Bluſhes, which appeared on the Face of this Beautiful Lady.</p>
               <p>I know not (ſaid ſhe to him, intreating him to riſe) whether I ought of a ſuddain, to ſhew you the Inclination I had for you,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:53855:44"/>having concealed it ſo long a time from you: I believe, I ſhould have hid it, all my Life-time, if you had taken leſs pains to ſhew me the Love you had for me; But, I confeſs, I could not but reſiſt a Paſſion that was purſued and maintained upon ſuch weak and ſlender Hopes. The firſt Moment <hi>I</hi> ſaw you, you appeared Lovely to me; <hi>I</hi> have endeavoured to ſee you undiſcovered, with more care than you did to ſee me: In fine, <hi>I</hi> was deſirous to be as well aſſured of the Paſſion you had for me, by your Words, as you had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced me of it by your Actions.</p>
               <p>Great Gods! What Aſſurance could <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> have in <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Words! She little knew the bewitching and inevitable Charms of his alluring Speeches: He out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did all the Hopes ſhe conceived of his Love; and by his flattering and inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Wit, he gained an intire Conqueſt over the Heart of this Lovely Creature: She promis'd to give him a ſecond Meeting in the ſame place: He returns to <hi>Tharſus,</hi> fully perſwaded, that he was the Man of the World, the moſt in Love; and had almoſt perſwaded <hi>Mulziman</hi> and <hi>Selemin,</hi> that he was ſo. He viſited <hi>Naria</hi> divers times; who ſhewed him the greateſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, and trueſt Marks of Love, that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53855:44"/>ever were: But ſhe told him, That ſhe had learnt, the great Diſpoſition he had to Change: That ſhe was incapable of giving any ſhare of her Heart to any other; and that, if he intended to preſerve hers, he muſt think of no Body elſe: And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt occaſion ſhe ſhould have of being Jealous of him, ſhe would for ever break with him. <hi>Alamire</hi> anſwered her with ſo many Oaths, and ſo much Addreſs, that he perſwaded her of his Eternal Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <p>But the very Thought of ſuch a ſtrict Engagement troubled him; and as there were no Obſtacles to hinder him from the Freedom of ſeeing her, his Love began to grow cold: Nevertheleſs, he continued making ſtill the ſame Proteſtations of Love to her. As ſhe had no other Thoughts but of Marrying him, ſhe believed there was nothing could obſtruct it, ſince ſhe both Loved, and was Beloved of him; inſomuch, that ſhe begun to talk to him of Marriage: <hi>Alamire</hi> was ſurprized at the Diſcourſe; but his Addreſs was ſuch, that the Surprize was not taken notice of; And <hi>Naria</hi> made a full Account, that in a few Dayes, ſhe ſhould be Marryed to this Prince.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:53855:45"/>
               <p>Since his Love for <hi>Naria</hi> began to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, his Purſuit of <hi>Zoromade</hi> began to increaſe: And by the Aſſiſtance of an Aunt of <hi>Selimens,</hi> whom her Nephew's Favour made Complaiſant to the Princes Paſſion, he found means to write to her: The Impoſſibility of ſeeing her, was ſtill the ſame, by which his Paſſion ſtill aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</p>
               <p>All his Hopes was in the Feaſt, that is kept in the beginning of the Year: It was the Cuſtom, to ſend great Preſents one to another, during this Feaſt; and the Streets were crowded with Slaves, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with all that was Rich and Rare to be found. <hi>Alamire</hi> ſent Preſents to divers Perſons: <hi>Naria,</hi> being of a haughty and and proud Diſpoſition, would not give way to any conſiderable Preſents; yet he ſent her ſome <hi>Arabian</hi> Sweets, which were ſo Rare, that none had any of them but himſelf; and ſent them with all the Ornaments, that might make them more agreeable to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naria's</hi> Paſſion was grown ſo violent for this Prince, upon the Receipt of this Preſent, that if ſhe had followed the Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of her Heart, ſhe had ſtaid at Home to think of him; and would have avoided all Divertiſements, where he was not to be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53855:45"/>Notwithſtanding, being invited by <hi>Zoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mades</hi> Mother to a Feaſt at their Houſe, ſhe could not with Decency gratify her Inclination herein. She went thither, and was not a little ſurprized at the Smell of the ſame Perfumes, as ſhe came into a large Cloſet, which <hi>Alamire</hi> had ſent. She ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with ſome Aſtoniſhment, to inquire from whence that Pleaſant Smell came? <hi>Zoromade,</hi> who was Young, and not uſed to conceal any thing, Bluſh'd, and was out of Countenance: Her Mother ſeeing her make no Anſwer, ſaid, She thought, they came from <hi>Selimen</hi>'s Aunt, who had ſent them to her Daughter. This Anſwer confirmed <hi>Naria,</hi> that they came from the Prince: She ſaw them with the ſame Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as hers were, but ſome-what Richer. This Diſcovery made ſo violent an Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon her, that ſhe feigned her ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed, and went Home as really ſick, as ſhe deſired to appear: She was violent, and quick of Apprehenſion; The Thought of being deceived by the Man ſhe Adored, put her into a deplorable Condition: But, before ſhe would give her ſelf up to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, ſhe took a Reſolution to be more fully informed of the Princes Infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>She ſent him word, That ſhe was ſick,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53855:46"/>and that ſhe could not go to any of the Publick Entertainments, during theſe Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivals. <hi>Alamire</hi> came to ſee her; and aſſured her, that he alſo would not ſee any of thoſe Publick Divertiſements, ſince ſhe could not be there: and talked to her after a manner, that did almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her, that ſhe did him wrong to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him. Nevertheleſs, as ſoon as he was gone, ſhe got up, and diſguis'd her ſelf ſo, that ſhe could not be known: She fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented thoſe Places, where it was moſt likely to find him. The firſt Object that offer'd, was <hi>Alamire</hi> diſguiſed; but no Diſguiſe could hide him from her: She ſaw him following <hi>Zoromade;</hi> and during the Playes that were Repreſented, ſhe perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him alwayes cloſe by this Fair Lady. The next Day, ſhe followed him again; But, inſtead of finding him in Purſuit of <hi>Zoromade,</hi> ſhe ſaw him in another Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, cloſely Courting another Lady: Her Grief, at firſt, began to leſſen; and ſhe was not a little pacifyed, to think that <hi>Alamire</hi> had only talked to <hi>Zoromade,</hi> by Accident, or to divert himſelf only. She crowded her ſelf, amongſt thoſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that attended this Young Lady, whom <hi>Alamire</hi> followed; and ſhe came ſo near to him, that at the turning of a Street,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:53855:46"/>where this Young Lady made a ſtop, ſhe heard <hi>Alamire</hi> ſpeaking to her, with the ſame Aire, and thoſe very Terms, that had ſo forcibly perſwaded her of his Love. Judge what became of <hi>Naria,</hi> and the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Affliction ſhe felt. She would have thought her ſelf Happy at that time, if ſhe could have been convinced, that <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romade</hi> was the only Object of <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Purſuit. She would believe, at leaſt, that the Inclination he might have for this Beautiful Perſon, might cauſe his Change: She might have ſlatter'd her ſelf to have been Beloved of him, before his Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for <hi>Zoromade:</hi> But finding, that he was able to have the ſame Care, and ſpeak the ſame Words, to two or three at the ſame time, ſhe was ſatisfyed, that ſhe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had buſted his Wit, and not poſſeſſed his Heart; and that ſhe was only amuſed, without attaining to her Happineſs.</p>
               <p>It was ſuch a cruel Adventure for a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her Humour, that ſhe had not Force enough to bear it: She returns Home o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-whelmed with Grief and Affliction; where ſhe found a Letter from <hi>Alamire,</hi> aſſuring her, that he was ſhut up in his Cloſet at Home; not being able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge himſelf the Pleaſure of ſeeing the Publick Entertainments, ſince he could
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53855:47"/>not hope for that, of ſeeing her there. This Cheat made her judge of what weight were all the paſs'd Actions of <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire.</hi> She was confounded with Shame, for having ſo long pleaſed her ſelf with a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that was but a meer Treachery: She ſoon reſolved what to do; She writ to him, all that Grief, Affection, and Deſpair could invent, of moſt ſenſible, and moſt paſſionate, without acquainting him what ſhould become of her; only, bid him an Eternal Fare-well. This Letter ſurprized him, and gave him ſome ſenſe of Grief: The Beauty and Wit of <hi>Naria,</hi> were of ſuch high Perfection, that it render'd the Loſs of her troubleſome, even to the Inconſtant Humour of <hi>Alamire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He went to tell his Adventure to <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziman,</hi> who made him aſhamed of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure: You are deceived (ſaid he to him,) if you think your manner of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Women, is not contrary to the true Senſe of an Honeſt Man. <hi>Alamire</hi> was netled at this Reproach. I will juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my ſelf to you, anſwered he; for, I have too much Eſteem for you, to let you continue in ſo bad an Opinion of me: Do you think me ſo great a Beaſt, as not to Love with ſincerity, a Perſon that I thought Loved me truly? But, do you
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53855:47"/>think (interrupted <hi>Mulziman</hi>) to juſtify your ſelf, by accuſing thoſe you Love? Did any of them deceive you? Did not <hi>Naria</hi> Love you with a true and ſincere Paſſion? <hi>Naria</hi> believed, ſhe Lov'd me, replyed <hi>Alamire;</hi> but ſhe lov'd my Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the Rank to which I might raiſe her. I have hitherto found nothing but Vanity and Ambition in Women: They loved the Prince, and not <hi>Alamire.</hi> The deſire they have to make a ſignal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and the Ambition to raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above that Slaviſh Life, to which they are ſubject, has created in them what you call Love; as the Pleaſure of being Beloved, and the deſire to over-come Difficulties, begot in me, what ſeemed a Paſſion to them. I believe (ſaid <hi>Mulzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>) you wrong <hi>Naria;</hi> for, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, ſhe truly loved your Perſon. <hi>Naria</hi> ſpoke to me of Marriage (anſwered <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi>) as well as the reſt; and I know not, whether her Paſſion was more ſincere than theirs. How (replyed <hi>Mulziman!</hi>) Would you have a Woman Love you, and not think of Marrying you? No (ſaid <hi>Alamire,</hi>) I would not have them think of Marrying me, while I am above their Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that ſhould pretend to it: But, I would not be unwilling they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53855:48"/>it, if they did not know my Quality; and did in a manner believe, they tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs'd againſt the Rules of Prudence, in Marrying me: But ſo long as they look upon me as a Prince, that may raiſe them above the Sphere they are in; and may give them a Prerogative, to claim more Liberty, than they enjoy in the Quality of a Subject; I ſhall not think my ſelf obliged, to take any great Notice of the Deſigne they may have to Marry me; or take it for a true Love. You ſhould ſee, added he, That I am very capable of Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſincerely, if I found a Perſon that ſhould Love me, without knowing who <hi>I</hi> am. You deſire an Impoſſibility, to ſhew your Fidelity, replyed <hi>Mulziman;</hi> and if you were capable of being Conſtant, you ſhould meet with enough, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting ſuch extraordinary Occaſions to ſhew it.</p>
               <p>The Impatience he was in, to know what was become of <hi>Naria,</hi> broke off this Converſation: He goes to her Houſe, where he learnt, that ſhe was gone to <hi>Mecka:</hi> and that none knew the Way ſhe took, nor the Time when ſhe would come back. This was enough to make him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <hi>Naria:</hi> All his Thoughts are now bent upon <hi>Zoromade;</hi> who was guarded
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53855:48"/>with ſo much Care, that it render'd all his Addreſſes in a manner vain: Not knowing, therefore, what other Courſe to take, he reſolves to venture upon a way, the moſt dangerous in thoſe Countries, that could be thought of; which was, to hide himſelf in one of thoſe Houſes, where Women uſe to Bath themſelves.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Baths are ſtately Pallaces; Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men frequent them two or three times a week: They take a pride to ſhew their Grandure and Magnificence, by making a great number of Slaves to March before and after them, carrying all thoſe things of which they have uſe in their Bathing Houſes; the entrance of thoſe Houſes is forbidden to all men upon pain of Death, and there is no Mercy for them, that are found there? <hi>Alamire</hi>'s quality ſeemed to warrant him againſt the ordinary Laws; but his Rank expoſed him to a general Revolt and Sedition, in which he ſhould not be able to ſave either his Life or Eſtate.</p>
               <p>All Reaſons were too weak to retain him from it; he writ to <hi>Zoromade</hi> that he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to hazard all for to ſee her, &amp; intreated her to inſtruct him how he might ſpeak to her; <hi>Zoromade</hi> made a difficulty to conſent to the hazard to which he was to expoſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53855:49"/>himſelf; but at laſt Led away by her Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for him, and forced by that inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Conſtraint under which the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian</hi> Women live, writ to him, That if he could find means to get into the Bathing Houſe, he muſt inform himſelf of that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment where ſhe uſed to be; that there was a Cloſet where he might conceal himſelf; that ſhe would not Bath that Day; and that whileſt her Mother was in the Bath, ſhe might have the opportunity of entertaining him. <hi>Alamire</hi> felt a ſenſible pleaſure, in the difficulty of his enterpriſe: He won the maſter of the Baths by great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents; he learnt the Day <hi>Zoromade</hi> was to come thither; he got in by Night, and was conducted to the Appartment wherein that Cloſet was, where he remain'd until morning, with all the the impatience that a man truly in love could be in.</p>
               <p>Much about the time that <hi>Zoromade</hi> was to come, he heard a Noiſe in the next Chamber, as if divers People were come into it; a little after, the Noiſe leſſen'd, and the Cloſet Dore is open'd, he expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee <hi>Zoromade</hi> come in to him; but in her ſtead, he ſees another Perſon whom he knew not, Richly attired, of a Beauty that had all the Flower, and all the Life of a blooming Youth. This Lady was as
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53855:49"/>much ſurprized at the ſight of <hi>Alamire,</hi> as he was to ſee her; he was no leſs proper than ſhe, to cauſe Aſtoniſhment, by the agreeableneſs of his Perſon, and the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Apparel. It was ſo unnatural a thing, to ſee a Man in that Place; that, if <hi>Alamire</hi> had not made ſigns to this young Lady, to hold her peace, ſhe had cried out loud enough, to make all that was in the Room, to come into the Cloſet: She comes nearer to <hi>Alamire,</hi> who was raviſht with this new adventure, and asked him by what accident he came into this place; he told her it was a ſtory too tedious to be told then, but conjured her to ſay nothing, and not to ruin a man, who valued not the danger he was in, ſince he ow'd to it the pleaſure of ſeeing the beautiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Perſon in the World; ſhe bluſhes with an ayre of Innocence and Modeſty, capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of inflaming a heart leſs ſenſible than <hi>Alamire's. I</hi> should be very ſorry, repli'd she, to do any thing that might hurt you. But you have run great hazard in coming in here; I know not whether you are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the danger you are in.</p>
               <p>Yes Madam, I know it, and it is not the greateſt that I am threaten'd withall this Day. After theſe words of which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:53855:50"/>she underſtood the meaning, he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to tell him who she was, and how she came to enter into that Cloſet: My Name is <hi>Elſibery,</hi> anſwered she; I am the Governor of <hi>Lemnos</hi> his Daughter, my Mother came to <hi>Tharſus</hi> two Days ago, where she never had been before, no more than I; she is now in the Bath; I was not diſpos'd to Bath, and I came by chance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Cloſet; but I beg of you likewiſe added she, to tell me who you are? <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> was glad to meet with a young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that knew him not: He told her, his Name was <hi>Selemin,</hi> (it was the firſt Name he could think of): As he talked to her, he heard a Noiſe: <hi>Elſibery</hi> went towards the Cloſet-Door, to hinder any to come in; <hi>Alamire</hi> followed her two or three Steps, forgetting the Danger he expoſs'd himſelf to. May not one hope to ſee you again, Madam, ſaid he? I know not (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed ſhe, with an Ayre full of trouble,) but I think, it is not impoſible: With this, ſhe went out, and ſhut the Door after her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> was charmed with this Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: He never ſaw any thing ſo Beautiful, nor ſo Lovely, as <hi>Elſibery:</hi> He did believe, that he had obſerved by her, that he was not unpleaſing to her: She did not know
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53855:50"/>him to be the Prince of <hi>Tharſus.</hi> In fine, He found in this Lady, all that might ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly touch him. He ſtaid until Night, in that Cloſet, without once thinking, that that he was come thither to ſee <hi>Zoromade;</hi> ſo full was his Imagination, with the Charms of <hi>Elſibery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>Zoromade</hi> was not ſo eaſie in her Mind; She truly loved <hi>Alamire:</hi> The Danger in which <hi>Alamire</hi> was in, put her into a Mortal Diſquiet, and a ſenſible Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, that ſhe could reap no Benefit by it. Her Mother was indiſpoſed, and would not go to the Bath; and therefore, her Appartment was given to <hi>Elſibery</hi>'s Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Alamire,</hi> at his return, found a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from <hi>Zoromade;</hi> informing him, what <hi>I</hi> have told you; and likewiſe, that they talked of Marrying her out of hand: But that, ſhe was not much diſquieted at it, ſeeing he might prevent it, by declaring to her Father, the Intentions he had for her. He ſhewed this Letter to <hi>Mulziman,</hi> to let him ſee, that all Womens Love to him, tended only to get him to marry them: He told him alſo, his Adventure in the Bathing-Houſe: He did Exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to him the Charms of <hi>Elſibery,</hi> the Joy he had to believe, that ſhe had an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination for him, without knowing him
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53855:51"/>to be the Prince. He aſſured him, That he had now found ſomething, that deſerved to engage his Heart; and that he ſhould ſee, how real his intentions ſhould be for <hi>Elſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery;</hi> and, in truth, he reſolved to leave off all other Purſuits, and to think of no Body elſe, but how to win the Love of this Beautiful Perſon. It was almoſt impoſſible for him to ſee her; eſpecially, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to make himſelf known, as Prince of <hi>Tharſus:</hi> The firſt Reſolution he takes, was to hide himſelf once more in the Bathing-Houſe: But, he underſtood, that <hi>Elſiberyes</hi> Mother was ſick, and that her Daughter would not come abroad with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her.</p>
               <p>In the mean-time, the time of <hi>Zoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mades</hi> Marriage was at hand; and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair ſhe was in, to ſee her ſelf ſleighted and forſaken by the Prince, made her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to it: As her Father was a Man of great Quality, and the Man she was to marry was no leſs; ſo it was reſolved, the Ceremony should be very Splendid at her Wedding. <hi>Alamire</hi> learnt, that <hi>Elſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery</hi> was to be there. The manner of Marrying amongſt the <hi>Arabians,</hi> could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford him no Hope of ſeeing her there; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Women are quite ſeparated from the Men, both in their Moſques, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:53855:51"/>at their Feaſts: He reſolves, nevertheleſs, to hazard as much for her, as he had done for <hi>Zoromade:</hi> He feigned himſelf ſick the Wedding-Day, the better to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe himſelf from aſſiſting Publickly at the Ceremony: He put himſelf into Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Attire; and put on a long Vail, ſuch as the Women do wear when they go abroad; and goes to the Moſque with <hi>Selimen</hi>'s Aunt. He ſaw <hi>Elſibery</hi> coming in; and, though ſhe was Veil'd, yet her Garbe was ſo particular, and her Habit ſo different from that the Women of <hi>Thar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> wear, that he was not afraid to be miſtaken in her: He followed her cloſe to the Place, where the Ceremony was to be performed. He placed himſelf ſo near <hi>Zoromade,</hi> that, carryed on by the Remains of that Humour, that was ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to him, he could not forbear making himſelf known to her; and ſpeaking to her, as if he had diſguiſed himſelf only to ſee her. His Sight cauſed ſo much trouble in <hi>Zoromade,</hi> that ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to go back ſome Steps: And, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf towards him; It is an inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane thing of you (ſaid ſhe) to come to trouble my Quiet, by an Action that ſhould perſwade me, that you Love me, if I were not well aſſured of the contrary;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53855:52"/>But, I hope, I ſhall not long ſuffer the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, which you have cauſed me. She could ſay no more, nor could he make a Reply; for, the Ceremony ended, and all the Women went to their own Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> never thought of the Grief, in which he ſaw <hi>Zoromade;</hi> he was ſo full of his Deſire and Care, how to ſpeak to <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibery:</hi> He kneel'd juſt by her, and begun to ſay his Prayers very loud, after the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabian</hi> Faſhion: That kind of confuſed Murmur of ſo many People, that ſpeak all at once, make it hard to be heard, but by thoſe that ſtand cloſe to one another. <hi>Alamire,</hi> without turning his Face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Elſibery,</hi> or changing the Tone in which he prayed, call'd her ſeveral times by her Name: She turned towards him; and, as he ſaw that ſhe looked upon him, he lets fall his Book; and in taking it up, he lifted up his Vail a little; ſo that, <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibery</hi> alone might ſee him: He ſhewed her a Countenance, whoſe Beauty and Youth did not bely the Habit of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. He found, that his Diſguiſe did not deceive <hi>Elſibery;</hi> Yet, he asked her, If he was ſo Happy, as to be known a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by her? <hi>Elſibery,</hi> whoſe Vail was not quite down, turning her Eyes towards
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:53855:52"/>
                  <hi>Alamire,</hi> without turning her Head; I know you too well, ſaid ſhe; but, I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the Danger you are in. There is none ſo great, to which I would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my ſelf, rather than not ſee you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed he. It was not to ſee me, ſaid ſhe, that you expos'd your ſelf in the Bathing-Houſe; and, perhaps, it is not for me, that you are now here. It is for you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, Madam, replyed he; and you ſhall ſee me every Day in the ſame Dangers, unleſs you give me ſome Opportunity of ſpeaking to you. I go to Morrow, ſaid ſhe, with my Mother to the <hi>Caliph</hi>'s Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; be you there with the Prince: My Vail ſhall be off, becauſe it is the firſt time that I come thither. She would ſay no more, for fear of being over-heard by the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were near her.</p>
               <p>She put <hi>Alamire</hi> into great Perplexities about the Aſſignation ſhe gave him; he very well knew that the firſt time Women of Quality are admitted to the <hi>Caliphs</hi> Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, if the <hi>Caliphe</hi> or the Princes his Children come into the place where the Women are, they do not let down their Veils, and after that they are always Vei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: So that <hi>Alamire</hi> was ſure to ſee <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibery;</hi> but then he muſt be forced to ſhew himſelf, as Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> and that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53855:53"/>was, what he could not conſent to do. The pleaſure of being beloved for the ſole Beauty of his Perſon, was ſo great and ſenſible to him, that he was reſolv'd not to rob himſelf of it; but yet it was a great trouble to him to loſe an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſeeing <hi>Elſibery,</hi> and an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which ſhe her ſelf gave him. That litle Jealouſie which ſhe ſhewed; For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found him in the Bathing-Houſe, whether he came not for her ſake, ingaged him the more not to omit any thing that might perſwade Her of the reality of his inclinations for her. This perplexity made him heſitate a good while without anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her. At laſt he asked her if he might not Writ to her: I dare not truſt any Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaid ſhe, unleſs you can gain, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, a Slave whoſe Name is <hi>Zebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lec.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> was ſatisfi'd with theſe Words, they leave the Temple; he goes to change his Habit, and to take his meaſures what to do the next Day, though he found it difficult to conceal his Quality from <hi>Elſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery;</hi> and though it was a great trouble to him to avoid ſeeing the perſon of the World he moſt coveted to ſee, yet he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to do it, becauſe he determin'd to find whether he could be truly loved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53855:53"/>out the help of his Quality; by which, after he had conſidered how to carry on his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he writ this Letter to <hi>Elſibery,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The LETTER of <hi>ALAMIRE</hi> to <hi>ELSIBERY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF I had already deſired any Favour from you, or that you had given me any hope, perhaps I ſhould not trouble you with the Requeſt I am going to make, I thought it might then ſeem more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable than now. But Madam, you ſcarce know me, and I cannot flatter my ſelf, with the thought that I could make any impreſſion upon your Heart; You are not ingaged to me either by inclination or word; and you are going to morrow to a place where you will ſee a Prince, who never yet ſaw any thing of Beautiful, but he was in love with: What may not I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prend, Madam, from that interview? I cannot doubt but <hi>Alamire</hi> will fall in love with you; and though perhaps it may ſeem a Caprice in me to fear him as much as I do, and to apprehend that he may be ſo happy as to pleaſe you, yet I cannot forbear praying you not to ſee him. Why ſhould you refuſe me this Madam?
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53855:54"/>It is no Favor I ask; and I am happily the only man in the World that ever did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſuch a thing; I know my requeſt will ſeem ſtrange to you, ſince it appears more ſtrange to my ſelf; But do not refuſe this Boon to one who has expoſed his Life, that he might have the Happineſs, only to ſay, he loves you.</p>
               <p>Having writ this Letter, he diſguiſes himſelf to go along with ſome he confided in, to find out who this Slave ſhould be, of whom <hi>Elſibery</hi> ſpoke: He beſtir'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo well about the Governour of <hi>Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos</hi> his Houſe, that, at laſt, he gained the Favour of an old Slave, to bring <hi>Zebelec</hi> to him. He ſaw at a diſtance, this young Slave coming; and was ſurprized with his Beauty and Shape, and the Fineneſs of his Face. <hi>Alamire</hi> ſtood ſculking in a dark Entry; and this young Slave looked upon him, as he came towards him, as if he had known him formerly: But, as ſoon as he came near, the Prince (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhewing himſelf) begun to ſpeak to him of <hi>Elſibery.</hi> The Slave hearing a Voice which he knew not, of a ſuddain, changed his Countenance; and, after a great Sigh, looks down, and ſtood ſilent, with ſo profound a Sadneſs, that <hi>Alamire</hi> could not forbear asking him the Reaſon
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:53855:54"/>thereof. I believed, I knew him that asked for me, anſwered he; and I did not think, that I was call'd to hear talk of <hi>Elſibery:</hi> But, go on; what-ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards <hi>Elſibery,</hi> concerns me near. <hi>Alamire</hi> was ſurprized and troubl'd at the manner of this Slave's Diſcourſe; He went on, nevertheleſs, in Recommending to him, the Delivery of a Letter to <hi>Elſibery;</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming himſelf <hi>Selemin:</hi> The Sadneſs and Beauty of this Slave, made the Prince imagine, That this was ſome Lover of <hi>Elſibery,</hi> who had diſguiſed himſelf to be near her. The Trouble in which he ſaw him, when he ſpoke to him of Letters that he was to give, confirm'd him in that Opinion: But, he reflected like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, That if <hi>Elſibery</hi> had known this Slave to be her Lover, ſhe would not make Choice of him, to convey his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals Lotters. In fine, This Adventure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed him; And, be it how it would, this Slave appeared to him too Beautiful, and of an Ayre ſo far above his Condition, to be permitted to continue about <hi>Elſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He expected the next Day with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſorts of Diſquiet; He went be-times to his Mothers Appartment: No Lover was ever more impatient, to ſee his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:53855:55"/>than he was not to ſee his: Nor had any Lover more Reaſon to wiſh, he might not ſee her. He believed, that if <hi>Elſibery</hi> came not to the Pallace, it was to grant him the Favour he beg'd of her: That it was a true Signe, that ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Letter, which he gave <hi>Zebelec</hi> for her; and that, if that Slave had given it her, it was apparent he was none of his Rival. In fine, In not ſeeing <hi>Elſibery</hi> come along with her Mother, he was ſure he had Eſtabliſhed a Correſpondency with her; that he had no Rival, and that he might hope to gain her Love. He was taken up with theſe Thoughts, when Word was brought him, that <hi>Elſiberyes</hi> Mother was coming; and he had the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee, that her Daughter was not come with her. His Tranſports were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible: He retired, being unwilling his Face ſhould be known to his Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Mother; and went to his own Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to wait for the time which he appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſpeak to <hi>Zebelec.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fair Slave came to him, with as much Sadneſs as he ſhewed the Day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; aad brought him <hi>Elſiberyes</hi> Anſwer: He was over-joyed at this Letter: He found in it Modeſty, mixt with much Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: She aſſur'd him, that ſhe would
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53855:55"/>have for him the Complacency of not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> and that ſhe ſhould never make a difficulty of granting him ſuch Favours. She prayed him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, not to hazard himſelf for her; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that her own Natural Fearfulneſs, and the ſtrictneſs of the Watch that was kept over her, would render all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ineffectual. Though <hi>Alamire</hi> was extreamly ſatisfyed with this Letter; yet, he could not endure the Beauty and Sadneſs of the Slave: He asked him divers Queſtions about the Means of ſeeing <hi>Elſibery:</hi> But, the Slave made but cold An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers. This Proceeding increaſed the Princes Suſpicions; and, as he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more touched with the Beauty of <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibery,</hi> than he had ever been with any other; ſo he feared to enter into a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of uſing her, as he had done all thoſe that he Loved before; or to engage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a Perſon, that might have other Inclinations. In the mean-time, he writ to her every Day: He obliged her to let him know to what Places ſhe went: And his Love made him as careful to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſeeing her in all Publick Places, where ſhe might know him to be the Prince, as he was induſtrious to find out the means of ſeeing her in Private. He
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53855:56"/>ſo carefully obſerved all the Places about the Houſe wherein ſhe lodged; that he found, that upon the Top of the Houſe, which was made into a Terraſs, there was a Balcony jetting out over a Back-Street, which was ſo narrow, that one might Diſcourſe from the Houſe that was againſt it: He ſoon found wayes to be Maſter of that Houſe. He writ to <hi>Elſibery,</hi> conjuring her to be the Night following upon the Terras, where ſhe might be ſeen and entertain'd by him. For, being come thither, <hi>Alamire</hi> might eaſily diſcourſe with her, without being over-heard by any other: Nor was the Night ſo dark, but that he might have the Pleaſure diſtinctly to ſee that Beauty, of which he was ſo enamour'd.</p>
               <p>They enter'd into a long Diſcourſe of the Inclinations they had for each other: <hi>Elſibery</hi> deſired to be informed, what Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture had brought him to the Bathing-houſe: He confeſſed to her the whole Truth, and all that had paſſed betwixt <hi>Zoromade</hi> and him. Young People are too ſenſible of theſe kind of Sacrifices, without apprehending the Conſequences of them for themſelves. <hi>Elſibery</hi> had a violent Paſſion for <hi>Alamire:</hi> She gave her ſelf wholly up in this Interview; and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:53855:56"/>they reſolved to ſee one another often in that Place. As he was ready to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, he turned his Head by chance, and was not a little ſurprized, to ſee the Fair Slave, that had already cauſed him ſo much Diſquiet, ſtanding at one of the Corners of the Terraſs.</p>
               <p>He could not conceal his Trouble; but ſaid, Madam, if I have ſhewed you ſome Jealouſie the firſt time I writ to you, may I be ſo bold, as to ſhew it you again the firſt time I ſpeak to you? I know, that Women of your Quality have alwayes Slaves about them; But, I think, they are not of the Age and Meine of him, I ſee with you. I do confeſs, that what I know of the Perſon and Wit of <hi>Zebelec,</hi> may render him as dangerous to me, as the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> can be. <hi>Elſibery</hi> Smiled at this Diſcourſe; and calling the Beautiful Slave, Come <hi>Zebelec,</hi> ſaid ſhe; Come, and cure <hi>Selemin</hi> of the Jealouſie you have cauſed him. Madam, I dare not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your Permiſſion; and I wiſh, replyed <hi>Zebelec,</hi> That you had the Power to make him Jealous: It is not for my own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt I wiſh it; it is for Yours, and for the Apprehenſions I have of the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, to which you are going to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your ſelf. But Sir, continued the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53855:57"/>Slave, addreſſing her ſelf to the Prince, whom ſhe took for <hi>Selemin;</hi> It is not juſt, to let you ſuſpect the Vertue of <hi>Elſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am a wretched Creature, whom Chance has placed in her Service; I am a Chriſtian of <hi>Greece,</hi> of a Birth, far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Condition you ſee me in: A little Beauty (of which, there are ſcarce any Foot-ſteps left) drew many Lovers to Court me, in the Prime of my Youth: I found ſo little Truth, and ſo much Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery in them, that I looked upon them with Scorn. One more Unfaithful than all the reſt (but who knew how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe it better) gain'd my Affections: I broke off for his ſake, a conſiderable Match. My Parents perſecuted us: He was forced to fly: He Marries me; I Diſguis'd my ſelf in Man's Apparel, and followed him: We took Shipping: There happen'd a Perſon of great Beauty to be in the ſame Ship, brought thither by ſome extraordinary Accident, to paſs into <hi>Aſia,</hi> as well as my ſelf: My Husband fell in Love with her: We were ſet upon, and taken by the <hi>Arabians:</hi> They ſhared the Slaves: My Husband, and one of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, had their Choice to be in one Lot with thoſe, that ſhould fall to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:53855:57"/>or the Lieutenant's Share: It was my Lot, to fall to the Captain; and, by an unheard-of Ingratitude, my Husband choſe to go with the Lieutenant, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this Woman he Loved: Neither my Preſence nor Tears, nor what I had done for him, nor the wretched Condition in which he was going to leave me, could move him: Judge of my Grief! I was led hither: My good Fortune gave me to <hi>Elſiberies</hi> Father. Though I have ſeen my Husbands Ingratitude, I cannot altogether loſe the Hope of his Returning; and that was it, that cauſed the Change you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in my Face, the firſt time I came to ſpeak to you: I was in hopes, it might be him that deſired to ſpeak to me; and, as ill grounded as this Hope was, I could not loſe it without Grief. I do not oppoſe the Inclination which <hi>Elſibery</hi> has for you: <hi>I</hi> know, by woful Experience, how vain it is, to oppoſe ſuch kind of Thoughts: But, <hi>I</hi> grieve for her; and <hi>I</hi> do fore-ſee, the Mortal Pangs into which you will throw her. She never was in Love: She is now Engaging her ſelf into a ſincere and real Paſſion for you; which no Man that has been already in Love, can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:53855:58"/>
               <p>When ſhe had left ſpeaking; <hi>Elſibery</hi> told <hi>Alamire,</hi> That her Father and Mother knew her Quality, her Sex, and her Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; but for Reaſons that ſhe had to remain unknown, ſhe appeared in the Guiſe of a Slave. The Prince was Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Wit and Vertue of <hi>Zebelec;</hi> but more, to find how vain the Grounds of his Jealouſies were. In the Sequel, He found ſo many Charms, and ſo much Sincerity in <hi>Elſiberies</hi> Conduct, that he was convinced, that he was never Beloved but by her alone. She lov'd him for Loves ſake, without conſidering what this Paſſion tended to: She never dived into his Fortune, nor his Intentions: She hazzarded all to ſee him; and did all things blindfold, that he could deſire: Another Woman would find much Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, in the Conduct he deſired ſhe ſhould obſerve. He would have her ſtill believe him to be <hi>Selemin:</hi> He was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to hinder her from going to certain Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Feaſts, where he was obliged to appear as Prince: But ſhe found nothing difficult, that pleaſed him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> believed himſelf, for a time moſt happy to be beloved for his own ſake; but it came into his Head, that although <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibery</hi> loved him without knowing that he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:53855:58"/>was the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> it might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that ſhe might forſake him for one, that ſhould be of that Quality: He was reſolved to put her Heart to the Teſt, by making the true <hi>Selemin</hi> paſs for the Prince of <hi>Tharſus;</hi> making Love to her; and to ſee with his own Eyes, after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhe would treat him: He told <hi>Sele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> his Intention; and they, together, found means to put it in Execution. <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> made a Horſe-Race; and told <hi>Elſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery,</hi> That, to give her ſome ſhare in the Divertiſement, he would get the Prince, with all his Company, to paſs by her Window: That the Prince and He would be Attired alike, and that he would Ride cloſe by the Princes ſide; and that, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had alwayes apprehended her ſeeing <hi>Alamire,</hi> he believed himſelf too well aſſured of her Heart, to apprehend, that the Prince might draw her Eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, chiefly in a Place where he ſhould be near enough, to have his ſhare of her Looks. <hi>Elſibery</hi> did verily believe, that he whom ſhe ſhould ſee with her Lover, would be the Prince of <hi>Tharſus;</hi> and the next Day, ſeeing the true <hi>Selemin</hi> with <hi>Alamire,</hi> did not doubt, but that it was the Prince: She thought, her Lover had no Reaſon to repreſent <hi>Alamire,</hi> for
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53855:59"/>ſuch a formidable Man, ſince ſhe thought him nothing ſo agreeable, as him ſhe took for his Favourite. She did not forget to tell him the Judgment ſhe made of him: But, that was not enough to him: He reſolved to try further, whether this ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Prince would not take with her, when he ſhould ſeem to be in Love with her, and propoſe to Marry her.</p>
               <p>At one of the <hi>Arabian</hi> Feaſts, where the Prince was not obliged to appear in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; he told <hi>Elſibery,</hi> that he would Diſguiſe himſelf, that he might be near her: He did ſo; but carryed <hi>Selemin</hi> with him: They placed themſelves near <hi>Elſibery,</hi> and <hi>Selemin</hi> call'd her three or four times: her mind being full of <hi>Alamire,</hi> ſhe doubted not, but that it was he; And taking her time, where no body looked on her, ſhe lifted up her Vail to ſhew him her Face, and began to ſpeak to him; But ſhe was ſurpriſed, when ſhe ſaw him near her, whom ſhe took for the Prince of <hi>Tharſus; Selemin</hi> ſeemed to be ſurpriſed likewiſe, and ſmitten with her Beauty; He fain would have ſpoken to her, but ſhe would not hear him; And being troubled, at this Adventure, ſhe went nearer to her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; In ſo much, that <hi>Alamire</hi> could not accoſt her all the reſt of the day. At
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53855:59"/>Night, <hi>Alamire</hi> went to ſpeak to her up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Terraſs: She told him all that happen'd to her, and that with ſo much Truth and Exactneſs, and ſuch Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, leſt he ſhould ſuſpect that ſhe had any way contributed to it, that <hi>Alamire</hi> had all the Reaſon imaginable, to be well ſatisfyed: Yet he was not content, but cauſed the old Slave (which he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready found very ſenſible of Preſents) to be bribed, to carry a Letter from the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Prince to <hi>Elſibery:</hi> As the Slave would have given it her, ſhe chid him foundly, and refuſed the Letter: She gave an account of it to <hi>Alamire,</hi> who knew it already, and enjoyed the Pleaſure of his Cheat. To accompliſh what he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, he carries <hi>Selemin</hi> to the Terraſs, where he was uſed to ſpeak to <hi>Elſibery,</hi> and hid himſelf ſo, as ſhe could not ſee him; but might hear every Word they ſpoke. <hi>Elſibery</hi> was extreamly ſurprized, to ſee the ſuppoſed Prince upon the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſs: At firſt, ſhe thought to with-draw; but her Suſpicion, that her Lover betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to the Prince, and her deſire to find it out, kept her there for ſome Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. I will not tell you, Madam, (ſaid he) Whether it was by my own Addreſs, or by the Conſent of him you thought to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53855:60"/>find here, that <hi>I</hi> poſſeſs the Place that was intended for him; neither will I tell you, whether he be ignorant of my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions for you; but you may judge, by the likelihood of it, and by the Power that the Quality of a Prince may give me: I will only tell you, That by one ſight of you, you have done that in me which long Converſe could never effect: I would never Engage my ſelf; and now, my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Happineſs is, to induce you to accept of the Quality I poſſeſs: You are the only Perſon, to whom <hi>I</hi> ever have offer'd it; and you ſhall be the laſt, to whom <hi>I</hi> ever ſhall offer it: Think of it, Madam, more than once, before you deny me; and think, that in refuſing the Prince of <hi>Thar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> you refuſe the only Means to draw you out of that Eternal Captivity, to which you are now deſtined.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elſibery</hi> could hear no more what the ſuppoſed Prince ſaid to her: As ſoon as he gave her to underſtand, that her Lover had ſacrificed her to his Ambition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any Reply to what he had ſaid to her: I know not, Sir, (anſwered ſhe) by what Adventure you came hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But let it be how it will, <hi>I</hi> muſt hold no longer Converſation with you; and <hi>I</hi> beſeech you, to allow me the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53855:60"/>to with draw. In ſaying theſe Words, ſhe left the Terraſs, and retired to her Chamber with <hi>Zebelec,</hi> who had follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her with as much Diſquiet, and Prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Mind, as <hi>Alamire</hi> had Joy and Tranquillity: He ſaw, with Delight, that ſhe deſpiſed the Offers of ſo great a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, at the ſame time that ſhe had grounds to believe, that he had deceived her: Nor could he any longer doubt, but that ſhe was proof againſt thoſe Aſpiring Thoughts, of which he was apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive. The next Day, he tryed again to get a Letter conveyed to her from the Prince, to ſee if Spite and Rage had not cauſed her to change her Mind: But the old Slave that was intruſted with it, and endeavoured to deliver it, was as ill han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled by her, as he had been the firſt time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elſibery</hi> paſſed the Night with incredible Grief: There was all the Appearance imaginable, that her Lover had betray'd her: There was none but him, that could diſcover their Intelligence, and the Place where they uſed to ſpeak to one another. Nevertheleſs, her great Kindneſs for him, would not let her condemn him without hearing him. She ſaw him the next Day; and he argued his Caſe ſo well, that he
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:53855:61"/>perſwaded her, that he was betray'd by one of his People; and that the <hi>Caliphe,</hi> at his Son's Requeſt, had kept him a part of the Night from coming upon the Terraſs: Nay, he perſwaded her, that he was ſenſibly diſpleaſed at the Princes Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for her. The fair Slave was not ſo eaſie of belief, as <hi>Elſibery;</hi> and the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſhe had of the Falſhood of Men, would not permit her to give Credit to the ſuppoſed <hi>Selemin</hi>'s Words: She endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured (but in vain) to let her ſee, that he impoſed upon her: But, a little while after, Chance gave her occaſion to convince her of it.</p>
               <p>The true <hi>Selemin</hi> was not ſo taken up with the Princes Gallantries, but that he had time enough to have ſome of his own: The Lady he was in Love with, had a young Slave that waited upon her, who was paſſionately Enamoured of <hi>Zabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lec,</hi> whom ſhe took for a Man. She told her the Love that was betwixt <hi>Selemin,</hi> and her Miſtriſs, and the Contrivance they had found to ſee one another. <hi>Zebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lec,</hi> who knew <hi>Alamire</hi> by no other Name but that of <hi>Selemin,</hi> cauſed her ſelf to be thorowly informed of all that might let <hi>Elſibery</hi> ſee the Infidelity of her Lover; and went in that very inſtant, to tell her
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:53855:61"/>of it. She was ſenſibly afflicted at this Diſcovery; yet ſhe gave her ſelf up to her Sorrow, without reflecting injuriouſly upon him that cauſed it. <hi>Zebelec</hi> uſed all the Arguments ſhe could think of, to perſwade her never more to ſee <hi>Alamire;</hi> nor to hearken to any Juſtifications, which could be no other but new Inventions, to cheat her. <hi>Elſibery</hi> was willing enough to follow her Advice, but had not the Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> came that very Evening to the Terraſs; and much aſtoniſhed, when <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibery</hi> began their Interview with a Flood of Tears, and followed it with Reproaches ſo tender, that even thoſe who had no Love for her, could not chooſe but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for her. He could not imagine, what ſhe could accuſe him of; or by what ſtrange turn of Fortune, ſhe alone ſhould accuſe him of Infidelity; having never been Faithful to any but to her ſelf: He juſtifyed himſelf with all the Force that Truth could inſpire: But, in ſpight of the Diſpoſition ſhe was in to believe him Innocent, ſhe could not give Credit to his Words. He preſſed her to tell him, who ſhe ſhould be, that ſhe thought him in Love with: She did ſo, and told him all the Circumſtances of their Commerce.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:53855:62"/>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> was not a little ſurprized, to find that it was the Name of <hi>Selemin,</hi> that made him appear Guilty; and was much perplexed, to find by what means he ſhould go about to juſtifie himſelf: He could not reſolve it preſently: His only Courſe was, to make new Proteſtations of his Innocency, without engaging him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into a further Juſtification: His Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, and his Words, in general, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd <hi>Elſibery</hi> of his Infidelity.</p>
               <p>He goes immediately: to <hi>Selemin,</hi> to tell him his Misfortune; and think with him, of the Means to make his Innocence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. <hi>I</hi> would break off with the Perſon <hi>I</hi> Love, for your ſake, ſaid <hi>Selemin,</hi> if <hi>I</hi> thought that would be any Advantage to you: But, although <hi>I</hi> ſhould leave ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her, <hi>Elſibery</hi> would believe ſtill, that there was a time in which you had been Unfaithful to her; and ſo, would not be able to give any Credit to your Words: If you would take away all Ground of Suſpicion from her, my Opinion is, That you own who you are, and who <hi>I</hi> am. She has Loved you, without the Help of your Quality: She believed me to be the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> and deſpiſed me for your ſake; and, in my Opinion, that was what you would be at. You have Reaſon
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:53855:62"/>my dear <hi>Selemin,</hi> cryed the Prince, but <hi>I</hi> cannot reſolve, to diſcover my Quality to <hi>Elſibery: I</hi> ſhall loſe by that Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, all that was Charming in my Love; <hi>I</hi> ſhall loſe the only true Pleaſure <hi>I</hi> ever had; and, <hi>I</hi> know not, whether <hi>I</hi> ſhall not loſe the Paſſion <hi>I</hi> had for her. But, conſider alſo, Sir, anſwered <hi>Selemin,</hi> that in going ſtill by my Name, you will loſe the Heart of <hi>Elſibery;</hi> and that, in loſing that, you will loſe all the Pleaſures, that a falſe Imagination makes you apprehend, can never be found again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Selemin</hi> ſpoke ſo convincing to <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire,</hi> that (at laſt) he made him reſolve to diſcover himſelf to <hi>Elſibery:</hi> He did ſo that very Evening: And none ever was tranſported of a ſuddain, from ſo deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Condition, to ſo happy a State, as ſhe was. She found Marks of a moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and tender Paſſion, in all thoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents that before appeared to her as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits: She had the Pleaſure, to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced <hi>Alamire</hi> of her Inclination for him, without knowing that he was a Prince. Laſtly, Her Tranſports were ſo great, that her Heart was ſcarce able to contain them; nor did ſhe hide them from <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire:</hi> But, he ſuſpected this Joy of hers: He believed, the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> had a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:53855:63"/>ſhare in it, and that <hi>Elſibery</hi> was more ſenſibly touched for having him for her Lover: But, he concealed his Thoughts from her, and continued viſiting her with much Aſſiduity. <hi>Zebelec</hi> was ſurprized, that ſhe had been deceived in her Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Men's Paſſions; and envyed <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiberies</hi> Happineſs, in having found ſo Faithful a Lover: But, the Cauſe of her Envy did not laſt long. It was impoſſible, but that thoſe extraordinary Things which <hi>Alamire</hi> had done for <hi>Elſibery,</hi> ſhould add new Life to the Paſſion ſhe had for him: The Prince perceived it. This redoubling of her Love, appeared to him an Infidelity; and cauſed in him the ſame trouble, which the Decreaſe of it ought to have done. In fine, He thought himſelf ſo well aſſured, that the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> was better Beloved, than <hi>Alamire</hi> had been under the Name of <hi>Selemin,</hi> that his Paſſion began to diminiſh, though he had no Engagement elſe-where. He had already had of ſo many ſorts; and, this laſt had ſomething in it that was ſo quick, and ſeelingly Charming, that he found himſelf inſenſible of any other. <hi>Elſibery</hi> ſaw the Love and Care he had for her, decay inſenſibly; and, although ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to deceive her ſelf; yet ſhe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:53855:63"/>could no longer doubt of her Misfortune, when ſhe was told, That the Prince had taken a Reſolution, to go to Travail over all <hi>Greece.</hi> She learnt it from others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he told her any thing of it: He was now weary of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> and that inſpired him with the Deſigne, which he put in Execution, notwithſtanding all <hi>Elſiberies</hi> Intreaties and Tears.</p>
               <p>The fair Slave ſaw then, that <hi>Elſibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Deſtiny was as Unfortunate as her own; And <hi>Elſibery,</hi> had no other comfort, but what ſhe found in bemoaning her ſelf to <hi>Zebelec;</hi> who had the News of her Husband's Death, for which ſhe was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly agrieved, notwithſtanding his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Infidelity to her: His Death having now taken away the cauſe of her Diſguiſe, ſhe prayed. <hi>Elſiberies</hi> father, to give her that Liberty, which he had ſo often of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd her; having obtained it, ſhe put on a Reſolution, to return to her own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; there to ſpend the reſt of her dayes in ſome Solitude, remote from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of all men. She had often ſpoken to <hi>Elſibery,</hi> of the Chriſtian Religion: This fair Creature being touched with what ſhe had heard her ſay, and with the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of <hi>Alamire,</hi> (for which ſhe hoped for no Redreſſe) reſolves to turn Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53855:64"/>to follow <hi>Zebelec;</hi> and live with her in a profound Oblivion of all earthly Tyes; She went away, without giving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notice to her Parents, only by a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which ſhe left for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> was already got far on his way, when he underſtood by a letter from <hi>Selemin,</hi> what I came from telling you of <hi>Elſibery:</hi> But where ever ſhe be, perhaps ſhe would find ſome Conſolation, could ſhe but know how ſeverely her Quarrel was revenged upon <hi>Alamire,</hi> for his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity to her, by the Violent Paſſion which <hi>Zaydes</hi> Beauty kindled in him.</p>
               <p>He arrived in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and fell in Love with that Princeſs, (as <hi>I</hi> told you) after ballancing ſome time betwixt Her and Me: But, he Loved her with a Paſſion ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from all others he ever Loved, that he ſcarce knew himſelf. Formerly, he would alwayes declare his Love, from the firſt Moment that he felt it; He never was afraid to offend thoſe to whom he declared it: But, to <hi>Zayde,</hi> he ſcarce durſt let her have any inckling of it. He was aſtoniſhed, at this Change in himſelf: But, he being forced by the Violence of his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to declare it to <hi>Zayde;</hi> and, that he found, that the indifference ſhe had for him, did but irritate his Love for her; when he
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53855:64"/>ſaw himſelf brought to Deſpair by her uſage to him, without being able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intangle himſelf from his Paſſion for her; he felt a Grief, that was not to be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>How! (would he ſay to <hi>Mulziman</hi>) Love never had more Power over me, but I was pleaſed to give it; and, though it had entirely Conquer'd me, I alwayes was pleaſed with all Places where I Loved: And now he muſt, through the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World, in whom I found a Reſiſtance, to Domineer over me, with ſo abſolute an Empire, that he has left me no Power to diſ-ingage my ſelf from him. I could not Love all thoſe that Lov'd me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I am compelled to Adore <hi>Zayde,</hi> that deſpiſes me. Is it her extraordinary Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that produces this unuſual Effect? Or, Can it be poſſible, that the only way to fix me, was not to Love me? Ah, <hi>Zayde!</hi> Shall I never be in a Condition to know, that they are not your Rigors that ty me to you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mulziman</hi> could not tell what to ſay to him; ſuch was his Surprize, to ſee him in the Condition he was in: He endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, notwithſtanding, to comfort him, and to eaſe his Pain. Since the Arrival of <hi>Zaydes</hi> Father, and her Declaring never
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:53855:65"/>to Marry that Prince, his Deſpair grew greater, and hurryed him to ſeek his Death any where with Joy.</p>
               <p>This is, as near I can remember, what I learnt from <hi>Mulziman,</hi> continued <hi>Felime;</hi> and perhaps, I have been too exact in my Narrative: But, you muſt pardon thoſe Charms, which thoſe that are in Love, found in the Perſons whom they Love; though it may be, even upon diſagreeable Subjects. Don <hi>Olmond</hi> told the Princeſs: That, far from thinking her ſelf obliged to excuſe the Length of her Narration; That he was bound rather, to return her Thanks, for informing him of <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Adventures: He conjured her, to finiſh what ſhe had begun to tell him: She continued her Diſcourſe after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:</p>
               <p>You may very well judge, that what I learnt of the ſtrange Adventures and Humour of <hi>Alamire,</hi> could give me no great Hope; ſince I was covinced, that the only way to make him Love, was not to love him; notwithſtanding, I did not love him leſs. The Dangers to which he dayly expoſed himſelf, gave me Mortal Apprehenſions for him; I did believe, that every Stroke might fall upon his Head; that he was the only Man, that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:53855:65"/>could be in danger. I was ſo over-whelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with grief, that I thought nothing could be added to it: But, Fortune expoſed me to a kind of Miſery, more cruel than any I had yet felt.</p>
               <p>Some Dayes after <hi>Mulziman</hi> had told me <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Adventures, <hi>I</hi> was ſpeaking of them to <hi>Zayde;</hi> and <hi>I</hi> made ſuch ſad Reflections upon the Cruelty of my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny, that my Face was all bathed in Tears. One of <hi>Zaydes</hi> Women paſs'd thorow the Room where we were, and left the Door open, which <hi>I</hi> not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving: It cannot be denyed, ſaid I to <hi>Zayde,</hi> but that <hi>I</hi> am very Unfortunate, to have ſettled my Affections upon a Man, that is ſo unworthy in all Reſpects, of the Inclination <hi>I</hi> have for him: As <hi>I</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theſe Words, <hi>I</hi> heard ſome Body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me in the Room; I thought, at firſt, it was that Woman, that was going tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row again: But, What a confuſion and trouble was <hi>I</hi> in, when <hi>I</hi> ſaw it was <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire!</hi> and that he was ſo near me, that he could not chooſe but hear my laſt Words? But the Trouble <hi>I</hi> was in, and the Tears that trickled down my Cheeks, took from me all Means of hiding from him the Truth of what <hi>I</hi> had ſaid: My Strength fail'd me; my Speech left me;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:53855:66"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> wiſhed my ſelf Dead: In ſhort, None ever was in ſuch a taking, as <hi>I</hi> felt my ſelf. And, to add to the Cruelty of my Adventure, the Princeſs <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> came in, accompanyed with divers others; who went all to ſpeak to <hi>Zayde,</hi> and left me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone with <hi>Alamire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince looked upon me with an Ayre, that ſhewed the fear he had to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the Confuſion in which he ſaw me. <hi>I</hi> am ſorry, Madam, ſaid he, that <hi>I</hi> came in at a time, when in all appearance, you were not willing to be heard by any but <hi>Zayde:</hi> But, Madam, ſince Chance has ordained it otherwiſe, do not take it ill if <hi>I</hi> ask you, How it can poſſible be, that a Man that has been ſo happy as to pleaſe you, could oblige you to ſay, That he was unworthy in all Reſpects, of the Kindneſs you have for him? <hi>I</hi> know, no Man can deſerve the leaſt of your Favours: But, Can there be any Man, that could give you Cauſe to complain of his Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Be not angry, Madam, that <hi>I</hi> have ſome ſhare in your Confidence; you ſhall not find me unworthy of it; and, though you took care to conceal from me what <hi>I</hi> have heard; yet, <hi>I</hi> ſhall alwayes have a great Value for a Secret, which <hi>I</hi> owe only to Chance.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:53855:66"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> had ſpoke on for a long time, if he had ſtay'd untill <hi>I</hi> had been able to interrupt him: <hi>I</hi> was ſo out of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and ſo daunted with the fear he ſhould find out, that he was the Man of whom <hi>I</hi> complain'd; and with Grief, that he ſhould believe, that <hi>I</hi> loved ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man; that it was utterly impoſſible, for me to anſwer him. You think, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, that having concealed from him the Paſſion <hi>I</hi> had for him, with ſo much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and ſeeing him ſo much in Love with <hi>Zayde; I</hi> ſhould be indifferent, whether or no he imagined, ſome other might have gain'd my Eſteem: But, Love had already put ſo much Conſtraint upon it Self, to hide it from the Perſon that gave it Birth, that it could not be ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el to it ſelf, as to let him think, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother had kindled it. <hi>Alamire</hi> attributed my Perplexity, to my trouble of ſeeing him perſwaded that <hi>I</hi> was in Love. <hi>I</hi> ſee, Madam, ſaid he, that you are unwilling I ſhould be your Confident; but your Concern is unjuſt: Can any Man have more Reſpect for you than my ſelf, or more Intereſt to pleaſe you than I? You have an abſolute Power over that Princeſs, of whom depends my Deſtiny: Tell me then, Madam, Who he is, of whom you
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:53855:67"/>complain? and if I have half as much Power with him, as you have over her I Adore; you ſhall quickly ſee, if I do not make him know his Happineſs, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him worthy of your Goodneſs for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Words increaſed my trouble and agitation of Mind: He urged me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to tell him, who he ſhould be, of whom I complain'd: But, all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that made him deſire to know him, render'd him in my Thoughts, unworthy to be informed. At laſt, <hi>Zayde</hi> judging the Perplexity I was in, came to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt us, before I could have the Power to utter one word to <hi>Alamire.</hi> I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, without ſo much as looking upon him: My Body was not able to bear the Agitation of my Mind: I fell ſick that very Night, and continued ſo a long time.</p>
               <p>Among the Number of Men of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that were then in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> it were hard if ſome did not concern themſelves in the Preſervation of my Life: I was told of their Care, to be informed of the ſtate of my Health: I made Reflections, how littled I was touched with their Kindneſs: And, when I conſider'd, that if <hi>Alamire</hi> had known my Inclination for
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53855:67"/>him, parhaps, it might make as little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon him, as the Paſſion of thoſe that loved me, made upon me. I thought my ſelf happy, that he was ignorant of my Love for Him; But, I muſt confeſs, this Happineſs was only pleaſing to my Reaſon, and no way grateful to my Heart. When I began to Recover, I put off as long as I could, all occaſions of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Alamire;</hi> and when I came to be ſeen by him, I took notice, that he obſerved me with great Care, to find out by my Actions, who it was, of whom I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd; the more I found him diligent, in prying into my Deportment, the worſe I handled all thoſe, that ſhewed any incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for me; though there were many, of whoſe Merit and Quallitys, I needed not be aſhamed; yet, there was none of them, that did not blemiſh my Honour; For, I could not indure, he ſhould think, that I lov'd without being belov'd Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procally; and, this very Thought made me Fancy, that I ſeem'd to him, to be leſs Worthy of him therefore.</p>
               <p>The Emperors Troops plyed <hi>Famagoſta</hi> ſo warmly, that the <hi>Arabians</hi> thought it their beſt way to deſert it. <hi>Zulema</hi> and <hi>Oſmin</hi> reſolv'd to embark us with the Princeſs <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> and <hi>Belleny: Alamire</hi> alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:53855:68"/>to leave <hi>Cyprus</hi> to follow <hi>Zayde,</hi> and quit a place where his Valour could be no longer uſeful. He had ſtill a great Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, to find out who it was that I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of: When we were ready to part, and ſaw that my Sadneſs did not increaſe; How, ſaid he! Can you leave <hi>Cyprus</hi> without ſhewing new Marks of Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? It is impoſſible, Madam, but you moſt ſenſibly feel this Departure: Do me the Favor to let me know, Who it is that you are concerned for? There is not a Man in all this place, but I can prevail with, to go into <hi>Africk;</hi> and, you ſhall have the Pleaſure to ſee him there, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his leaſt Suſpition, that you deſir'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch thing: I have no mind, ſaid I to trouble my ſelf, to diſpoſſeſs you of an Opinion, which you conceived upon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances that ſeem'd to be true; Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, I muſt tell you, that thoſe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences are falſe, I leave none in <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> For whom I have any extraordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern: And yet, it is not for any Change my Heart has made. I underſtand you, Madam, the Man that had the good Luck to pleaſe you is not here: I looked for him in vain, amongſt the Number of your Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; and, I believe he was gon from <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus,</hi> before I had the Honor to ſee you.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:53855:68"/>It is neither before you ſaw me, nor ſince your coming hither, that any has been ſo happy as to pleaſe me, ſaid I to him, very abruptly; and I pray you, not to ſpeak to me any more, of a thing that diſpleaſes me ſo much.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> ſeeing that I was Angry, would ſay no more to me, and aſſured me, he would never trouble me any more upon this Subject; <hi>I</hi> was glad to end a Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, in which, <hi>I</hi> was always in danger of diſcovering, what <hi>I</hi> ſo earneſtly deſired to conceal. In fine, we went abroad, and our Voyage was at firſt ſo pleaſant, that we had no reaſon to fear ſuch an unfortunate Ship-Wrack, as we ſuffer'd upon the Coaſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> as I ſhall inform you A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Felime</hi> was going to continue her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, when a ſervant came to tell her that her Mother grew worſe. Though I had many other things to tell you, ſaid ſhe to Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> as ſhe was going to leave him, I have told you enough, to let you know, that my Life depends upon that of <hi>Alamire,</hi> and likewiſe, to engage you to keep your Word with me. Madam, I will moſt exactly perform my Promiſe; But <hi>I</hi> pray you to remember alſo, that you muſt inform me of the reſt of your Adventures.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:53855:69"/>
               <p>The next Day he went to the King; who no ſooner perceived him, but he preſently would have <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> put out of the impatience, and the diſquiet which appeared in his Countenance: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, leading them both into his Cloſet, and commanding, Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> to tell him, whether he had ſeen <hi>Felime;</hi> or learnt from her, what intereſt ſhe took in the Preſervation of <hi>Alamire.</hi> Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> without ſeeming to Dive into the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Why the King, ſhould be ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to know the Adventures of that Prince; he gave an exact Account, of all that he had learnt from <hi>Felime,</hi> of her Paſſion for <hi>Alamire,</hi> of <hi>Alamires</hi> for <hi>Zayde;</hi> and, of all that happen'd to them, until their departure from <hi>Cyprus.</hi> Having made an end, he judged, that the King, and <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> could not be ſo free in their Diſcourſe, as they would be if he were not there; and, to leave them at Liberty, he ſaid, for excuſe, that he was Oblig'd to return to <hi>Orepeſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So ſoon as he was gon, the King look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his Favorite, with an Ayre that ſhew'd the kindneſs he had for him, ſaid to him, Do you yet believe, that <hi>Alamire</hi> is beloved of <hi>Zayde?</hi> Do you believe it was ſhe, that made <hi>Felime</hi> Write? Do
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:53855:69"/>not you ſee, how ill your Apprehentions are grounded? No Sir, (replied gravely, Don <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi>) all that Don <hi>Olmond</hi> has ſaid, cannot perſwade me yet, but that I have cauſe to fear; Perhaps, <hi>Zayde</hi> was not, at firſt, in Love with <hi>Alamire;</hi> or, that ſhe concealed it from <hi>Felime,</hi> ſeeing the Paſſion ſhe had for that Prince; but whom do you believe ſhe lamented, when ſhe was Shipwrack'd upon the Coaſt of <hi>Spain</hi> but <hi>Alamire,</hi> whom ſhe believed Dead? Whom can I reſemble but that Prince? <hi>Felime</hi> ſpoke only of him in her Relation; <hi>Zayde,</hi> has deceived her, my Lord, or elſe, ſhe has owned to her the inclination ſhe had for him: But ſince there being at <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s Houſe, all that I have heard, does not deſtroy the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I had; and, I fear much, that, what remaines yet untold, will rather confirm, than deſtroy them. It was ſo late when <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> left the King, that he ſhould have thought of nothing elſe, but of taking his Reſt: But, his diſquiet of Mind would not give him leave to take any. <hi>Felimes</hi> Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion augmented his Curioſity, and left him ſtill in that cruel uncertainty, in which he had been ſo long. In the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, one of the Officers of the Army, that came back from <hi>Oropeſe,</hi> brought him
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:53855:70"/>a Note from Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> wherein he Read theſe Words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Don <hi>Olmonds</hi> Letter to <hi>GONSAL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>O.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FElime <hi>has kept her Word with me, and told me, the reſt of her Adventures. The Love ſhe bears to</hi> Alamire, <hi>is the only Cauſe of her Concern for his Life:</hi> Zayde, <hi>has no Intereſt in it; and, if any Man ſhould have hard Thoughts of</hi> Zayde, <hi>it is not of</hi> Alamire, <hi>he muſt be Jealous.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Note put <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> into a new trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and made him think, that he was only deceaved in believing, that <hi>Alamire</hi> was the Man ſhe loved; But, that he could not be deceived in his belief, that <hi>Zayde</hi> was in Love. The Letter he ſaw her Write at <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s Houſe, what he had heard her ſay at <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> of a firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, and the Note he Received from Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> would not let him doubt of it. He thought he muſt be ſtill unhappy, ſince <hi>Zaydes</hi> Heart, was firmly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; Nevertheleſs, without knowing why, he felt ſome eaſe, by the aſſurance he had,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:53855:70"/>that her Paſſion was not for the Prince of <hi>Tharſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean while, the <hi>Mores</hi> made Overtures of Peace, which were ſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious, that it was not thought Prudence to reject them; Plenipotentiaries were named on both ſides to Regulate Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and a new Ceſſation was agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was Privy to all the Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Yet, as buſied as he was by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of thoſe Affairs, which the King intruſted him with, he was much more impatient to know who this Rival ſhould be, of whom, he never heard before. He expected Don <hi>Olmond</hi> with ſo much impatience, that he could take no Reſt: At laſt, he beſeeched the King, either to ſend for him to the Camp; or, to give him leave to go to <hi>Orepeſe;</hi> Don <hi>Garcias,</hi> who whas as curious to hear the ſequel of <hi>Zaydes</hi> Adventures, reſolv'd to be by at Don <hi>Olmonds</hi> telling them; he ſent for him with all ſpeed. When <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſaw him coming, and looking upon him, as the Man that was to relate to him, the true Sentiments of <hi>Zayde,</hi> he was almoſt ready to ſtop his mouth; he ſo much fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to hear the truth of his misfortune, though at the ſame time, he earneſtly wiſhed to know it. Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> with
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:53855:71"/>his accuſtomed diſcretion, without ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to perceive <hi>Gonſalvos</hi> trouble, begun to tell what he had received from <hi>Felime,</hi> in their laſt Converſation. The King ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Commanded him to ſpeak</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sequel of the Hiſtory of <hi>FELIME</hi> and <hi>ZAYDE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Princes, <hi>Zulema</hi> and <hi>Oſmin,</hi> left <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus,</hi> with an intention to paſs into <hi>Africk,</hi> and to land at <hi>Tunis: Alamire</hi> went along with them; and their Voyage was Proſperous enough, untill a contrary Wind drove them towards <hi>Alexandria.</hi> When <hi>Zulema</hi> ſaw himſelf ſo near that Place, he had a mind to go a Shore, to viſit <hi>Albumazar,</hi> (the moſt famous Aſtrologer of all <hi>Africk</hi>) his old Acquaintance. The Princeſſes (who were not uſed to the Hardſhips of the Sea), were glad to go a Shore, to reſt themſelves; and the Winds continued in a contrary Point; ſo that, they could not put to Sea again ſo ſoon as they expected.</p>
               <p>One Day, as <hi>Zulema</hi> was ſhewing to <hi>Albumazar</hi> divers Rarities which he had brought from his Travails, <hi>Zayde</hi> eſpyed in a Box which he open'd, the Picture of a
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:53855:71"/>Young Man, of an extraordinary Beauty, and a moſt agreeable Phyſiognomy; the Dreſs (that was like to that which is uſed by the Princes of <hi>Arabia</hi>) made her imagine, that it might be the Picture of one of the <hi>Caliph</hi>'s Sons: She asked her Father, Whether it was not ſo as ſhe thought? He told her, He knew not for whom that Picture was drawn; that he bought it of a Soldier, and kept it for the Excellency of the Work: <hi>Zayde</hi> ſeemed taken with the Beauty of that Picture: <hi>Albumazar</hi> took notice of her Attention, in conſidering it; He joked with her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; and told her, That he perceived, that a Man that ſhould reſemble this Picture, might hope to pleaſe her.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Grecians</hi> have naturally a great opinion of Aſtrology, and young People are very curious to know what is to come; ſo, <hi>Zayde</hi> preſſed this famous Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger, to tell her ſomething of her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny: But he ſtill excuſed himſelf. He paſſed all that little time which he could ſpare from his Studies, in <hi>Zulema</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and ſeemed to avoid all occaſions, of ſhewing his extraordinary Skill. At laſt, one Day finding him in her Father's Chamber, ſhe urged him more than ever, to conſult the Stars about her Fortune.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:53855:72"/>I need not conſult the Stars for that, ſaid he, Madam; for, I can aſſure you, that you are Deſtin'd for the Man, whoſe Picture <hi>Zulema</hi> ſhewed you. Very few Princes in <hi>Africk</hi> are equal to him: You ſhall be Happy if you Marry him: Have a care, you do not Engage your Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any other. <hi>Zayde</hi> received this Anſwer, as a kind of Rallery, for her too much Attention in viewing the Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: But <hi>Zulema</hi> told her, with all the Authority of a Father, That ſhe muſt no wayes doubt of the Truth of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; That he gave ſo full a Credit to it himſelf, that he ſhould never conſent ſhe ſhould Marry any other, but the Man for whom this Picture was drawn.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zayde</hi> and <hi>Felime</hi> could not believe, that <hi>Zulema</hi> ſpoke what he truly thought; but when he declared, that he had no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention now, that the Princeſs (his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) ſhould marry the Prince of <hi>Tharſus:</hi> They no wayes doubted of the Truth of what <hi>Albumazar</hi> had ſaid. <hi>Felime</hi> was not a little tranſported with Joy, when ſhe knew that <hi>Zayde</hi> was no longer deſtin'd for <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire.</hi> She fancied a great pleaſure to tell him of it: She flatter'd her ſelf with the hope, that he would return to her, when he ſhould have no further expectation,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:53855:72"/>that <hi>Zayde</hi> would be his. She begg'd leave of this fair Princeſs, to acquaint <hi>Alamire</hi> with <hi>Albumazars</hi> Prediction, and <hi>Zulema's</hi> intention; this leave was ſoon granted, <hi>Zayde</hi> eaſily conſented to all, that might Cure the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> of the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he had for her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Felime,</hi> found an occaſion to ſpeak to the Prince, and without making any ſhew, of the Pleaſure ſhe took, in telling it to him, ſhe adviſed him to break off with <hi>Zayde;</hi> ſince ſhe was deſign'd for another, and that <hi>Zulema</hi> was no longer favorable to him; ſhe, moreover told him, how <hi>Zule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> came to change his Mind, and, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him the Picture, which was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide <hi>Zaydes</hi> deſigne. <hi>Alamire</hi> appeared overwhelmed with Grief, at the words of <hi>Felime,</hi> and ſurpriſed, with the Beauty of the Picture, ſhe ſhewed him; he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a good while ſilent; at laſt, lifting up his Eyes, with an Ayre which ſhewed his Grief; <hi>I</hi> believe it, Madam, ſaid he, that Man, whoſe Picture <hi>I</hi> ſee, is deſign'd for <hi>Zayde;</hi> his Beauty deſerves her; But, he ſhall never have her; For, I will Kill him, before he ſhall be able to pretend to Rob me of <hi>Zayde:</hi> But, replied <hi>Felime,</hi> if you undertake to fight with every Man, that may be like this Picture, You muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:53855:73"/>a great number of men, before you find out him, for whom it was drawn. I am not happy enough, anſwer'd <hi>Alamire,</hi> to be in danger of ſuch a miſtake. This Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture repreſents ſo great, and ſo particular a Beauty, that very few can be like it. But, Madam added he, this Phyſiognc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as agreeable and as pleaſing as it appears, may hide ſuch unpleaſing Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and a temper of mind ſo different, from what ought to pleaſe <hi>Zayde,</hi> that as Beautifull, as this pretended Rivall may be, perhaps he may not be beloved of her: And, as favourable and kind as Fortune and <hi>Zulema</hi> may be to him, if he does not Captivate <hi>Zaydes</hi> inclinations, I ſhall not think my ſelf altogether unhappy; I ſhall be leſſe troubled to ſee her in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a man that ſhe cannot love, then to ſee her in love with a man that ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſeſſe. Nevertheleſs Madam, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, although this Picture has made ſuch an impreſſion in my mind, that cannot eaſily be blotted out, I conjure you to leave it with me for ſome time, that I may conſider it at leiſure, and that I may imprint the <hi>Idea</hi> thereof more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in my Memory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Felime</hi> was ſo much Concerned to ſee that, what ſhe had ſaid, would not abate
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:53855:73"/>of <hi>Alamire</hi>'s hopes, that ſhe let him carry away the Picture: Which he return'd to her ſome dayes after, in ſpight of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire he had, to hide it for ever from the eyes of <hi>Zayde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After ſome ſtay at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the winds were favourable, for their departure; <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire</hi> received Letters from his Father that obliged him to leave <hi>Zayde,</hi> to return to <hi>Tharſus:</hi> But knowing that he ſhould not need to ſtay long there, told <hi>Zulema,</hi> that he ſhould be as ſoon at <hi>Tunis</hi> as he. <hi>Felime</hi> was as much afflicted at their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, as if ſhe had been really beloved by him: She was uſed to all the afflictions which love cauſes, but ſhe had not been yet acquainted, with that which abſence gives: And ſhe felt it ſo ſenſibly, that ſhe found, that it was the pleaſure alone, of ſeeing him ſhe loved, that gave her ſtrength to ſupport the Misfortune of not being beloved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alamire</hi> parted for <hi>Tharſus;</hi> and <hi>Zulema</hi> and <hi>Oſmin,</hi> in different Ships, ſailed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Tunis: Zayde</hi> and <hi>Felime</hi> would not be parted, but ſtaid together in <hi>Zulema</hi>'s Ship. After ſome Dayes Navigation, a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Storm roſe, which diſperſed the Fleet: That Ship in which <hi>Zayde</hi> was, ſpent her main Maſt: At which, <hi>Zulema</hi> loſing all
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:53855:74"/>Hope of Safety in ſtaying in the Ship, and knowing that he was not far off the Land, reſolved to ſave himſelf in the long Boat: He cauſed his Wife, his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and <hi>Felime,</hi> to go into the Boat; and took with him all that he had of Value: But, as he was going to ſtep into the Boat, a Wave broke the Rope that faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it to the Ship, and carryed it with that Violence, that it ſtaved in againſt the Beach. <hi>Zayde</hi> was caſt upon the Shore of <hi>Catalonia</hi> half Dead; and <hi>Febime,</hi> who had got hold of a Planck, was driven in there too, after ſhe had ſeen the Princeſs <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> drowned. When <hi>Zayde</hi> was come to her ſelf, ſhe was in a maze, to find her ſelf among People that ſhe did not know, and whoſe Language ſhe could not underſtand.</p>
               <p>Two <hi>Spaniards</hi> that were walking upon the Beach, found her in a Trance, and cauſed her to be carryed to their Houſe; Some Fiſher-men led <hi>Felime</hi> thither too: <hi>Zayde</hi> was over-joyed to ſee her; but was more afflicted, to hear of the Death of the Princeſs, her Mother: Having ſhed many Tears for this Loſs, ſhe bent her Thoughts how to get out of that Place: She made Signes, that ſhe deſired to go
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:53855:74"/>to <hi>Tunis,</hi> where ſhe hoped to find <hi>Oſmin</hi> and <hi>Belleny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Looking earneſtly upon the Youngeſt of thoſe two <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whoſe Name was <hi>Theodorick,</hi> ſhe perceived, he very much reſembled the Picture, with which ſhe had been ſo taken: This Reſemblance ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized her, and made her look upon him with more Attention. She went along the Beach, to ſearch for a Box, in which this Picture was; which, ſhe believed, was put into the Boat, when ſhe came off from the Ship, She ſought in vain; and ſhe was extreamly vexed, that ſhe could not find what ſhe looked for. She perceived, for ſome Dayes, that <hi>Theodorick</hi> had a Paſſion for her, though ſhe could not underſtand it by his Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; yet his Carriage, and his Actions, made her ſuſpect it; Nor was that Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion diſagreeable to her.</p>
               <p>Some time after, ſhe thought her ſelf miſtaken: She ſaw him very Melancholly, without any Cauſe from her: She ſaw, that he often left her to go alone, to Dream and Think. In fine, She believed, he was ingaged in Affection to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which made him uncaſie, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Mind. This Imagination gave her a ſurprizing Diſquiet, and made her as
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:53855:75"/>Melancholly, as <hi>Theodorick</hi> ſeemed to her. Although <hi>Felime</hi> was taken up with her own Thoughts; yet ſhe was too well acquainted with Love, not to perceive the Paſſion which <hi>Theodorick</hi> had for <hi>Zayde,</hi> and the Inclination <hi>Zayde</hi> had for <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick:</hi> She hinted it to her divers times; and, notwithſtanding the Reluctancy this fair Princeſs found in her, to own it to her ſelf; yet, ſhe could not forbear own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to <hi>Felime.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, ſaid ſhe, I have an Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for <hi>Theodorick;</hi> of which I am not Miſtriſs: But, I pray you <hi>Felime,</hi> Is it not of him, that <hi>Albumazar</hi> ſpoke? And was not that Picture (think you) which we ſaw, drawn for him? There is no like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood of it, anſwered <hi>Felime;</hi> The For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and Country of <hi>Theodorick,</hi> has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that can relate to what <hi>Albumazar</hi> ſaid. Conſider, Madam, that having no wayes credited that Prediction, you now begin to believe it, by imagining, that <hi>Theodorick</hi> may be the Man that is deſtin'd for you; and judge from thence, what are your Thoughts for him. Hitherto, reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Zayde,</hi> I did not believe the Words of <hi>Albumazar,</hi> to be a true Prediction: But, I muſt confeſs, that ſince I ſaw <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> they began to make an Impreſſion
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:53855:75"/>upon my Fancy. I thought it ſomething Extraordinary, to have found a Man that reſembled that Picture; and, at the ſame time, to feel an Inclination for him. I am ſurprized, when I think of <hi>Albumazar</hi>'s forbidding me to ſuffer my Heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any Impreſſion: He ſeems to me, to have fore-ſeen the Inclination I have for <hi>Theodorick:</hi> And, his Perſon is ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to me, that if I am deſign'd for a Man that reſembles him, what ſhould make me Happy, is like to make my Life uncomfortable. My Inclination is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with this Reſemblance, and hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries me to him, to whom I ought not to belong; and, perhaps, prepoſſeſſes me ſo ſtrangely, that <hi>I</hi> ſhall not be able to Love him, whom the Deſtinies have ordained I ſhould Love. There is no other Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, continued <hi>Zayde,</hi> but to leave a Place where I run ſuch hazard, and where De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency it ſelf, forbids we ſhould continue any longer. It is not in our Power, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Felime,</hi> to leave it: We are in a ſtrange Country, even where our Language is not underſtood. We muſt ſtay for the Ships: But take notice, that what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Care you ſeem to take, to leave <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorick,</hi> you will not eaſily be able to blot out the Impreſſion he has made upon
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:53855:76"/>your Heart. I perceive in you, the ſame things I felt, when <hi>I</hi> began to love <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire;</hi> and would to the Gods, I could ſee in him, what you cannot but ſee in <hi>Theodorick.</hi> You are miſtaken, ſaid ſhe, if you think that <hi>Theodorick</hi> has any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination for me; he has, doubtleſs, for ſome other Perſon: And the Sadneſs I perceive him in, proceeds from a Paſſion, of which I am not the Cauſe. I have, at leaſt, this Conſolation in my Misfortune; that the Impoſſibility of expreſſing my Thoughts to him, will hinder me from the Weakneſs of declaring to him that <hi>I</hi> love him.</p>
               <p>A few Dayes after this Converſation, <hi>Zayde</hi> ſaw <hi>Theodorick</hi> at a diſtance; look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with great Attention, upon ſome thing, which he held betwixt both his Hands; Her Jealouſie made her fancy, that it was a Picture: She reſolves to find out the Truth, and ſteals towards him as ſoftly as ſhe could; but ſhe could not do it ſo gently, but that he heard her: He turned his Head, and hid what he had in his Hands, ſo that ſhe could ſee nothing but the Luſtre of ſome Diamonds: She no longer doubted, but that it was a Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Caſe, as ſhe had imagined; the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance ſhe believed, ſhe had of it, ſtruck
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:53855:76"/>her with ſuch a Grief, that ſhe could not hide her Sadneſs, nor look upon <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick;</hi> And ſhe felt ſuch anguiſh of mind, to be ſo paſſionately ſmitten with a Man, whom ſhe believed in Love with another. <hi>Theodorick,</hi> by chance, let fall what he hid; ſhe ſaw it was a Knot of Diamonds, which held to a Bracelet of her Hair, which ſhe had loſt ſome Dayes before: The Joy ſhe was in, that ſhe had been miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, would not let her ſhew any Anger. She ſnatch'd up her Bracelet, and return'd the Diamonds to <hi>Theodorick;</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently threw them into the Sea, to let her ſee how much he deſpiſed them, when they were ſeparated from her Hair: This Action convinced <hi>Zayde</hi> of the Love and Magnificence of that <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and did no ſmall Feats in her Heart.</p>
               <p>After this, he gave her to underſtand, by the help of a Picture (where he made the Painter to draw a Beautiful Lady, weeping over a Dead Man), that the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity ſhe ſhewed him, proceeded from the Tyes ſhe had for that Man, whom ſhe lamented. It was no ſmall Grief to <hi>Zayde,</hi> to find, that <hi>Theodorick</hi> believed, that ſhe loved another: She was now no longer in doubt of his Love for her; and ſhe loved him with ſo much Tenderneſs, that ſhe no
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:53855:77"/>longer endeavoured to ſmother it.</p>
               <p>The time in which ſhe was to depart, drew on; and not being able to reſolve upon her Departure, without letting him know, that ſhe loved him; ſhe told <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime,</hi> That ſhe was reſolved to write to him the Inclination ſhe had in her Heart for him; but not to give it him, until the very moment ſhe was to Embark. He ſhall not know the Paſſion I had for him, until I am ſure, I am out of danger of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeeing him more: It will be a great Comfort to me, that he ſhall know, that <hi>I</hi> thought of no other but himſelf; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, he believed, <hi>I</hi> was wholly taken up with the Remembrance of another Man. <hi>I</hi> ſhall find a great Pleaſure, in expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all my Actions to him; and in give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf the Freedom of telling him, how much <hi>I</hi> loved him: I ſhall have this Delight, without breach of Modeſty. He knows not who I am: He ſhall never ſee me more: And, what matter is't, if he knows that he touched the Heart of that Stranger, whoſe Life he has ſaved from Shipwrack. You have forgot, Madam, ſaid <hi>Felime</hi> to her, that <hi>Theodorick</hi> does not underſtand your Language; So that, what you will write to him, will be of no uſe to him. Ah, Madam! If he has
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:53855:77"/>any kindneſs for me, he will find means to be informed of what I ſhall have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to him; and if he has not, I ſhall be glad that he does not know, that I love him: And, I am reſolv'd to leave him with my Letter, the Bracelet of my Hair, which I ſo cruelly took from him, and which he deſerved but too well.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zayde</hi> began the very next Day, to write what ſhe intended to leave to <hi>Theodorick:</hi> He ſurprized her, as ſhe was Writing: and ſhe eaſily found, that he was Jealous at it. If ſhe had followed the Impulſe of her Heart, ſhe had then told him, That ſhe writ to none but him: But her Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the little Knowledge ſhe had of the Quality or Fortune of this Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, kept her from ſaying any thing, that might be taken for an Engagement; and made her conceal, what ſhe deſired he might know, when he ſhould ſee her no more.</p>
               <p>Some ſhort time before ſhe was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, <hi>Theodorick</hi> left her; and made her comprehend, that he would be back the next Day. The Day following, ſhe and <hi>Felime</hi> went to walk upon the Beach, not without Impatience to ſee <hi>Theodorick</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; and this Impatience made her more Penſive than uſual: So that, ſeeing a Boat
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:53855:78"/>put in to the Shore, inſtead of being Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to ſee thoſe that were in it, ſhe walked another way: But, ſhe was much ſurprized, to hear her ſelf call'd, and to diſtinguiſh her Father's Voyce: She ran to him with great Joy; and he was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported to ſee her again. After ſhe had acquainted him how ſhe eſcaped from Shipwrack, he told her in few words, That his Ship was driven upon the Coaſt of <hi>France;</hi> from whence he could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, till ſome few Dayes before, and that he was come to <hi>Tarragone,</hi> to wait for the Ships that were to ſail for <hi>Africk:</hi> That in the mean-time, he reſolved to Row a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Coaſt, where <hi>Alaſinthe, Felime,</hi> and ſhe had ſuffer'd Shipwrack; to find, if any of them had chanced to eſcape<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> At the Name of <hi>Alaſinthe, Zayde</hi> could not contain her Tears; by which, <hi>Zulema</hi> underſtood the Loſs he had received: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beſtowed ſome time upon his Grief, he commanded the Young Princeſſes to go into the Boat, to ſail along with him to <hi>Tarragone. Zayde</hi> was in great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, how to perſwade her Father, not to carry her away juſt then: She told him the Obligations ſhe had to thoſe <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who had received her into their Houſe; thereby, thinking to induce him
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:53855:78"/>to let her go to take her Leave of them: But, all ſhe could alleadge, would not perſwade him to truſt her any more into the Hands of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> He made her Embarque, in ſpight of all ſhe could ſay to the contrary. She was ſo ſenſible of the Opinion <hi>Theodorick</hi> might conceive of her Ingratitude; or rather, that ſhe was going to leave him, without all Hopes of ever ſeeing him any more; that, not being able to maſter her Grief, ſhe was forced to ſay, She was ſick. The ſole Conſolation ſhe could find in her Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was to ſee, that her Father had ſaved the Picture, with which ſhe had been ſo well pleaſed; and which now, was become that of her Lover.</p>
               <p>But, this Conſolation was not ſtrong enough to help her to ſupport <hi>Theodoricks</hi> abſence: She was not able to reſiſt it: She fell dangerouſly ill: And <hi>Zulema</hi> was a long time in fear of Loſing ſo every way accompliſh'd a Creature, in the Prime, and Flower of her Youth and Beauty. At laſt there were viſible Hopes of her recovery: But ſhe was yet ſo weak that ſhe could not brook the fatigue of the Sea. Her whole employ was to learn the Spaniſh Language, and having interpreters, and converſing with none
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:53855:79"/>but <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſhe eaſily learnt it during that time which ſhe paſſed in <hi>Catalonia:</hi> She made <hi>Felime</hi> learn it likewiſe, and ſhe found ſome pleaſure in ſpeaking no other Language, but <hi>Spaniſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time, the great Ships were parted from <hi>Taragone,</hi> for <hi>Affrick;</hi> and though <hi>Zulema,</hi> did not know what was become of <hi>Oſmin,</hi> after they had been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated by the ſtorm, yet he writ to him, to let him know how he was Shipwrack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the reaſon that obliged him to ſtay in <hi>Catalonia.</hi> Thoſe Veſſels returned from <hi>Affrick</hi> before <hi>Zayde</hi> was recovered of her Sickneſs: <hi>Oſmin</hi> writ to the Prince his brother, that he Arrived ſafe: And that he found, the <hi>Calipe</hi> in the mind to keep them ſtill at a diſtance: And that King <hi>Abderame,</hi> having ſent to him for Generals, to command his Armies, he deſigned they ſhould paſſe into <hi>Spain,</hi> and that, for that purpoſe he had ſent him the orders. <hi>Zule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> knew well it was not ſafe to diſobey the <hi>Calipe:</hi> He reſolves therefore to take a brigantine, to go by Sea to <hi>Valentia,</hi> to joyn with the King of <hi>Cordova,</hi> and ſo ſoon as the Princeſs his Daughter, was in a condition to Travel, he had her Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Tortoſa:</hi> Where he remained ſome dayes to give her ſome reſt: But ſhe was
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:53855:79"/>far from finding any: For, during the time of her ſickneſs, and ſince ſhe began to recover, the deſire ſhe had to let <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorick</hi> hear from her, and the difficulty of doing it, put her into a Cruel diſquiet of mind: She could not be ſatisfied in her thoughts, becauſe ſhe had the Letter, which ſhe intended to leave him, about her that day her father carried her away. She was extreamly vext, that ſhe had not left it ſomewhere, where he might light upon it. In fine, the night before ſhe parted from <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> ſhe ſent one of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Gentlemen with the Letter, with Directions where he ſhould find <hi>Theodorick</hi> near <hi>Tarragone:</hi> She commanded him not to tell who ſent him, and to have a care that he ſhould not be dogg'd as he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor known who he was. Though ſhe never hoped to ſee <hi>Theodorick,</hi> yet her grief was renewed, by leaving a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try wherein he lived: She paſſed ſome part of the night, making her moan to <hi>Felime,</hi> in thoſe pleaſant Gardens belonging to the houſe where ſhe lodged.</p>
               <p>The next morning, that Gentleman whom ſhe ſent, came back, and told her, that he had been at the place whether ſhe directed him: but that he had bin informed that <hi>Theodorick,</hi> was gone from thence that
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:53855:80"/>day before, with deſign to return nomor to that place. <hi>Zayde</hi> was ſenſibly vexed at this unlucky Chance, which deprived her of the only Conſolation ſhe ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And rob'd her Lover of the onely favour ſhe ever intended him: She em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked with a heavy heart, and Landed in few dayes at <hi>Cordova. Oſmin</hi> and <hi>Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> ſtaid there for them: The Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> was there likewiſe, who hearing at <hi>Tunis</hi> that ſhe was in <hi>Spain,</hi> under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of thoſe Warrs, came thither to find her out. <hi>Felime</hi> at the ſight of <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> did not find that abſence had cured her, of the paſſion ſhe had for him: <hi>Alamire</hi> found nothing but an Augmentation of, the rigors of <hi>Zayde:</hi> And <hi>Zayde</hi> an increaſe of her Averſion for <hi>Alamire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Cordova,</hi> gave the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral command of his Army to <hi>Zulema,</hi> with the Government of <hi>Talevera,</hi> and that of <hi>Oropeſe</hi> to <hi>Oſmin:</hi> Theſe two Princes a little while after, had ſome cauſes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt given them by <hi>Abdrame,</hi> but being unwilling to publiſh their anger, they withdrew themſelves to their Governments pretending to viſit the Fortifications, and to give the neceſſary Orders for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of thoſe places. <hi>Alamire</hi> followed <hi>Zulema,</hi> that he might be near <hi>Zayde:</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:53855:80"/>But a little while after, the Armies going to Action, he was forced to go to joyn with <hi>Abderame.</hi> I parted about that time to find out <hi>Gonſalvo. I</hi> was taken priſoner by the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and carried to <hi>Talevera: Belleny,</hi> and <hi>Felime</hi> went to <hi>Oropeſe,</hi> but <hi>Zayde</hi> remained with the Prince her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. After <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> had taken <hi>Talevera,</hi> and a truce was propoſed, <hi>Alamire</hi> ſent word to <hi>Zulema,</hi> that he would lay hold upon the freedom of this Ceſſation to wait upon him, and that he would take <hi>Oropeſe</hi> in his way; <hi>Zayde</hi> being informed of what <hi>I</hi> told you by her father, writ to <hi>Felime</hi> to let her know, that ſhe had found her <hi>Theodorick</hi> again, and that, ſhe was unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſhould imagine that it was the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> whom ſhe lamented at <hi>Alphonſoes</hi> houſe: and therefore prayed her to forbid him to come to <hi>Talevera.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Felime</hi> found no difficulty to deliver this Meſſage to <hi>Alamire.</hi> The next day <hi>Belleni</hi> finding her ſelf indiſpoſed with the cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the place, took the advantage of the Ceſſation, and went out of the town to take the Ayr, in a great Wood that was near the City: as ſhe was walking with <hi>Oſmin</hi> and <hi>Pelime,</hi> they eſpied the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> coming towards them, whom they received with Joy: And after they
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:53855:81"/>had diſcourſed together a good while, <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime</hi> had opportunity to entertain <hi>Alamire</hi> in private.</p>
               <p>I am ſorry, I muſt tell you a thing that will hinder you from going on the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney you intended: For, <hi>Zayde</hi> prays you not to go to <hi>Talavera,</hi> and ſhe intreats it after a manner, that may paſs for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. By what Exceſs of Cruelty, Madam, cryed <hi>Alamire,</hi> would <hi>Zayde</hi> Rob me of the only Comfort her ſeverity has left me, which is to ſee her? I believe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Felime,</hi> ſhe intends to put an end to the Paſſion you profeſs to have for her; you know the averſion ſhe has to be Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to a Man of your perſwaſion: You likewiſe know, that ſhe has reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that you are not the Man that is deſtin'd for her; and know moreover, that <hi>Zulema</hi> has changed his Reſolution. All theſe Obſtacles, replied <hi>Alamire,</hi> ſhall never make me change, nor the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Zaydes</hi> unkindneſs; and in deſpite of the Fates, and the manner ſhe uſes me, I will never let fall my hopes of being beloved. <hi>Felime</hi> more than uſually Netled at the Obſtinacy of <hi>Alamires</hi> Paſſion, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him a good while, upon the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ought to draw him from his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit: But ſeeing all her Arguments were
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:53855:81"/>in vain, Rage did ſo inflame her, that, ceaſing for the firſt time to be Miſtreſs of her ſelf, ſhe told him; That if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Heaven, and the unkindneſs of <hi>Zayd,</hi> would not make him loſe his hopes, ſhe knew not what would. Nothing, anſwered <hi>Alamire,</hi> but to ſee that another Man has won her Heart; then you muſt lay by all your hopes, replied <hi>Felime:</hi> for <hi>Zayde</hi> has met with a Man, that has found the way to pleaſe her, and by whom ſhe's Adored &amp; Beloved. Alas! who is that happy Man, cryed <hi>Alamire?</hi> A <hi>Spaniard,</hi> ſaid <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime,</hi> that reſembles the Picture you have ſeen; in all likelihood it is not he, for whom that Picture was Drawn, nor whom <hi>Albumazar</hi> meant: But as you fear none but him, that may pleaſe <hi>Zayde,</hi> let it ſuffice you, to know, that ſhe loves him, and that it is her fear of diſpleaſing him, that makes her not to conſent to ſee you. What you ſay cannot poſſible be, replied <hi>Alamire, Zayd's</hi> Heart is not ſo eaſily Conquered, if it had been ſo, you would not tell it me, nor would <hi>Zayde</hi> give you leave to reveal ſuch a Secret: nor have you any Reaſon that may induce you to tel me of it. I have too many, replied ſhe, tranſported as ſhe was with her Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and you — She was going to
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:53855:82"/>continue, but of a ſuddain ſhe recover'd her Reaſon: She was out of Countenance at what ſhe had ſaid: ſhe was troubled, and was ſenſible of her Error: this ſame increaſed her Surpriſe. She remain'd a while without ſpeaking, and as it were beſides her ſelf; at laſt, caſting her looks upon <hi>Alamire,</hi> and believing ſhe ſaw ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his looks, that diſcover'd ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Truth, ſhe put a conſtraint upon her ſelf, and reaſſuming a Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, wherein appeared, more of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, than ſhe had in her mind. You have reaſon, ſaid ſhe to believe, that if <hi>Zayde</hi> were in love with any body, I ſhould not acquaint you with it; I had only a mind to make you apprehend ſuch a thing. It is true, that we have met with a <hi>Spaniard</hi> that is in love with <hi>Zayde,</hi> and reſembles that Picture which you ſaw: But you have made me perceive, that I have perhaps, committed an Error, to have told it you, and I am in great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, fearing leſt <hi>Zayde</hi> ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed at it.</p>
               <p>There was ſomething ſo natural, in what <hi>Felime</hi> ſaid, that ſhe believed it had wrought ſome part of the effect, at which ſhe aimed: Nevertheleſs, her Surprize was ſo great, and the words ſhe had Spoken
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:53855:82"/>were ſo remarkable, that excepting the trouble in which ſhe ſaw the Prince of <hi>Thar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> ſhe could not flatter her ſelf with the hope that her words had not laid open her own thoughts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oſmin,</hi> who came to them juſt then, interrupted their diſcourſe: <hi>Felime</hi> preſſed by her ſighs and her tears, which ſhe could not contain, walked into the wood to hide her grief, and eaſe her mind by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her moan, to one in whom ſhe had an intire confidence. The Princeſs <hi>Belleny</hi> her Mother order'd her to be call'd back, that they might return to <hi>Oropeſe,</hi> ſhe durſt not look upon <hi>Alamire,</hi> for fear of ſeeing in his eyes too much grief for what ſhe had told him of <hi>Zayde,</hi> or to much knowledge of what ſhe had ſaid of her ſelf: She ſaw notwithſtanding that he went towards the Camp, and it was ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to her to think, that he did not go to viſit <hi>Zayde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King could not forbear interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Don <hi>Olmond</hi> in this place; I do not wonder now, ſaid he, to <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> at the ſadneſs in which you ſaw <hi>Alamire,</hi> when you met him after his leaving <hi>Felime:</hi> It was to her, that the Trooper ſaw him ſpeak in the Wood; what ſhe ſaid to him, was the cauſe he knew you: And we
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:53855:83"/>now underſtand the meaning of thoſe words, which he ſpoke to you, when he drew his Sword at you, and which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to you then ſo obſcure; and gave us ſo much Curioſity to know what they meant; <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> made no anſwer, and Don <hi>Olmond</hi> followed the thred of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>It is not hard to judge how <hi>Felime</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that Night, and into how many ſorts of Afflictions her mind was divided. She ſaw that ſhe had betrayed <hi>Zayde;</hi> and ſhe feared, that ſhe had put <hi>Alamire</hi> into Deſpair: And, in ſpite of her jealouſie ſhe was troubled, that ſhe had made him ſo Unhappy: Notwithſtanding, ſhe wiſhed he might know that <hi>Zayde</hi> was ingaged in her inclinations to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſhe apprehended, that ſhe had too well diſwaded him from the Opinion ſhe gave him of it: But above all, ſhe fear'd that ſhe had to much diſcover'd her own Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for him. The next day, a new Affliction blotted out all the reſt: She heard of the Combat that was betwixt <hi>Alamire</hi> and <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi> and, her whole Mind was taken up with the fear of loſing him: She ſent every day to the Caſtle, where he lay, to know how he did? and when ſhe began to have ſome hopes of his Recovery, ſhe
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:53855:83"/>heard what the King had ordered about his Life, to Revenge the Prince of <hi>Gallicia's</hi> Death. You ſaw the Letter which ſhe writ to me the laſt Day, to oblige me to labour for his Preſervation. I told her what <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> had done at her Requeſt: And <hi>I</hi> have nothing more to tell you, but that <hi>I</hi> never ſaw in one and the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo much Love, ſo much Diſcretion, and ſo much Grief.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Olmond</hi> thus ended his Relation; during which, <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> felt an inexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Pleaſure: To know, that he was beloved of <hi>Zayde;</hi> to find Marks of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in all that he took for Marks of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference, was an Exceſs of Happyneſs, which tranſported him beyond Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and made him taſte in one moment, all the Pleaſures, which other Lovers taſte only by fits. The King was going to tell Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> that <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was <hi>Theodorick,</hi> when word was brought him, That the Deputies who came to treat of Peace, deſired Audienco. He left thoſe two Friends toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and Don <hi>Olmond</hi> taking up the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>I</hi> might with Juſtice complain, ſaid he, that <hi>I</hi> owe the Knowledge who <hi>Theodoric</hi> was, only to my ſelf, ſince our Friendſhip might claim that Knowledge from you. I wonder how you could believe, it could
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:53855:84"/>be poſſible for you to conceal it from me, while you ſhewed ſo much Curioſity to know all that might concern <hi>Zayde. I</hi> know, you loved her the firſt Day you ſpoke to me of her: And <hi>I</hi> could not well believe, that the firſt ſight could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in you ſo violent a Paſſion, as to me it appeared by what <hi>Felime</hi> told me; ſince <hi>I</hi> was ſure, that the Man (ſuch as ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed <hi>Theodorick</hi>) could be no other but <hi>Gonſalvo. I</hi> had no other way to Revenge the Secret you kept from me, but by the Note which <hi>I</hi> writ to you, with an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to give you ſome Diſquiet: My Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge is over; and the Pleaſure <hi>I</hi> gave you by my Relation, makes me forget all that could diſpleaſe me. But, added he, <hi>I</hi> will not let you take more Pleaſure than you ought; for, I muſt tell you, That unleſs you have produced a great Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Zaydes</hi> Heart, ſhe is reſolved to reſiſt the Inclination ſhe has for you, to obey her Father's Commands and Will.</p>
               <p>The Certainty of being beloved, inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him with ſo violent a Deſire to ſee that Princeſs, that he beg'd Leave of the King to go to <hi>Talavera:</hi> Don <hi>Garcias</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly granted his Requeſt; and <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> parted full of Hopes, to be confirmed, at leaſt, (by the fair Ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of <hi>Zayde</hi>) in the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:53855:84"/>Truth of all that he had heard from Don <hi>Olmond.</hi> He heard at his Arrival to the Caſtle, that <hi>Zulema</hi> was indiſpoſed. <hi>Zayde</hi> came to receive him at the Entry of her Father's Appartment; and told him, The Trouble her Father was in, that he was not in a Condition to ſee him. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was ſo ſurprized, and ſo dazled at the Charming Beauty of that Princeſs, that he ſtood ſtock ſtill, and could not forbear ſhewing his Amazement: She took notice of it, and bluſhed; and remained in ſuch a Surprize of Modeſty, that it added a new Luſtre to her Beauty. He led her to her Lodgings, and ſpoke to her of his Love with more Aſſurance, than he had done in his firſt Converſation: But, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhe anſwer'd him with a Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reſervedneſs, which would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal from him how her Heart was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined towards him, if he had not learned it from Don <hi>Olmond;</hi> he reſolved to let her underſtand, that he knew ſome part of her Inclinations.</p>
               <p>Will you never tell me, Madam, ſaid he, The Reaſon that made you wiſh, <hi>I</hi> were the Man whom <hi>I</hi> reſembled? Do not you know, ſaid ſhe, that it is a Secret which <hi>I</hi> cannot reveal? Is it poſſible, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, replyed he, looking ſtedfaſtly upon
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:53855:85"/>her, That the Paſſion <hi>I</hi> have for you, and the Obſtacles you ſee to my Happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will not induce you to have ſome pity of me, and to let me ſee (at leaſt) that you wiſh my Deſtiny were more Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: It is only this poor Wiſh of my Happineſs, that you conceal from me with ſo much Induſtry. Ah, Madam! Do you think it too much for a Man, that has Adored you from the firſt moment that ever he ſaw you, to prefer him only in Wiſh, to ſome <hi>Affrican</hi> whom you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw? <hi>Zayde</hi> was ſo ſurprized with what <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> ſaid, that ſhe could not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Be not amazed, Madam, ſaid he, (fearing ſhe ſhould accuſe <hi>Felime</hi> for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering her Thoughts); be not troubled, that Chance hath informed me what <hi>I</hi> have now told you: <hi>I</hi> heard you in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Night before you parted from <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſa;</hi> and <hi>I</hi> knew from your ſelf, what you have the Cruelty to conceal from me. How <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> cryed <hi>Zayde!</hi> You heard me in the Garden at <hi>Tortoſa?</hi> Were you ſo near me, and would not ſpeak to me? Ah, Madam, anſwered <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> (caſting himſelf at her Feet!) What a Joy you give me by this Reproach? and, How glad <hi>I</hi> am, to ſee you forget that <hi>I</hi> liſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you, to remember, that <hi>I</hi> did not
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:53855:85"/>ſpeak to you? Do not repent, Madam, continued he, (ſeeing her trouble that ſhe had diſcovered the Inclination of her Heart): Be not ſorry to give me ſome Pleaſure; and give me leave to believe, that <hi>I</hi> am not altogether indifferent to you. But to vindicate my ſelf from that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, <hi>I</hi> muſt tell you, Madam; That <hi>I</hi> over-heard you at <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> without knowing that it was you: And that my Imagination was ſo fill'd with the Opinion, that we were ſeparated by the Seas; that, although <hi>I</hi> heard your Voice, being in the Night, and could not ſee you, and that you ſpoke <hi>Spaniſh, I</hi> could never imagine, that <hi>I</hi> was ſo near you: <hi>I</hi> ſaw you the next Day in a Barge; But, when <hi>I</hi> ſaw you, and knew you, <hi>I</hi> was no longer in a Condition to ſpeak to you; being then in the Cuſtody of thoſe the King ſent to find me out. Since you over-heard me, anſwered <hi>Zayde,</hi> it is but a Folly to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, to give another Conſtruction to my Words: But, <hi>I</hi> beſeech you, to ask me no more Queſtions; and to give me leave, to go from you: For, <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs, that the Shame <hi>I</hi> have of what you have heard unknown to me, and of what <hi>I</hi> have unadviſedly ſaid to you, puts me into ſuch a Confuſion, that <hi>I</hi> muſt beg
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:53855:86"/>of you, if <hi>I</hi> have any Power over you, to be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was ſo pleaſed with what he had ſeen, that he would not preſs <hi>Zayde</hi> to make any Declaration of her Thoughts: He left her as ſhe deſired; and came back to the Camp full of Hope, to make her ſhortly change the Reſolution ſhe had taken.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Garcias</hi> his Forces, and the Valour of <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> were ſo formidable to the <hi>Moors,</hi> that they ſubmitted to all the Articles of Peace, which the King off <hi>Leon</hi> had propoſed. The Treaty was ſigned on both Sides: And, as the <hi>Moors</hi> were to ſurrender ſome Places that were far of; it was agreed, That Don <hi>Garcias</hi> ſhould retain all the Priſoners, until every Article of the Peace were fulfilled. In the mean time, he was reſolved to ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourn for ſome time, in thoſe Cities which he had won; and therefore, went to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maras,</hi> which the <hi>Moors</hi> had ſurrendered to him. The Queen, who paſſionately loved the King, accompanyed him from the beginning of the Wars in the Field: But, during the Siege of <hi>Talavera,</hi> ſtaid at a Place that was not far off; where a ſlight Indiſpoſition held her ſtill: But, ſhe was, in a few Dayes, to come to him. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> being impatient until he ſaw
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:53855:86"/>
                  <hi>Zayde</hi> again, pray'd the King, to deſire the Queen to paſs to <hi>Talavera,</hi> under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſeeing this new Conqueſt; and bring away all the <hi>Arabian</hi> Ladies, that were there. The Queen knew the Intereſt <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> had in <hi>Zayde;</hi> and, ſhe was glad to Repair on this occaſion, in ſome meaſure, thoſe many Croſſes ſhe had cauſed him, in the Intreigue of <hi>Nugna Bella.</hi> She went to <hi>Talavera;</hi> and all the <hi>Arabian</hi> Ladies readily conſented, to paſs all the time they were to ſtay in <hi>Spain,</hi> in the Queens Court. <hi>Zulema,</hi> who remain'd Priſoner at <hi>Talavera,</hi> was not ſo willing to conſent, that <hi>Zayde</hi> ſhould leave him; and the Rank which he alwayes held made him ſee with ſome Trouble, that his Daughter muſt be obliged to follow the Queen, as well as the reſt of the <hi>Arabian</hi> Ladies: He conſented to it, nevertheleſs; and <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> received the joyful News, that he ſhould ſoon ſee that admirable Beauty, which made him ſo much in Love. The Day that the Queen was to come, the King went two Leagues to meet her: She was on Horſe-back, with all the Ladies of her Train. As ſoon as ſhe came near him, ſhe preſented <hi>Zayde</hi> to him, whoſe Beauty was increaſed by the care ſhe took in her Dreſſing; inſpired there-to, by
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:53855:87"/>her Deſire to appear to <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> with all her Charms about her: Her graceful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, her compleat Wit, and her modeſt Behaviour, ſurprized all that ſaw her. She was treated as a Perſon of her Birth, Merit, and Beauty, deſerved: And ſhe ſaw her ſelf, in a few Dayes, the Delight, and the Admiration of all the Court of <hi>Leon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> could not look upon her with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Tranſports of joy; and the Aſſurance he had, that ſhe loved him, would not let him think of the Obſtacles which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his Happineſs: If he loved her formerly, onely for the Charmes of her Beauty, the Knowledge of her Vertue made him now adore her. He watched all opportunities of ſpeaking to her in private, with as much Induſtry, as ſhe uſed to avoid them: At laſt, having found her one Night in the Queens Cloſer, where there were but few beſides; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured her with ſo much Earneſtneſs and Reſpect, to tell him, how ſhe was diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed towards him, that ſhe could not deny him.</p>
               <p>If it had been poſſible for me, ſaid ſhe, to hide it from you, I would do it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the eſteem I have for you; and I would ſpare my ſelf the ſhame of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:53855:87"/>ſhewing an Inclination for a man, for whom I am not deſtin'd; But, ſince you have known my thoughts againſt my will, <hi>I</hi> willingly own them to you, and will explicate to you ſome Paſſages, of which you could have but an obſcure Knowledge. Then ſhe told him all thoſe things which he had already heard by Don <hi>Olmond,</hi> Concerning <hi>Albumazar's</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, and the Reſolutions of <hi>Zulema:</hi> You ſee, added ſhe, That all <hi>I</hi> can do, is to pitty you, and bemoan my ſelf. You are too full of Reaſon to expect, or ask me, not to follow my Fathers will. At leaſt Madam, ſaid he, let me flatter my ſelf, that if he were capable of Changing his Reſolution, you would not oppoſe in <hi>I</hi> cannot tell you whether <hi>I</hi> ſhould oppoſe it or no, anſwered ſhe. But <hi>I</hi> believe, I ought to do it, becauſe all the Happineſs of my life depends upon it. If you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, Madam, replied <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> that you ſhould be unhappy in making me happy, you have reaſon to continue the Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you have taken: But <hi>I</hi> dare tell you, that if you continued in that opinion, which you would have me flatter my ſelf with, you have nothing could induce you to believe, that it were poſſible for you to be unhappy. You are deceived, Madam,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:53855:88"/>when you imagin that you have ſome little kindneſs for me; and I was miſtaken too, when <hi>I</hi> fancied at <hi>Alphonſes</hi> houſe, that you were diſpoſed to be favourable to me. Let us ſay no more, replied <hi>Zayde,</hi> of what we might believe of one another, during our aboad in that ſolitude: And do not make me remember all that might perſwade me, that your mind was taken up with other affliction, than thoſe I might give you. I have learnt ſince <hi>I</hi> ſaw you at <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>luvera,</hi> what made you leave the Court Nor do I queſtion but that you beſtowed upon the Memory of <hi>Nugna Bella,</hi> all the time, which you did not ſpend in my company. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was Glad, that <hi>Zayde</hi> had given him occaſion, to clear all the doubts, which ſhe had of his paſſion: He laid open before her the true ſtate his Heart was in, when he firſt ſaw her: He told her moreover, what he ſuffered for not being able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand her, and all that he thought of her affliction: And yet <hi>I</hi> was not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſtaken Madam, added he, when <hi>I</hi> believed <hi>I</hi> had a Rivall: And <hi>I</hi> have been informed ſince of the paſſion the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> had for you. It's true Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Zayde,</hi> that <hi>Alamire</hi> has profeſſed a paſſion for me: And that my Father in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:53855:88"/>to give me to him, before the ſaw that Picture, which he keeps with an extraordinary care; So fully he is perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that my Happineſſe depends upon marrying the man, for whom it was drawn. Well Madam, ſaid <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> you are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved then, to conſent to it, and to beſtow your ſelf upon the man that you ſhall and like me. If it be true, that you have no Averſion for me, you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that you will have none for him: So that the aſſurance <hi>I</hi> bove, that <hi>I</hi> am not diſpleaſing to you, is to me a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Argumend, that you will without any Reluctancy Marry my Rivall. It is a kind of Misfortune which no man, but my ſelf has ever met with. And <hi>I</hi> know not why the condition, <hi>I</hi> am in ſhould not move your pity. Do not complain of me, ſaid ſhe; but rather, that you have been born a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> Although <hi>I</hi> ſhould be to you, what you would deſire, and that my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were not prepoſſeſſed, your Country would ſtill be an invincible obſtacle againſt your wiſhes. And <hi>Zulema</hi> would never conſent that <hi>I</hi> ſhould Marry you. Give me leave at leaſt. Madam, applied <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> to acquaint him with my intenſions. The Averſion you ſhewed for <hi>Alamire,</hi> ought to put him out of hope of making you mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:53855:89"/>a man of his Religion: It may be, he is not ſo tyed to <hi>Albumazar's</hi> words as you think: In fine Madam, Give me leave to try alwayes, by which <hi>I</hi> may Arrive to a happineſſe, without which it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for me to live. <hi>I</hi> conſent to what you deſire, anſwered <hi>Zayde;</hi> nay, and <hi>I</hi> would have you believe too, that <hi>I</hi> fear all your endeavours will prove unſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> went away preſently to the King, to beſeech him to aſſiſt him to ſound <hi>Zulema</hi>'s thoughts, and to try to make him approve of his deſigne. They concluded to Charge Don <hi>Olmond</hi> with this Commiſſion; whoſe addreſs, and Friendſhip for <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> ſeemed more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than any other, to ſucceed in this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair. The King writ by him to <hi>Zulema:</hi> And requeſted <hi>Zayde</hi> for <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> with the ſame Application, as if he demanded her for himſelf. Don <hi>Olmonds</hi> journey, and Don <hi>Garcias</hi> his Letter, were in vain. <hi>Zulema</hi> made anſwer, that the King Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured him too much, who having his Daughter in his poſſeſſion, might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of her: But that by his confent, ſhe ſhould never Marry a man, that was of a contrary Opinion to his own. This anſwer gave <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> all the affliction he
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:53855:89"/>could bear: Being beloved of <hi>Zayde,</hi> he would not acquaint her with the illneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fearing leſt that the certainty of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver being his, would make her Change the intentions ſhe had for him: He told her only, that he did not deſpair of gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Zulemas</hi> conſent, and obtaining of him what he ſo earneſtly deſired.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs <hi>Belleny, Felimes</hi> Mother, who was left Sick at <hi>Oropeſe,</hi> died a litle after the Peace had been concluded. <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nin</hi> was ſent to <hi>Talavera,</hi> to be with <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lema,</hi> until the expiration of the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed, for the releaſing of the Priſoners; and <hi>Pelime</hi> was conducted to the Court: She had all her wonted Charmes about her. The affliction of her mind had ſo Macerated her Body, that her Beauty was impaired by it; but it was not hard to perceive, that her indiſpoſition of health, had cauſed this alteration. This Princeſs was much ſurpriſed, to find, that the ſame <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> whom ſhe believed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have known before, and whoſe Name ſhe could not hear without Horror; for, the Wounds he gave to the Prince of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> was the ſame <hi>Theodoric,</hi> that ſhe had ſeen at <hi>Alphonſo's</hi> Houſe, and that found the way to pleaſe <hi>Zayde.</hi> Her Afflictions were increaſed,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:53855:90"/>when ſhe reflected, that what ſhe ſaid to <hi>Alamire</hi> in the Woods of <hi>Oropeſe,</hi> made him know <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> for his Rival, and was the occaſion of their Combat.</p>
               <p>That Prince was carried to <hi>Almaras;</hi> ſhe had the ſatifaction to hear from him eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day; and the conſolation, not to be oblig'd to hide her Affliction, which was attributed to the Death of her Mother. <hi>Alamire,</hi> whoſe Youth for a time ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Life, was at laſt reduced to that extremity of weakneſs, that the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans began to deſpair of his Recovery. <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime</hi> was with <hi>Zayde</hi> and <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> when word was brought them, that one of that unfortunate Princes Gentlemen deſired to ſpeak with <hi>Zayde:</hi> She bluſhed, and after remaining ſome time in a confuſion, ſhe cauſed him to be brought in, and asked aloud, what the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Madam, ſaid he, my Maſter is upon the point of Death, and he beggs, he may have the Honor, to ſee you before he Dies: He hopes the Condition he is in, will not let you refuſe him this Favor. <hi>Zayde</hi> was troubled and ſurprized at the Gentlemans Requeſt; ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſome time without anſwering: At laſt, turning her Eyes towards <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo,</hi> as if it were to know of him
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:53855:90"/>what he would have her do: But ſeeing he ſaid nothing, and judging by his Countenance, that he did not deſire ſhe ſhould ſee <hi>Alamire:</hi> I am very ſorry ſaid ſhe, to the Gentleman, that I cannot gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> in what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of me; If <hi>I</hi> thought that my preſence would contribute any thing to his Cure, <hi>I</hi> would moſt willingly ſee him; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſwaded that it will avail him nothing, <hi>I</hi> begg he will excuſe my not ſeeing him; and, <hi>I</hi> pray you to aſſure him, that <hi>I</hi> am much troubled at his weak Condition. The Gentleman went away with this Anſwer; and <hi>Felime</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained overwhelmed with Grief; of which, nevertheleſs, ſhe made no other ſhew but by her ſilence. <hi>Zayde</hi> was ſad for <hi>Felime,</hi> and ſhe had ſome pity for the wretched Deſtiny of the Prince of <hi>Thar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. Gonſalvo</hi> was divided, betwixt his joy to ſee the complaiſance <hi>Zayde</hi> had for a meaning which he had not ſo much as acquainted her with, and his Grief to have deprived that dying Prince of the ſight of the Princeſs.</p>
               <p>As all theſe perſons were thus taken up with their divers thoughts; <hi>Alamire's</hi> Gentleman returned again, and told <hi>Felime,</hi> that his Maſter deſired to ſee her: That
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:53855:91"/>there was no time to be loſt, if ſhe meant to grant him that Favor: <hi>Felime</hi> riſes from her Seat, and had no other ſigne of a liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Body, but her power to go: She gave her hand to that Gentleman, and being accompanied by her women, ſhe went to the place where <hi>Alamire</hi> lay. She placed her ſelf at his bed-ſide, and without ſaying any thing to him, ſhe remained without motion, with her eyes fixed upon him: <hi>I</hi> am Happy Madam, ſaid he to her, that the example of <hi>Zayde</hi> has not inſpired you with the ſame Cruelty, to refuſe me the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of ſeeing you; it was the only Comfort <hi>I</hi> could expect, ſince <hi>I</hi> have been depriv'd of her, to whom <hi>I</hi> took the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to pretend. <hi>I</hi> beſeech you to tell her, that ſhe had reaſon to think me unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Honor which <hi>Zulema</hi> once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended me. My Heart has been inflamed with ſo many Fires, and has been profain'd by ſo many falſe Adorations, that it did not deſerve to touch hers: But if an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy which ended at the firſt ſight of her, could be repaired by a paſſion which made me directly oppoſite to what <hi>I</hi> was before, and by a purſuit, the fulleſt of reſpect that ever was; <hi>I</hi> do believe, Madam, that <hi>I</hi> had expiated all the Crimes of my Life. Aſſure her Madam, <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:53855:91"/>you, that <hi>I</hi> had for her the ſame kind of Veneration, with which the Gods are ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and that the Wounds <hi>I</hi> receiv'd from <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> are not ſo Mortal to me, as to ſee that he is beloved by her. You told me the truth in the Woods of <hi>Oropeſe,</hi> when you informed me that her Heart was ingaged. <hi>I</hi> believed it too true, though <hi>I</hi> told you at firſt <hi>I</hi> did not; <hi>I</hi> juſt parted from you, full of the <hi>Idea</hi> of the happy <hi>Spaniard.</hi> When <hi>I</hi> met <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> his reſemblance to the Pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure which <hi>I</hi> had ſeen, and what you had then told me, ſtruck me of a ſuddain, ſo that <hi>I</hi> made no doubt, but that he was the Man of whom you ſpoke. <hi>I</hi> gave him to underſtand that <hi>I</hi> was <hi>Alamire;</hi> he fell upon me with that Animoſity, as if he had known me for his Rival. <hi>I</hi> have been told ſince, that <hi>I</hi> was not miſtaken, when <hi>I</hi> took him for the Man, that had the luck to pleaſe <hi>Zayde.</hi> He deſerves her Love, <hi>I</hi> envy his Happineſs, without thinking him unworthy of her: <hi>I</hi> Dye oppreſſed with my misfortunes, without murmuring; and if I durſt, I would only complain of <hi>Zaydes</hi> inhumanity, in depriving a Man of her ſight, that is going to loſe her for Ever. It is eaſie to judge, how many mortal Arrowes pierced the Sould of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime</hi> at theſe words of <hi>Alamire.</hi> She en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:53855:92"/>once or twice to ſpeak; but her Sighs and her Tears obſtructed her Speech. At laſt, with a Voice interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Sighs, and precipitated by a Paſſion, which ſhe could no longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; Believe me, ſaid ſhe, That if I had been in <hi>Zaydes</hi> place, no Man ſhould be preferred before the Prince of <hi>Tharſus.</hi> In ſpight of his Grief, he was ſenſible of the force of theſe Words; and ſhe turned her Head aſide, to hide the abundance of her Tears, and to avoid the Eyes of <hi>Alamire.</hi> Alas, Madam, replyed this dying Prince! Can it poſſible be, that what you have let me ſee, can be true? I muſt confeſs, that the Day you ſpoke to me in the Woods, I believed ſome part of what I now dare believe: But, I was ſo full of trouble, and you ſo dexterouſly turned the Meaning of your Words, that I retained but a very ſlight Impreſſion of it. Pardon me, Madam, that I dare think it; and, pardon me, for creating a Misfortune, which has been more grievous to my ſelf, than to you. I did not deſire to be Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; I had been too too Fortunate, if—</p>
               <p>A ſuddain Fainting hindred him from proceeding; He loſt the uſe of his Speech: And, turning his Eyes towards <hi>Felime,</hi> as if he meant to bid her Adieu, he cloſed
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:53855:92"/>them for ever, and dyed that very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Felimes</hi> Tears ſtopped; ſhe is drowned in Sorrow: She looks upon this dying Prince with her Eyes fixt in her Head, and without motion. Her Women, ſeeing that ſhe did not offer to ſtir from her Seat, came and led her away from a Place, where ſhe no longer could ſee any thing but diſmal and funeſtuous Objects. She ſuffer'd her ſelf to be Conducted away, without pronouncing one Word: But, when ſhe came into her Chamber, the Sight of <hi>Zayde</hi> embitter'd her Sorrow, and gave her Strength to ſpeak. Are you now ſatisfyed, Madam, ſaid ſhe to her? <hi>Alamire</hi> is Dead! I, <hi>Alamire</hi> is Dead, continued ſhe, as if ſhe were ſpeaking to her ſelf! I ſhall never ſee him more! I have then loſt all Hopes of ever being Beloved of him! It is no longer in Love's Power, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him for me! My Eyes ſhall never meet with his! His Preſence, which ſweeten'd all my afflicting Misfortunes, is for ever vaniſh'd from my ſight. Ah, Madam, ſaid ſhe to <hi>Zayde!</hi> Is it poſſible, that any Man ſhould pleaſe you, when <hi>Alamire</hi> could not? How Cruel was your Humanity? Why would not you love him? He Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you moſt Religiouſly. What could there be wanting in him, to render him
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:53855:93"/>more Amiable? But, replyed <hi>Zayde,</hi> ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; You very well know, that I ſhould encreaſe your Sufferings, if I had loved him; and that it was the only thing in the World, which you apprehended moſt. It is true, Madam, anſwered ſhe; it is true, I was unwilling you ſhould make him ſo Happy: But, I would not have had you deprive him of Life. Alas! Why did I with ſo much Care, conceal from him the Paſſion I had for him? Perhaps, it had won upon him; happily it might have given him ſome Diverſion, from that fatal Love which he had for you. What was I afraid of? Why ſhould not he know, that my Heart Adored him? The only Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation which is left me, is, that he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſome-thing of it: Well, although he had known it, it may be, he would have diſſembled that he loved me, and ſo would have deceived me: What, if he had continued to deceive me, as he begun? Thoſe dear Moments, wherein he made me believe that he loved me, are yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to my Memory. Is it poſſible, that after ſuffering ſo many Evils, there ſhould reſt ſtill ſo great for me to endure? I hope, at leaſt, that my Grief will be ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to bereave me of Force to ſupport them.</p>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:53855:93"/>
               <p>As ſhe talked thus; <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> came to the Door of her Chamber (not thinking ſhe was there) to know in what Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhe was in, after returning from <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi>'s Apartment: He with-drew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſuddainly, that he might not irritate her grief by his Preſence: But, he could not do it ſo quickly, but that ſhe had a Glimpſe of him; and this ſight of him, made her cry out ſo mournfully, that the hardeſt Hearts could not chooſe but be moved there-at. <hi>I</hi> beſeech you, Madam, ſaid ſhe to <hi>Zayde,</hi> to give order, that <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi> comes not in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> my ſight: <hi>I</hi> cannot endure the Sight of a Man, from whoſe Hand <hi>Alamire</hi> received his Death; and who robb'd him of what was dearer to him, than his Life.</p>
               <p>The Violence of her Grief took away her Speech, and her Senſes: And her Health being already much impair'd, it was eaſie to perceive, that her Life was in danger. The King, and the Queen, being told of her Condition, came to ſee her; and ſent for all that could give her Eaſe. After five or ſix Hours lying in a kind of Lethargy, the Strength of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines which was given her, brought her to her ſelf: She knew none of the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by, but <hi>Zayde;</hi> who fate weeping by
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:53855:94"/>her, with much ſorrow. Do not lament my Loſs, ſaid ſhe, (ſo low, that ſhe could hardly be over heard); I ſhould no longer be worthy of your Friendſhp; nor could <hi>I</hi> love a Perſon that cauſed the Death of <hi>Alamire.</hi> She could ſay no more. She fell into the ſame Fainting-Fits again: And the next Day, about the ſame Hour that ſhe ſaw the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> depart, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Life, which Love had render'd ſo Unfortunate.</p>
               <p>The Death of two Perſons, of ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Merit, was ſo worthy of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, that all the Court of <hi>Leon</hi> was afflicted there-at: <hi>Zaydes</hi> Grief was inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible; She loved <hi>Felime</hi> paſſionately: and the manner of her Death, added more Sorrow to her Affliction. All <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Prayers, and his Cares, could not prevail for ſeveral Dayes with her, to moderate her Grief: But, her Apprehenſions of leaving <hi>Spain,</hi> and loſing <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> gave ſome Reſpite to her Tears, to afflict her with another ſort of Diſcontent. The King returned to <hi>Leon:</hi> And there remain'd ſo little now of what was to fulfil the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Accompliſhment of the Articles of Peace, that in all appearance, <hi>Zulema</hi> was very ſhortly to re-paſs into <hi>Africk:</hi> Yet, he was not in a condition to Travail; for,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:53855:94"/>he was dangerouſly ſick, when <hi>Felime</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the Extreamity he was reduced to, was kept from <hi>Zayde,</hi> that ſhe might not be oppreſſed with ſo many Afflictions at one and the ſame time. <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> was full of Mortal Diſquiet; and ſtudied all wayes, by which he might either induce that Prince to conſent to his Happineſs, or perſwade <hi>Zayde</hi> to ſtay in <hi>Spain</hi> with the Queen; ſince Reaſon ſeemed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with her, for not following a Father, that appeared in a Reſolution, to force her to change her Religion. Some Dayes after they came to <hi>Leon, Gonſalvo</hi> came one E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening into the Queens Cloſet; where <hi>Zayde</hi> was; but her Eyes were ſo fixt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Picture of <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s, that ſhe did not ſee him when he came in. It is decreed, Madam, ſaid he, that <hi>I</hi> muſt alwayes be jealous of Pictures; ſince <hi>I</hi> am ſo even of my own, and muſt envy the Attention you have in looking on them. What, of your Picture, anſwered <hi>Zayde,</hi> with an extream Surprize! Yes, Madam, of my Picture, replyed <hi>Gonſalvo: I</hi> ſee, you can hardly believe it, becauſe it is ſo Handſom; but <hi>I</hi> aſſure you, it was drawn for me. <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalve,</hi> ſaid ſhe, was there no other Picture drawn for you, like this? Ah, Madam, cryed he, with that kind of Trouble, which
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:53855:95"/>uncertain Joyes creates in us! May not I believe what you give cauſe to ſuſpect, and what I can ſcarce dare to tell? Yes, Madam, other Pictures like this you ſee, have been drawn for me: But, I dare not give my ſelf the Liberty to believe what I perceive you think, and what I ſhould have thought long ſince, if I had judged my ſelf worthy of thoſe Predictions which have been told you; and if you had not alwayes aſſured me, that the Picture which reſembled me, was drawn for an <hi>African.</hi> I believed ſo by the Habit, and the Words of <hi>Albumazar</hi> perſwaded me to it: You know, added ſhe, how much I deſired, that you might be the Man you reſembled: But what ſurprizes me, is, that having wiſhed it ſo much, my Pre-occupation ſhould hinder me from believing it. I ſpoke of it to <hi>Felime,</hi> the firſt time I ſaw you at <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s Houſe. When I ſaw you again at <hi>Talavera,</hi> and was informed of your Birth and Quality, this very Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation came into my Mind; but looked only upon it, as a pure Effect of my Wiſhes. But, How hard a matter will it be, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſhe, fetching a deep Sigh! to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my Father, to believe this Truth? And, how much I fear, that theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, which ſeemed true to him when
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:53855:95"/>he thought they concerned a Man of his own Perſwaſion, will ſeem falſe to him, when they relate to a <hi>Spaniard?</hi> While ſhe thus argued, the Queen came into the Cloſet; <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> made her partake of his Joy: She did not defer a moment ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting the King, with the Diſcourſe they had; and the King came that very inſtant, to know of <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained to be done, that his Happineſs might be compleated. After conſulting a good while, by what means <hi>Zulema</hi> might be won; it was agreed, he ſhould be brought to Court. A Meſſenger was in ſtantly diſpatched to <hi>Talavera,</hi> to acquaint him, that the King deſired he ſhould be brought to Court; and being now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Recovered, arrived there in few Dayes. The King received him with great Demonſtrations of Eſteem, and led him into his Cloſet. You would not grant me <hi>Zayde,</hi> ſayes he, for the Man of the World I conſider the moſt; but, I hope, you will not refuſe her to him, whoſe Picture you ſee here; and to whom, I know, ſhe is deſtined by the Predictions of <hi>Albumazar.</hi> At this, he ſhewed him <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Picture, and preſented to him <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> himſelf, who was with-drawn from them a little. <hi>Zulema</hi> looks now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:53855:96"/>the Picture, and then upon <hi>Gonſalvo;</hi> and ſeemed to be in a deep Study: The King believed, that his Silence proceeded from his Uncertainty. If you are not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, ſaid he, by the Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, that this is <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Picture; you ſhall have ſo many other Proofs, that you ſhall have no cauſe to doubt of it: The Picture you have, which is like this, could not fall into your Hands, but ſince the Battle which <hi>Nugnes Fernando</hi> (<hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvo</hi>'s Father) loſt againſt the <hi>Moors:</hi> He cauſed it to be drawn by an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Painter, who had Travel'd over moſt Parts of the World: He took ſuch a liking to the <hi>African</hi> Garb, that he drew all his Pictures in that Habi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. It is true, Sir, replyed <hi>Zulema,</hi> that I have that Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but ſince the time you ſpeak of: It is true likewiſe, becauſe you do me the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to ſay it and the Reſemblance makes it out; that I cannot doubt, but that it is <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Picture: But that is not the Cauſe of my Silence, or Aſtoniſhment. I admire the Decrees of Heaven, and the Effects of the Almighties Providence. There has been no Predictions made to me, Sir: The Words of <hi>Albumazar,</hi> of which I perceive, you heard ſpeak, were taken by my Daughter in another Senſe
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:53855:96"/>than they ſhould be. But, ſince you have the Goodneſs to be concerned for my Daughters Fortune, give me leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, what you cannot know but from me; and to ſhew you the beginning of a Life, which you alone can make Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</p>
               <p>The juſt Pretenſions my Father had to the Empire of the <hi>Caliphe,</hi> occaſioned his Baniſhment into <hi>Cyprus;</hi> whither I went along with him: There I fell in love with <hi>Alaſinthe,</hi> and Marryed her: She was a Chriſtian; I reſolved to embrace her Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion; becauſe it was the only way, that ſeemed to me fit to be lived in: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, the Auſterities of it, frighted me, and ſtopped the Execution of my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne. I went back into <hi>Africk:</hi> The Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and the Corruption of Manners, re-ingaged me more than ever, in my own Religion, and gave me a freſh Averſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſtians. I forgot <hi>Alaſinthe</hi> for many Years: But, at laſt. I had a deſire to ſee her, and <hi>Zayde,</hi> which I had left an Infant: I reſolved to go into: <hi>Cyprus</hi> to fetch her away, and to make her change her Religion; and Marry her to the Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Idris.</hi> He had heard of her, and earneſtly deſired to have her. His Father had a particular
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:53855:97"/>Friendſhip for me. The Wars that were then begun in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> made me haſten my Deſigne: When I arrived there, I found the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> in love with <hi>Zayde:</hi> I thought him very Deſerving. I did not queſtion, but that ſhe had an Inclination for him: I believed, my Daughter would have been eaſily perſwaded to Marry him: Nor was I wholly Engaged to the Prince of <hi>Fez.</hi> Her Mother being a Chriſtian, I feared ſhe would be an Obſtacle to the Deſigne I had, to make <hi>Zayde</hi> change her Religion. I gave my conſent to <hi>Alamire</hi>'s Pretentions: But was ſurprized, to find the Averſion ſhe ſhewed to him. And, during the Siege at <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> all my En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours could not prevail with her, to Marry him. I thought not fit, to preſs her too much, to conquer an Averſion which ſeemed Natural in her; but, reſolved to Marry her to the Prince of <hi>Fez,</hi> ſo ſoon as we ſhould be Landed in <hi>Africk.</hi> He writ to me ſince my Arrival in <hi>Cyprus;</hi> by which I underſtood, that his Mother was Dead: So that, I ſaw no Obſtacle to this Marriage. We left <hi>Famagoſta;</hi> we landed at <hi>Alexandria;</hi> where I found <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bumazar,</hi> with whom I had been long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted. He took notice, that my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter looked earneſtly upon a Picture, which
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:53855:97"/>I had, that was like this I ſee. The next Day, as I was ſpeaking to this Learned Man, of the Averſion ſhe had for <hi>Alamire;</hi> I told him my Intention to Marry her to the Prince of <hi>Fez,</hi> whether ſhe ſhould like him or not.</p>
               <p>I doubt, anſwered <hi>Albumazar,</hi> whether ſhe will have any Diſlike to his Perſon; for this Picture, which ſo much pleaſes her, is ſo like that Prince, that I believe, it was drawn for him. I cannot judge, ſaid I, becauſe I never ſaw him: It is not impoſſible, but that it may be his Picture: Nor do I know, for whom it was drawn; for, it came into my Hands, by Chance. I wiſh, that Prince may pleaſe <hi>Zayde:</hi> But, if ſhe ſhould diſlike him, I ſhould not have the ſame Complaiſance for her, as I had upon the Prince of <hi>Tharſus</hi> his account. Some dayes after, my Daughter prayed <hi>Albumazar</hi> to tell her ſomething of her Fortune: As he knew my Intentions; and did believe, that the Picture which ſhe ſaw, was made for the Prince of <hi>Fez;</hi> he told her, without any Deſigne, That his Words ſhould be taken for a Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; That ſhe was deſtin'd for him whoſe Picture ſhe had ſeen. I ſeemed to believe, that <hi>Albumazar</hi> ſpoke by a particular Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:53855:98"/>he had of Things to come. I ſtill appeared to <hi>Zayde,</hi> to be of the ſame Opinion. When I left <hi>Alexandria, Albu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazar</hi> aſſured me, that I ſhould never ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the Deſignes I had for her: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, I could not loſe my Hopes of bringing them to paſs. During my late Sickneſs, the Deſigne I had formerly of embracing the True Religion, came ſo ſtrongly into my Fancy, that ſince my Recovery, all my Thoughts have been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about fortifying my ſelf in this Reſolution; yet, I confeſs, that this Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reſolution was not yet ſo ſtrong, as it ought to be: But, now I muſt yield to what Heaven is working in my favor. It leads me by the ſame wayes, which I meant to follow, in making my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter marry a Man of my own Perſwaſion, to marry her to one of her Religion. The Words which <hi>Albumazar</hi> ſpoke without Deſigne, only upon a Reſemblance, in which he was miſtaken, proves a true Prediction; and this Prediction is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in every part, by the Happineſs which my Daughter will have, in marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Man, that is the Admiration and Wonder of his time. I have nothing more to ſay, but to beg of you, Sir, To receive
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:53855:98"/>me among the Number of your Subjects; and, To permit me, to end my Dayes in your Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The King and <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> were ſo ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and over-joyed with <hi>Zulema</hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that they Embraced him without replying; being not able to find Words of a ſuddain, to expreſs their ſatisfaction. At laſt, after having declared their Joy, they ſtood a great while, admiring the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of ſo ſtrange an Adventure: Yet <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> no way admired, that <hi>Albu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazar</hi> ſhould be miſtaken in his Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to the Prince of <hi>Fez;</hi> he knew, that others had been deceived in it, as well as he: He told <hi>Zulema,</hi> That the Prince of <hi>Fez</hi> his Mother, was Siſter to <hi>Nugnes Fernando,</hi> his own Father; and that, being taken away in an Invaſion which the <hi>Moors</hi> made, ſhe was carryed into <hi>Africk;</hi> where her Beauty made her Legitimate Wife to the Father of this Prince of <hi>Fez.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zulema</hi> went to acquaint his Daughter with what had paſſed; and it was eaſy for him to perceive by her manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this News, that ſhe was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:53855:99"/>of <hi>Gonſalvo</hi>'s Merit: Some few Dayes after, <hi>Zulema</hi> made publick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith.</hi> Nothing now was thought on, but the Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this Marriage; which was ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized with all the Gallantry of the <hi>Moors,</hi> and the Politeneſs of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53855:99"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
